<text>Hieroglyphics
    
      By
    
      Arthur Machen
    
      Author of "The Great God Pan," etc.
    
      London
      Grant Richards
      1902
    
    
    
    
        TABLE OF CONTENTS
    
                        Page
        NOTE              v
        I                 1
        II               42
        III              68
        IV               99
        V               125
        VI              150
        APPENDIX        171
    
    
    
    
    NOTE
    
    
    It was my privilege, many years ago, to make the acquaintance of the
    obscure literary hermit, whose talk I have tried to reproduce in the
    pages that follow. Our first meeting was one of those chance affairs
    that now and then mitigate the loneliness of the London streets, and a
    second hazard led to the discovery that we had many interests in common.
    I think that the Hermit (as I shall call him) had begun to find the
    perpetual solitude of his years a growing terror, and he was not sorry
    to have a listener; at first, indeed, he talked almost with the joy of a
    child, or rather of a prisoner who has escaped from the house of
    silence, but as he chose subjects which have always interested me
    intensely, he gave as much pleasure as he received, and I became an
    assiduous visitor of his cell.
    
    He had found an odd retreat. He avoided personalities, and had a happy
    knack of forgetting any that I vouchsafed on my side, (he forgot my name
    three times on the first evening that we spent together, and succeeded
    in repeating this feat over and over again since then), and I never
    gathered much of his past history. But I believe that "something had
    happened" many years before, in the prehistoric age of the 'seventies.
    There had been a break of some sort in the man's life when he was quite
    young; and so he had left the world and gone to Barnsbury, an almost
    mythical region lying between Pentonville and the Caledonian Road. Here,
    in the most retired street of that retired quarter, he occupied two
    rooms on the ground floor of a big, mouldy house, standing apart from
    the street and sheltered by gaunt grown trees and ancient shrubs; and
    just beside the dim and dusty window of the sitting-room a laburnum had
    cast a green stain on the decaying wall. The laburnum had grown wild,
    like all the trees and shrubs, and some of its black, straggling boughs
    brushed the pane, and of dark, windy nights while we sat together and
    talked of art and life we would be startled by the sudden violence with
    which those branches beat angrily upon the glass.
    
    The room seemed always dark. I suppose that the house had been built in
    the early eighteenth century, and had been altered and added to at
    various periods, with a final "doing up" for the comparative luxury of
    someone in the 'tens or 'twenties; there were, I think, twenty rooms in
    it, and my friend used to declare that when a new servant came she spent
    many months in finding her way in the complicated maze of stairs and
    passages, and that the landlady even was now and then at fault. But the
    room in which we sat was hung with flock paper, of a deep and heavy
    crimson colour, and even on bright summer evenings the crimson looked
    almost black, and seemed to cast a shadow into the room. Often we sat
    there till the veritable darkness came, and each could scarcely see the
    white of the other's face, and then my friend would light two lonely
    candles on the mantelpiece, or if he wished to read he set one on a
    table beside him; and when the candles were lighted I thought that the
    gloom grew more intense, and looking through the uncurtained window one
    could not see even the friendly twinkle of the gas-lamp in the street,
    but only the vague growth of the laburnum, and the tangle of boughs
    beyond.
    
    It was a large room and gave me always a sense of empty space. Against
    one wall stood a heavy bookcase, with glass doors, solid and of dark
    mahogany, but made in the intermediate period that came between
    Chippendale and the modern school of machine-turned rubbish. In the
    duskiest corner of the room there was a secretaire of better
    workmanship, and two small tables and three gaunt chairs made up the
    furnishing. The Hermit would sometimes pace up and down in the void
    centre of the room as he talked, and if I chanced to be sitting by the
    window, his shape would almost disappear as he neared the secretaire on
    his march, and I heard the voice, and used to wonder for a moment
    whether the man had not vanished for ever, having been resolved into the
    shadows about him.
    
    I have spent many evenings in that old mouldering room, where, when we
    were silent for an instant, the inanimate matter about us found a voice,
    and the decaying beams murmured together, and a vague sound might come
    from the cellars underneath. And it always seemed to me as if the
    crypt-like odour of the cellar rose also into the room, mingling with a
    faint suggestion of incense, though I am sure that my friend never
    burned it. Here then, with such surroundings as I have indicated, we
    held our sessions and talked freely and with enjoyment of many curious
    things, which, as the Hermit would say, had the huge merit of
    interesting no one but ourselves.
    
    He would sometimes, whimsically, compare himself to Coleridge, and I
    think that he often deliberately talked in S. T. C.'s manner with
    delight in the joke. For, I need hardly say that the comparison was not
    in any way a serious one; he had a veneration for Coleridge's
    achievement, with a still greater veneration for that which Coleridge
    might have achieved, which would have caused him to regard any such
    comparison, seriously entertained, as unspeakably ludicrous. Still, he
    liked to regard himself as a very humble disciple in Coleridge's school,
    he was fond, as I have said, of imitating his master's manner as well as
    he could, and I think that he cherished, in the fashion of S. T. C., the
    notion that he had a "system," an esoteric philosophy of things; he
    sought for a key that would open, and a lamp that would enlighten all
    the dark treasure-houses of the Universe, and sometimes he believed that
    he held both the Key and the Lamp in his hands.
    
    It is a confession of mysticism, but I incline to think that he was
    right in this belief. I recall the presence of that hollow, echoing
    room, the atmosphere with its subtle suggestion of incense sweetening
    the dank odours of the cellar, and the tone of the voice speaking to me,
    and I believe that once or twice we both saw visions, and some glimpse
    at least of certain eternal, ineffable Shapes. But these matters, the
    more esoteric doctrines of "the system" have entered hardly or not at
    all into the very imperfect and fragmentary notes that I have made of
    his conversations on literature.
    
    I should scarcely be justified in calling him a literary monomaniac. But
    it is true that Art in general, and the art of literature in particular
    had for him a very high significance and interest; and he was always
    ready to defend the thesis that, all the arts being glorious, the
    literary art was the most glorious and wonderful of all. He reverenced
    music, but he was firm in maintaining that in perfect lyrical poetry
    there is the subtlest and most beautiful melody in the world.
    
    I can scarcely say whether he wrote much himself. He would speak of
    stories on which he was engaged, but I have never seen his name on
    publishers' lists, and I do not think that he had adopted a pseudonym.
    One evening, I remember, I came in a little before my accustomed time,
    and in the shadowy corner of the room, a drawer in the secretaire was
    open, and I thought that it looked full of neat manuscripts. But I never
    spoke to him about his literary work; and I noticed that he did not much
    care to talk of literature from the commercial standpoint.
    
    It is perhaps needless to say that I consulted my friend before
    publishing these notes of his conversations. I had been forced to leave
    London for some months, and I wrote to him from the country, requesting
    his permission to give to the world (if the world would have them) those
    judgments on books which I had listened to in Barnsbury. His reply
    allowed me to take my own way, "with all my heart, so long as you make
    me sufficiently apocryphal. I am not going to compete with 'real'
    critics whose names are printed in the papers; but if you can maintain
    the _incognito_ and allow your readers (supposing their existence) to
    believe that I am a mere figment of your brain, you can print my _obiter
    dicta_ 'with ease of body and rest of reins.' Here is a suggestion for a
    title: what do you say to 'Boswell in Barnsbury'? But I really had no
    notion that you were taking notes all the time. Remember: keep the
    secret, _and the secrets_."
    
    I regarded this as a very liberal license, and I have tried to set in
    the best order I could compass the "system" so far as it relates to
    letters. I do not pretend that I am a _verbatim_ reporter, for I had to
    trust to my memory, and though I tried to arrange my notes at the time,
    I fear I have fallen here and there into confusion. Still, I think that
    the six chapters which follow will seem fairly consecutive in their
    argument and arrangement, and the "Appendix"--a confession of
    failure--is, in reality, the result of the "cyclical mode of
    discoursing," in which the Hermit jocularly professed to follow
    Coleridge.
    
    Perhaps indeed Coleridge was deceived, and my dear friend with him, in
    the hope of real essential knowledge; but even so, these fragments which
    I propose are evidence that the latter earnestly desired the truth and
    sought it.
    
            A. M.
    
    
    
    
    HIEROGLYPHICS
    
    
    
    
    I
    
    
    Do you know that just before you came in I found something highly
    significant in the evening paper? I am afraid from your expression that
    you rather undervalue the influence of the press; indeed, I remember one
    day when we were out together you swore at an inoffensive boy who tried
    to allure us with news of all the winners. I think I pointed out at the
    time that even horse-racing and an interest in "events" are preferable
    to stagnation, and that there is something august in the universal human
    passion for gambling. And, after all, the office-boy who "puts on"
    half-a-crown is really only an example of the love of man for the
    unknown; the half-crown is a venture into mystery, with that due flavour
    of commercialism which we in England add to most of our interests. But
    you see, don't you? that gambling, even under its most sordid aspects,
    is not altogether sordid; it's the mystery, the uncertainty, the hours
    of "strange surmise" that the smallest bet gives to the bettor that
    make the real delight of betting. When the office-boy wins and gets ten
    shillings for the risk of his two-and-six, his delight is not by any
    means pure love of gain, it is distinguished by a very marked line from
    the constantly repeated joys of the grocer, who is always buying
    delicious tea at ninepence and selling it at one-and-six. Here you have
    commercialism in its simplest form; but our office-boy, though he likes
    the money well enough, stands on a much higher plane. For the moment he
    is the man who has succeeded in solving the enigma of the Sphinx, in
    discovering the unknown continent, in reading the cypher, in guessing at
    the song the Sirens sang, in unveiling the hidden treasure that the
    buccaneers buried on the lonely shore; he has ventured successfully into
    the dim region of surmises. And when he loses, there are always
    consolations; the Indies have not been discovered on this voyage,
    certainly, but there have been wonders on the way, he has enjoyed many
    hours of delicious expectation. The proof that he likes the sport, even
    when he loses, is that he invariably takes the first opportunity of
    venturing again in the same manner. And, by the way, perhaps I was a
    little severe just now on trade, and especially on the grocer's sugary
    and soapy enterprise. Perhaps if we were to look with a rather finer
    vision into the commercial spirit, we might find that it is not wholly
    commercial, not altogether sordid. Of course if the grocer opens his
    shop with a certainty, mathematical or almost mathematical, that the
    public will buy his wares, he is a wicked fellow; he is gambling with
    loaded dice, betting against a horse that he knows is to be made "all
    right," playing cards with honours up his sleeve, and I am sure that if
    this be his enterprise, it will always meet with our sternest
    disapproval. Casanova died towards the close of the last century, and
    since then cardsharping has become impossible to a man of taste. But
    seriously, I suspect that a good deal of the allurement that trade
    possesses for so many of us is the risk which it almost always implies,
    and risk means uncertainty, and uncertainty connotes the unknown. So you
    see our despised grocer turns out, after all, to be of the kin of
    Columbus, of the treasure-seekers, and mystery-mongers, and delvers
    after hidden things spiritual and material. I suppose we have here the
    real explanation of the human trading passion, and the solution of a
    problem that has often puzzled me. The problem I mean is this: how does
    it happen that the English are both the greatest poets and the greatest
    tradesmen of the modern world? Superficially, it seems that keeping
    shops and making poetry are incompatibles, and Wordsworth and Coleridge,
    Keats and Shelley, Tennyson and Poe, should have come from Provence or
    Sicily, from the "unpractical," uncommercial Latin races. But if we
    trace back the trading instinct to that love of a risk--or in other
    words to the desire for the unknown--the antinomy disappears, and it
    will become perfectly natural that the race which has gone to the
    world's end with its merchandise, has penetrated so gloriously into the
    further regions of poetry.
    
    But that reminds me of what I was saying just after you had lit your
    pipe. I think I remarked that I had seen something of very high
    significance in the evening paper, and the glare of disgust with which
    you greeted my observation constituted an interruption, and an
    interruption that had to be dealt with. Now again you seem to hint at
    doubt with your eyebrows; you would say, perhaps, that I have not made
    out a very convincing case for journalism? But you must remember that
    my mental process resembles that of Coleridge; you called on the Seer at
    eleven o'clock in the morning, and (if young and imprudent) asked him a
    question. And at the waning of the light Coleridge was still diligently
    engaged in answering your question for you, having talked without
    intermission all the summer day. A "cyclical mode of discoursing" the
    pious Henry Nelson Coleridge called it, and he deals faithfully with
    certain persons who complained "that they could get no answer to a
    question from Coleridge." And you will please to remember this when you
    think that I am "wandering"--a vice of which Coleridge also was accused.
    To-night, for example, on the evening paper being mentioned, your face
    expressed disgust and contempt, which I diagnosed (and rightly, I
    believe?) as a tribute to the enormous interest taken by the editors of
    these agreeable journals in the very latest sporting news; an interest
    which allows but little space for the discussion of pure literature.
    Hence my remarks on the gambling-spirit; and now I hope you will at
    least assume a thrill of interest when the boy bawls in your ear "All
    the winners and S. P." It is possible you may be thinking of Ulysses or
    of Keats at the moment, and the interruption may annoy you, but it will
    do so no longer when you reflect that a burning anxiety as to the
    running of Bolter is for many thousands the symbol--and the only
    possible symbol--of the Doom of Troy and the wandering fields of foam,
    and the Isle of Calypso, and the "strange surmise" of Pizarro and all
    his men.
    
    But here is the evening-paper in question. Yes, the colour is, perhaps,
    a little sickly. A kind of pinky-green, it seems, doesn't it? But it
    forced itself on my notice in the most extraordinary manner, and I
    expect you will have to admit, when you have heard the story, that some
    Powers were at work. Well, I was walking up and down the room, just as
    it was getting dusk, and every now and then I stopped and looked out of
    the window. Yes, I was making phrases as usual, and thinking of a new
    story in the middle of the old one: hence the quarter-deck exercise. I
    daresay you have remarked that I do not keep my window in a very
    brilliant condition, and the air this evening, you will remember, was
    rather misty--October, I always think, wears a peculiar dim grace in
    Barnsbury--so I hope you will not find my impressions too incredible. I
    was staring, then, out of the window, when to my vast astonishment, a
    great pale bird seemed suddenly to shoot up into the air from the road,
    and to flutter into the garden, where it became entangled in that
    sapless old laburnum that weeps green tears upon the wall. I saw, as I
    thought, the beating and fluttering of wings, and I ran out, imagining
    that I was to secure a strange companion for my solitude. It was the
    evening paper, not a bird, and I saw at once that it would be impious to
    let it flutter there unread, so I secured it and brought it in,
    meditating the adventure, and wondering what strange message was thus
    borne to my eyes. So I went through its columns patiently, even to the
    leaderettes, and I will do myself the justice to say that I at once
    recognised the communication that was addressed to me in this singular
    and even I may say Arabian fashion. It was a short comment upon some
    agitation that is now appealing rather strongly to Progressive leaders;
    but the subject-matter is of no consequence, since the significance lies
    in the last sentence. Here it is: "We are glad to hear that extensive
    arrangements have been made for the dissemination of literature."
    
    You don't see the immense importance of that? You surprise me. Let us go
    into it, then. I told you I was not very precise as to the exact scope
    of the agitation alluded to--it may be a question of a heavy tax on
    persons who will say "lady" instead of "lydy," it may be an affair of
    restricting the franchise to citizens thoroughly ignorant of history; it
    doesn't matter--but here are men who wish some political change to be
    effected, and these men are issuing printed matter, the purpose of which
    is to convince others of the righteousness of this particular "program."
    And this printed matter is called "literature." You know the sort of
    thing indicated. It may be a series of arguments, simple and fallacious,
    it may be in dialogue, it may be in story form, it may assume the guise
    of parody, it may be a brief history. And now what I want to know is
    this: here we have a vast body of thought, clothed in words, ranging
    from the agreeable leaflets that we have been speaking of up to--let us
    say--the Odyssey, and all this mass is known as literature: what is to
    be our criterion, our means of distinguishing between the two extremes
    I have mentioned and all the innumerable links between them? Is the
    whole mass literature in the true sense of the word? If not, with what
    instrument, by what rule are we to divide the true from the false, to
    judge exactly in the case of any particular book whether it is
    literature or not? Of course you may say that the question is rather
    verbal than real; that "literature" is a general term conveniently
    applied to anything in print, and that in practice everybody knows the
    difference between a political pamphlet and the Odyssey. I very much
    doubt whether people do understand precisely the distinction between the
    two, but for the avoidance of verbal confusion I suggest that when we
    mean literature in its highest sense we shall say (for the present at
    all events), "fine literature"; and the question will be, then: what is
    it that differentiates fine literature from a number of grammatical, or
    partly grammatical, sentences arranged in a more or less logical order?
    Why is the Odyssey to come in, why is the "literature" of our evening
    paper to be kept out? And again, to put the question in a more subtle
    form: to which class do the works of Jane Austen belong? Is "Pride and
    Prejudice" to stand on the Odyssey shelf, or to lie in the pamphlet
    drawer? Where is Pope's place? Is he to be set in the class of Keats? If
    not, for what reason? What is the rank of Dickens, of Thackeray, of
    George Eliot, of Hawthorne; and in a word, how are we to sort out, as it
    were, this huge multitude of names, giving to each one his proper rank
    and station?
    
    I am glad it strikes you as a big question: to me it seems _the_
    question, the question which covers the final dogma of literary
    criticism. Of course after we have answered this prerogative riddle,
    there will be other questions, almost without end, classes, and
    sub-classes of infinite analysis. But this will be detail; while the
    question I have propounded is the question of first principles; it marks
    the parting of two ways, and in a manner, it asks itself not only of
    literature, but of life, but of philosophy, but of religion. What is the
    line, then; the mark of division which is to separate spoken, or
    written, or printed thought into two great genera?
    
    Well, as you may have guessed, I have my solution, and I like it none
    the less, because the word of the enigma seems to me actually but a
    single word. Yes, for me the answer comes with the one word, _Ecstasy_.
    If ecstasy be present, then I say there is fine literature, if it be
    absent, then, in spite of all the cleverness, all the talents, all the
    workmanship and observation and dexterity you may show me, then, I
    think, we have a product (possibly a very interesting one), which is not
    fine literature.
    
    Of course you will allow me to contradict myself, or rather, to amplify
    myself before we begin to discuss the matter fully. I said my answer was
    the word, ecstasy; I still say so, but I may remark that I have chosen
    this word as the representative of many. Substitute, if you like,
    rapture, beauty, adoration, wonder, awe, mystery, sense of the unknown,
    desire for the unknown. All and each will convey what I mean; for some
    particular case one term may be more appropriate than another, but in
    every case there will be that withdrawal from the common life and the
    common consciousness which justifies my choice of "ecstasy" as the best
    symbol of my meaning. I claim, then, that here we have the touchstone
    which will infallibly separate the higher from the lower in literature,
    which will range the innumerable multitude of books in two great
    divisions, which can be applied with equal justice to a Greek drama, an
    eighteenth century novelist, and a modern poet, to an epic in twelve
    books, and to a lyric in twelve lines. I will convince you of my belief
    in my own nostrum by a bold experiment: here is _Pickwick_ and here is
    _Vanity Fair_; the one regarded as a popular "comic" book, the other as
    a serious masterpiece, showing vast insight into human character; and
    applying my test, I set _Pickwick_ beside the Odyssey, and _Vanity Fair_
    on top of the political pamphlet.
    
    I will not argue the matter at the moment; I would merely caution you
    against supposing that I imply any equality of merit in the books that I
    have thus summarily "bracketed." You mustn't suppose that I think
    Dickens's book as good as Homer's, or that I have any doubts as to the
    vast superiority of _Vanity Fair_ over all the pamphlets in the world.
    "Here is a temple, here is a tub," we may suppose a child to say,
    learning from a picture-alphabet; but the temple may be a miserably
    designed structure, in ruinous condition, and the tub is, perhaps, a
    miracle of excellent workmanship. But one means worship and the other
    means washing, and that is _the_ distinction. Or, to take a better
    example; the bottom boy in the sixth form may be a miserable dunce
    compared with the top boy in the fifth; still the dunce is in the sixth
    form, and the genius is in the fifth. Or, to take a third instance (I
    want you to understand what I'm driving at), the fact that an English
    orator is fluent, brilliant, profound, convincing, while a Greek orator
    is stuttering, stupid, shallow, illogical does not hinder that the
    former, though he may speak ever so well, still speaks English, while
    the latter, however badly he may speak, speaks in Greek for all that.
    Analogies, as you know, are never perfect, and must not be pressed too
    far; they suggest rather than prove; but I hope you understand me though
    you may not agree with me.
    
    But before we argue the merits of my own literary solvent, we might very
    well see what we can do with other tests. I daresay you can suggest a
    good many. We won't go into the question of printed and not printed,
    written or not written, because it is obvious that the visible symbols
    by which literature is recorded have nothing to do with literature
    itself. In the beginning all literature was a matter of improvisation
    or recitation and memory, and hieroglyphics, writing, printing are mere
    conveniences. Indeed the point is only worth mentioning because there
    are, I believe, simple souls who think that the invention of printing
    has some sort of mysterious connection with the birth of literature, and
    that the abolition of the paper duty was its coming of age. But I don't
    think we need trouble ourselves much about a view of literary art which
    regards the cheap press as its father and the school board as its
    nursing mother. Many people think, on the other hand, that literature is
    to be estimated by its effect on the emotions, by the shock which it
    gives to the system. You may say that a book which interests you so
    intensely that you cannot put it down, that affects you so acutely that
    you weep, that amuses you so immensely that you roar with laughter must
    be very good. I don't object to "very good," but from my point of view,
    "very good" and "fine literature" are two different things. You see
    I believe that the difference between interesting, exciting,
    tear-compelling, laughter-moving reading matter and fine art is not
    specific but generic: who would blaspheme against good bitter beer, who
    would say that _because_ it is good, it is _therefore_ Burgundy?
    
    I am not quite sure that I am not muddling up two things which are in
    reality distinct. I mean I am in doubt whether the faculty of making the
    reader cry ought not to be distinguished from the faculty of interesting
    him intensely. On the whole I think that it would be well to draw a line
    between the two, especially as "interesting" is somewhat ambiguous.
    
    And you think it a paradox, then, to maintain that the power of exciting
    the emotions to a high degree is not a mark of fine literature? But just
    think it over. Suppose that a few yards from this room--in the next
    house, in the next street--a woman is waiting for the return of her
    husband and son. A ring comes at the bell, there's a reddish-brown
    envelope, and inside it the message: "Railway accident father killed."
    Well, you can imagine the effect that these four words will have on the
    woman's emotions; she will either faint away, or burst into an agony of
    tears; she may even die of the shock, and you can't have a more striking
    emotional result than death, can you? Very well; but is the telegram
    fine art? Is it art? Is it even artifice? It isn't art because it is
    true! But if I invented such a telegram and sent it to a woman whose
    husband and son were away, would it thereby become art? You must see
    perfectly well that it would be nothing of the kind; and I must ask you
    to explain how a book which is, virtually, a long succession of such
    telegrams can rise higher than its origin and source? You must see, I
    think, that the question of truth and falsity can make no real
    difference to our (no doubt pompous) high æsthetic standpoint; and if
    you admit that four words which produce an emotional result are not
    necessarily art, then it follows that four hundred or four hundred
    thousand words woven together on the same principle are in no better
    position. An increased quantity means no doubt an increased artifice,
    but artifice and art are very different things. We may agree then that
    it is impossible to measure the artistic merit of a book by the
    emotional shock that it may give to its readers. I have never read the
    "Sorrows of Werther"; but if you have read it and it has made you
    sorrowful you are hereby warned against deducing from this effect any
    conclusion as to its æsthetic value.
    
    I confess all this seems A B C to me, though I see you are still
    inclined to think me a little paradoxical--not to say sophistical--but
    it grows more difficult when one gets to the question of the
    "interesting" or "absorbing" book. As I said "interesting" seems such an
    ambiguous word. It may stand for that æsthetic emotion produced, say, by
    the OEdipus; it may denote the wide-eyed attention of the butcher's wife
    listening to the story of my landlady as to the love-affairs of the
    grocer's daughter--and there are many books which are, virtually,
    "Tales of My Landlady" printed and bound. We must really then omit
    "interesting" in our account of the possible criteria of fine art; the
    word as it were cancels itself out, because it may mean on the one hand
    the possession of the highest artistic value, or on the other it may
    serve as epithet for a book which gratifies the lowest curiosity. You
    know there are books which the French have kindly named "romans à clef";
    and I suppose there is no more miserable form of book-making. The
    receipt is easy enough. The grocer's daughter, to whose amours I alluded
    just now, is really named Miss Buggins, and the gentleman is Mr Tibb.
    Well, suppose that my landlady, relating their lyric to the butcher's
    wife, should, with a knowing wink, profess to tell the story of Miss
    Ruggins and Mr Ribb--she would simply be composing a _roman à clef_
    without knowing it. You might say that it is hardly worth while to
    labour the point, that such "interest" as this is wholly and lamentably
    inartistic--that it is the very contrary to all true art--but it is not
    long since a person of some literary note, in criticising the
    "Heptameron," stated that its chief value lay in the fact that one could
    identify the persons who tell the stories and those also of whom they
    were told!
    
    But there is another interest of a much higher kind, and that is the
    sensational. We have done some excellent books of this sort in England,
    and perhaps you will understand the class I mean when I say that a novel
    of this description is hard to lay down, and harder still to take up
    again when you have once found out the secret. This is not high art; you
    are always at liberty to put down "Lycidas," but then you are compelled
    to take it up again and again, and the secret of "Lycidas" is always a
    secret, and one never fails to experience the joy of an artistic
    surprise. Still the books I mean sometimes show very high artifice, and
    in itself, perhaps, the quality that I am talking about, the power of
    exciting a vivid curiosity, an earnest desire to know what is to come
    next is not, like the vulgar _roman à clef_ curiosity, in actual
    disaccord from the purpose of art. Indeed I imagine that this trick of
    stimulating the curiosity may be made subservient to purely æsthetic
    ends, it may become a handmaid to lead one towards that desire of the
    unknown which I think was one of the synonyms I gave you for the master
    word--Ecstasy. Still, though the trick is a good one, it will not, by
    itself, make fine art. You may discover so much by reading the
    "Moonstone," that monument of ingenuity and absurdity. On the face of it
    all detective stories come under this heading: formally, no doubt, they
    must all be reckoned as tricks, and they may vary from the infinitely
    ingenious to the infinitely imbecile, and so far as I remember, the
    famous French tales of detection verge towards the lower rather than the
    higher ground. But I am inclined, not very logically, perhaps, to make
    an exception in favour of Poe's Dupin, and to place him almost in the
    sphere of pure literature. Logically, he is a detective, but I almost
    think that in his case the detective is a symbol of the mystagogue. As
    I say, I should be pressed hard if I were asked to make out my case in
    terms and syllogisms, but if you require me to do so, I would say first
    of all that the atmosphere of Dupin--and you must remember that in
    literature everything counts; it is not alone the plot, or the style
    that we have to consider--has to me hints of that presence which I have
    called ecstasy. Listen to this:
    
    "It was a freak of fancy in my friend (for what else shall I call it?)
    to be enamoured of the Night for her own sake; and into this
    _bizarrerie_, as into all his others, I quietly fell; giving myself up
    to his wild whims with a perfect _abandon_. The sable divinity would not
    herself dwell with us always; but we could counterfeit her presence. At
    the first dawn of the morning we closed all the massive shutters of our
    old building; lighting a couple of tapers which, strongly perfumed,
    threw out only the ghastliest and feeblest of rays. By the aid of these
    we then buried our souls in dreams--reading, writing, or conversing,
    until warned by the clock of the advent of the true Darkness. Then we
    sallied forth into the streets, arm in arm, continuing the topics of
    the day, or roaming far and wide until a late hour, seeking amid the
    wild lights and shadows of the populous city, that infinity of mental
    excitement which quiet observation can afford."
    
    And again; in the stories themselves, in the conduct of M. Dupin's
    detective processes, I find a faint suggestion of the under-consciousness
    or other consciousness of man, a mere hint, not, I think, expressed in so
    many words, rather latent than patent, that if you would thoroughly
    understand the rational man you must have sounded the irrational man, the
    mysterious companion that walks beside each one of us on the earthly
    journey. Of course the artifice in the Dupin stories is of the very
    highest kind, but for the reasons I have given I am inclined to think that
    there is more than artifice, and the shadow, at all events, of art itself.
    
    But this exceptional case of Poe's detective tales only leads us back to
    the main proposition--that the power of exciting a very high sensational
    interest does not, in itself, mark out a book as being fine literature.
    I think I proved the proposition by my instance of the "Moonstone," but
    if that does not convince you, we might demonstrate this theorem in the
    same way as we demonstrated the other one about the "literature" that
    produces its effect on the emotions. We have only to send out a series
    of telegrams, or we may even glance at the newspaper, and follow a case
    in the Central Criminal Court. Or we may affirm, more generally, that
    life often offers many highly absorbing and highly interesting
    spectacles, but that life is not art, and therefore, that literature
    which fails to rise above the level of life, or rather, to penetrate
    beneath the surface of life, is not fine literature in our sense of that
    term. A gold nugget may be as pure and fine as you like, but it is not a
    sovereign; it lacks the stamp; and it is the business of art to give its
    stamp and imprint to the matter of life.
    
    I really think then that we have disposed of perhaps the most generally
    received of artistic fallacies--that books are to be judged by their
    power of reproducing in the reader those feelings of grief, interest,
    curiosity, and so forth which he experiences or may experience in his
    everyday life, which he really does experience in greater or less degree
    every time he talks to a friend, takes up a newspaper, or receives a
    telegram. It comes to this again and again, doesn't it, that Art and
    Life are two different spheres, and that the Artist with a capital A is
    not a clever photographer who understands selection in a greater or less
    degree.
    
    But before we go on with our work and see what can be done with other
    literary "solvents" I want to make a digression. I should have made it
    before, if you had pulled me up at the proper cue, and that was when I
    spoke of "interest" as a highly ambiguous term, the fruitful parent of
    "undistributed middles." You see how the unscrupulous sophist would bend
    this word to his dark work, don't you? It would be, I suppose, something
    like this:
    
         A very high degree of interest [of the artistic kind] is the mark
         of fine literature.
    
         But, the "Moonstone" excites a very high degree of interest [of the
         sensational kind].
    
         _Therefore_, the "Moonstone" has the mark of fine literature.
    
    You note the "paltering" with the word, its use now in one sense, and
    now in another; and if that sort of thing were allowed we should have
    Wilkie Collins placed among the Immortals before we knew where we were.
    But hasn't it occurred to you that nearly all the terms we are using are
    patient of the same vile uses? You remember that we began with
    "literature" itself, as a monstrous example of ambiguity, sheltering as
    it did both the publications of the Anti-Everything Society and the Song
    of Ulysses' Wandering; even now we are trying to track the monster to
    his den in spite of his manifold turnings and disguises. In the
    meanwhile, for the sake of clearness, we agreed to prefix the epithet
    "fine" to the word when we meant the "Odyssey" class, though if we say
    "fine" so often I am afraid we run the risk of being thought superfine.
    However one must run all risks in the cause of making oneself
    understood; and so I say you ought to have pulled me up when I talked
    about "art" and "books that appealed to the emotions." My "art" may not
    be the same as your "art," and "emotions" are still more dangerous in
    the same way.
    
    I think I made some attempt to deal with "art" as I was talking. I
    contrasted it with "artifice," and my phrase "Artist with a big A" was
    another hint to you that the word must be handled cautiously. You know
    that in ordinary conversation we say that bees have "the art" or "an
    art" of making hexagonal cells of wax, that wasps have an art of making
    a sort of paper for their nests, that there is an art of logic, an art
    of cookery, an art in making a gravel path. Now in each of these
    instances the word really speaks of the adaptation of means to ends. In
    the case of the bees and wasps there is a slightly different _nuance_ of
    meaning, because they make their cells and their paper just as a bird
    builds its nest, through the influence of forces which to us are occult,
    which we conveniently sum up under the word instinct. In the arts of
    cookery and pathmaking there is a conscious employment of certain means
    towards the securing of certain ends; and it is at least possible that
    the swallow, gathering its materials and shaping them, has at the moment
    nothing but a blind impulse, similar to that of hunger--we all know when
    we are hungry and we all know what to do in such a case, but we do not
    all know the physiology of the stomach and the gastric juices, and
    perhaps not one of us knows the whole secret of inanition and
    nutrition. We simply eat because we want to eat, not because we wish to
    supply ourselves with a certain quantity of peptones; and so perhaps the
    swallow gathers her nest and shapes it, without the consciousness of the
    eggs and the little birds that are to follow. But I need not remind you
    that there are plenty of well authenticated instances of animals who
    have consciously used means to secure ends, and thus "art" in its common
    significance is not even an exclusively human faculty. When, for
    example, the bees find themselves in danger of being left queenless,
    they administer what has been called "royal food" to a common grub, and
    that which would have been a worker becomes a queen; and in this case
    the bees are as much "artists" as the cook who puts a particular
    ingredient into a dish with the view of obtaining a particular flavour.
    
    Now, then, let us apply all this to our matter. I daresay you have often
    heard a book praised for its "great art," and if you have read it you
    will have discovered that its "art" is simply contrivance, the very
    adaptation of means to ends that we have been discussing. "The art with
    which the mystery is carefully kept in the background," "the art by
    which the two characters are contrasted throughout the volume," "the
    highly artistic manner in which Fernando and the heroine are brought
    together on the last page"--these, you see clearly, are contrivances,
    artifices, in no way differing in degree from the contrivances of the
    man who makes the garden path, of the cook who "dusts in" just a
    suspicion of lemon-rind, of the bee who administers the "royal food."
    This "art" then is a totally different thing from our Art with the
    capital letter, with the epithet "fine," or "high" before it; and in
    future when I mean "adaptation of means to ends," I shall always say
    "artifice"; while "art" will be retained and set apart for higher uses.
    
    And now as to "emotion." Here, I think, you ought to have been down on
    me. You might have said: "You declare that the appeal to the emotions is
    not a test of fine literature. But to what then does Homer appeal? What
    is the "OEdipus" but an appeal to the emotions? What is all exquisite
    lyric poetry but the cry of the emotions, set to music?" I suppose that,
    as a matter of fact, you understood my real meaning by the instance I
    gave; the anguish of a wife at the loss of a husband; you saw that what
    I wanted to say was this: that fine literature does not content itself
    with repeating, or mimicking, the emotions of private, personal,
    everyday life. Still, I should have gone into the matter more fully
    then, and as I did not do so, we had better see what can be done now.
    And do you know that I believe that the best approach we can make to a
    rather subtle question will be a somewhat indirect one? Just now I was
    talking about Poe's Dupin stories, and I tried, rather vaguely, to
    justify my tentative inclusion of them in the higher class of letters,
    by pointing out that Poe seemed to hint at the "other-consciousness" of
    man, and to suggest, at least, the presence of that shadowy, unknown, or
    half-known companion who walks beside each one of us all our days. I
    tried to realise the image of a man, followed or rather attended, by a
    spiritual fellow, treading a path parallel with but different from his
    own; and now I want you to carry out this image into the sphere of
    words. Already you must have a hint of it. One might draw a figure;
    something like this:
    
                   +--------------------+-----------------+
                   |                    |                 |
                   | Fine Literature.   |   "Literature." |
                   | Art.               |   Artifice.     |
                   | Emotion.           |   Feelings.     |
                   |                    |                 |
                   +--------------------+-----------------+
    
    And before I go into the special question, let me extend the list; it
    will explain itself.
    
        +------------------------+-----------------------------------------+
        |                        |                                         |
        | Romance, romantic.     |  A "Romantic" Affair in the West End.   |
        | Tragedy, tragic.       |  "Tragedy" in Soho.                     |
        | Drama, dramatic.       |  Le "drame" de la Rue Cochon:           |
        |                        |       "Dramatic" Elopement in Peckham.  |
        | Interest, interesting  |  An "interesting" number of "Snippets." |
        |      [of "Hamlet"].    |                                         |
        | Lyric.                 |  The "Lyric" Theatre.                   |
        | Inebriated.            |  In an "inebriated" condition.          |
        |                        |                                         |
        +------------------------+-----------------------------------------+
    
    That almost gives my secret away, doesn't it? Of course you see the
    place that the words in the right-hand column take in the scheme. The
    "Romantic" Affair in the West End really concerned the life of a
    draper's assistant, who robbed his master's till, in order that he might
    make presents to Miss Claire Tilbury, one of the "Sisters Tilbury" now
    performing at the "Lucifer." An unmentionable person cut his throat in
    some alley off Greek Street; hence the "Tragedy" in Soho. Two
    peculiarly squalid servants, who beat out their master's brains, under
    singularly uninteresting circumstances, acted the "Drama" of the Rue
    Cochon, and it was a dissolute barmaid who eloped "dramatically" from
    Peckham in the dog-cart of her employer. The two varying uses of the
    word "lyric" need not be underlined for you, who know the Elizabethans
    and the Cavaliers; but perhaps I may say that he who tastes _calix meus
    inebrians_ will not be in an "inebriated" condition. It would be
    possible to extend these parallel columns almost to infinity; but I
    think the list is long enough for our purpose, and "Trench on Words" is
    a well-known handbook. But you see my right-hand column word, parallel
    with "Emotion"? You see I have written "Feelings," and I suggest that it
    will be convenient to speak of feelings when we mean the things of life,
    of society, of personal and private relationship, while we may reserve
    emotion for the influence produced in man by fine art. Thus it will be
    with emotion that we witness the fall of OEdipus, the madness of Lear,
    while we feel for our friends and ourselves in misfortune. That seems to
    make it plain enough, doesn't it; you see now, clearly, what I mean by
    saying that the power of producing an emotional shock cannot be a test
    of fine literature. Art must appeal to emotion, and sometimes, no doubt,
    with a shock; but it must always be to the emotion of the left-hand
    column, never to the "feelings" on the right hand. So you must never
    tell me that a book is fine art because it made you, or somebody else,
    cry; your tears are, emphatically, not evidence in the court of Fine
    Literature.
    
    I daresay it may have struck you that the tests we have considered
    hitherto have been, in the main, popular tests. No doubt many persons
    calling themselves critics have praised the art of a book because it has
    drawn tears from eyes, or because it has not suffered itself to be put
    down, or because it contains easily recognisable portraits of well-known
    people, but such critics are to be spelt with a very small initial
    letter, and, as I said, I don't think we want to extend that list of
    parallels. There is another test that I had forgotten: I suppose there
    really are people who believe that a book is fine "because it will do
    good," but I don't think we'll argue with them, though I once knew a
    liberally-educated man who said a certain book was fine because it
    tended "to raise one's opinion of the clergy." So we will reckon our
    "popular" tests as done with, and proceed to the more technical solvents
    that are proposed by professed men of letters.
    
    Three of these more literary criteria occur to me at the moment, and I
    believe we shall understand them and the position which they represent
    better if we take them, at first, at all events, in a mass. I can
    conceive, then, that many persons whose opinion one would respect would
    state their position in literary criticism somewhat as follows:--"If a
    book (they would say) shows keenness of observation, insight into
    character, with fidelity to life as the result of these capacities; if
    its art (we should say, artifice) in the design and 'laying out' of the
    plot, in the contrivance of incident is confessedly admirable, and
    finally if it is written in a good style: then you have fine literature.
    Fine art, in short, is a clear mirror, and the artist's skill consists
    in arranging and selecting such parts of life as he thinks best for his
    purpose of reflection."
    
    Well, now, as to the first point: fidelity to life, clearness of
    reflection, the selection being taken for granted, as no one out of an
    asylum would maintain that a book must mirror the whole of life, or even
    the millionth part of one particular man's life. Come, let us apply the
    test in question to one or two of the acknowledged excellencies--to the
    "Odyssey" for instance, to the "Morte D'Arthur," to "Don Quixote." Is
    the story of Ulysses, in any accepted sense of the phrase "faithful" to
    life as we know it? Is it "faithful," that is to say, with the fidelity
    of Jane Austen, of Thackeray, of George Eliot, of Fielding? Is there
    anything in our experience answering to the episodes of the
    Lotus-Eaters, Calypso's Isle, the Cyclops' Cavern, the descent of the
    Goddess? Is the "reflection" even a reflection of Homer's own
    experience? Had he escaped from the cave under the belly of a ram? Had
    he been in the world of one-eyed giants? Were his friends in the habit
    of talking in hexameter verse? We may go on, of course, but is it worth
    while? It is surely hardly necessary to demonstrate the fact that the
    author of the "Morte D'Arthur" had never seen the Graal, that such a
    character as Don Quixote never existed in the natural order of things.
    We might have gone more sharply to work with this "fidelity" test: we
    might have said that poetry being, admittedly fine literature at its
    finest, and (admittedly also) being unfaithful to life as we know it
    both in matter and manner, that therefore the test breaks down at once.
    If fine literature must be faithful to life, then "Kubla Khan" is not
    fine literature; which, I think we may say, is highly absurd.
    
    I daresay you think I have dealt rather crudely, in a somewhat
    materialistic spirit, with this criterion of "fidelity to life." I admit
    the charge, but you must remember that I am dealing with very bad
    people, who understand nothing but materialism. And when these people
    tell you in so many words that it is the author's business clearly and
    intelligently to present the life--the common, social life around
    him--then, believe me, the only thing to be done is to throw "Odyssey"
    and "OEdipus," "Morte D'Arthur," "Kubla Khan" and "Don Quixote" straight
    in their faces, and to demonstrate that these eternal books were not
    constructed on the proposed receipt. Of course if I were treating with
    the initiated, if I were commentating and not arguing, I should handle
    the great masterpieces in a much more reverent manner. I mean that for
    those who possess the secret it skills not to bring in the Cyclops (who
    for us is not a giant but a symbol); we have only to bow down before the
    great music of such a poem as the Odyssey, recognising that by the very
    reason of its transcendent beauty, by the very fact that it trespasses
    far beyond the world of our daily lives, beyond "selection" and
    "reflection," it is also exalted above our understanding, that because
    its beauty is supreme, that therefore its beauty is largely beyond
    criticism. For ourselves we do not need to prove its transcendence of
    life by this or that extraordinary incident; it is the whole spirit and
    essence and sound and colour of the song that affect us; and we know
    that the Odyssey surpassed the bounds of its own age and its own land
    just as much as it surpasses those of our time and our country. You look
    as if you thought I were fighting with the vanquished, but let me tell
    you that great people have praised Homer because he depicted truthfully
    the men and manners of his time.
    
    But as I was saying, all this would be too subtle for the enemy, for the
    people who maintain that fine literature is a faithful reflection of
    life, and think that Jane Austen touched the point of literary
    supremacy. With them, as I said, we must be rough; we must ask: Did
    Sophocles describe the ordinary life of Athens in his day? No: very
    well, then; since the works of Sophocles are fine literature, it follows
    that some fine literature does not reflect ordinary life, and therefore
    that fidelity to nature is not the differentia of the highest art.
    
    I wonder whether I ought to caution you again against the ambiguity of
    language? We are dealing easily enough with such words as "life" and
    "nature," and from what you know of my system you may perhaps have seen
    that I have been using these words as the people use them, as those use
    them who would say that "Vanity Fair" is a faithful presentation of
    life. I thought you would understand this, but I may just mention in
    passing that words like "nature," "life" and "truth" or "fidelity" have
    also their esoteric values, that (by way of example) the truth of the
    scientist and the truth of the philosopher are two very different
    things. So it may turn out by and bye that in the occult sense,
    "fidelity to life" _is_ the differentia of fine literature; that the
    aim of art is truth; that the artist continually mirrors nature in its
    eternal, essential forms; but for the present moment, it is understood,
    is it not, that these words have been used in their common, everyday
    popular significance? The "Dunciad" is a study of man, and Wordsworth's
    "Ode on Intimations of Immortality" is a study of man, and the literary
    standpoint that we have been attacking is that of Pope and not that of
    Wordsworth.
    
    If I remember, the next test we have to analyse is that of artifice,
    often and improperly called art. But I think we have already demolished
    this criterion. In distinguishing between art and artifice I pointed out
    that the latter merely signifies the adaptation of means to an end, and
    has no relation whatever with art properly so-called; it is simply the
    mental instrument with which man performs every task and every work of
    his daily life; it consists in the rejection of that which is unfit for
    the particular purpose in view, and in the acceptance and use of that
    which is fit for the desired end and likely to bring it about. It
    concerns not creation but execution, and it is I need hardly say as
    indispensable to the author as are his pen and ink, and (I might almost
    say) is as little concerned as these with the essence of his art. Of
    course in works of the very highest genius we may declare that, in a
    sense, art has become all in all, that the necessary artifice has been
    interpenetrated with art, so that we can hardly distinguish in our minds
    between the idea and the realisation of it. In such cases, artifice has
    been lifted up and exalted into the heaven of art, and it remains
    artifice no longer; but in the view that we are considering it is merely
    the adaptation of means to an end, a clever choice of incident, the
    knack of putting in and leaving out. The faculty may, as I said, be
    glorified and transfigured by genius, but every newspaper reporter must
    have more or less of it, and it is clear enough I think (perhaps I may
    mention Wilkie Collins once more) that in itself it cannot establish the
    claim of any book to be fine literature.
    
    And lastly we have to deal with style; and here again I must have
    recourse to my distinctions. What _is_ a good style? If you mean by a
    "good" style, one that delivers the author's meaning in the clearest
    possible manner, if its purpose and effect are obviously utilitarian, if
    it be designed solely with the view of imparting knowledge--the
    knowledge of what the author intends--then I must point out that "style"
    in this sense is or should be amongst the accomplishments of every
    commercial clerk--indeed, it will be merely a synonym for plain speaking
    and plain writing--and in this sense it is evidently not one of the
    marks of art, since the object of art is not information, but a peculiar
    kind of æsthetic delight. But if on the other hand style is to mean such
    a use and choice of words and phrases and cadences that the ear and the
    soul through the ear receive an impression of subtle but most beautiful
    music, if the sense and sound and colour of the words affect us with an
    almost inexplicable delight, then I say that while Idea is the soul,
    style is the glorified body of the very highest literary art. Style, in
    short, is the last perfection of the very best in literature, it is the
    outward sign of the burning grace within. But we must keep the
    systematic consideration of style for some other night; it's not a
    subject to be dealt with by the way, and I have only said so much
    because it was necessary to draw the line between language as a means of
    imparting facts (good style in the sense of our opponents) and language
    as an æsthetic instrument, which is a good, or rather a beautiful style
    in our sense. In the latter sense it is the form of fine literature, in
    the former sense it is the medium of all else that is expressed in
    words, from a bill of exchange upwards.
    
    It seems to me, then, that we have considered one by one the alternative
    tests of fine literature which have been or may be proposed, and we have
    come to the conclusion that each and all are impossible. It is no longer
    permissible, I imagine, for you or for me to say: "This book is fine
    literature because it makes me cry, because it was so interesting that I
    couldn't put it down, because it is so natural and faithful to life,
    because it is so well (plainly and neatly) written." We have picked
    these reasons to pieces one by one, and the result is that we are driven
    back on my "word of the enigma"--Ecstasy; the infallible instrument, as
    I think, by which fine literature may be discerned from reading-matter,
    by which art may be known from artifice, and style from intelligent
    expression. At any rate we have got our hypothesis, and you remember
    what stress Coleridge laid on the necessity of forming some hypothesis
    before entering on any investigation.
    
    I believe we began to-night with the evening paper, and the strange
    glimpse it gives us, through a pinky-green veil, through a cloud of
    laborious nonsense about odds and winners and tips and all such foolery,
    into that ancient eternal desire of man for the unknown. And that, you
    remember, was one of the synonyms that I offered you for ecstasy; and so
    in a sense I expect that we shall have the evening paper close beside us
    all the way of our long voyage in quest of the lost Atlantis.
    
    
    
    
    II
    
    
    I think it is a horrible thing to have such a good memory as that. I
    recollect, now that you remind me, that I did lay down "Pickwick" _v._
    "Vanity Fair" as a sort of test case of my theory of literature; but you
    surely do not expect me to work out the arguments in detail? Of course
    if I were giving a series of lectures I should "set a paper" after each
    one; but I expect you to content yourself with the suggestion, with the
    skeleton map, as it were. Besides, if we take that special case of two
    eminent Victorian novels as a concrete instance of the abstract
    argument, don't you see that we are answering the particular question
    all the while that we are investigating the general proposition? Surely
    if you recollect all that we said about fine literature in general, you
    won't have much difficulty in adjudicating on the claims of Thackeray.
    Don't you see that he never withdraws himself from the common life and
    the common consciousness, that he is all the while nothing but a
    photographer; a showman with a set of pictures. A consummately clever
    photographer, certainly, a showman with a gift of amusing, interesting
    "patter" that is quite extraordinary, an artificer of very high merit.
    But where will you find Ecstasy in Thackeray? Where is his adoration?
    You may search, I think, from one end of his books to the other, without
    finding any evidence that he realised the mystery of things; he was
    never for a moment aware of that shadowy double, that strange companion
    of man, who walks, as I said, foot to foot with each one of us, and yet
    his paces are in an unknown world. And (unless you have got any fresh
    arguments) I think we decided last week that the book which lacks the
    sense of all this is not fine literature.
    
    I hope you don't think I am abusing Thackeray. I am always reading him,
    and I chose his "Vanity Fair" because it strikes me as such a supremely
    clever example of its class. I suppose there is nothing more amusing
    than the society of a brilliant, observant man of the world. Well,
    Thackeray was brilliant and observant _in excelsis_, and besides that,
    he understood the artifice of story-telling, and he could write a terse,
    clean-cut English which was always sufficient for his purpose. He
    contrives the corporal overthrow of the Marquis of Steyne, he shows you
    that bald old nobleman sprawling on the floor, and the words that he
    uses are his brisk, willing, and capable servants. He has observation,
    and artifice, and "style" in that secondary sense which we distinguished
    from the real style; from those "melodies unheard" which I called (I
    think rather picturesquely) the glorified body of the highest literary
    art. But these qualities, we found out, are not, separately or
    conjointly, the differentia of fine literature as we understand the
    term; and consequently, with all our admiration and all our interest we
    are compelled to place Thackeray in the lower form, simply because he is
    clearly and decisively lacking in that one essential quality of ecstasy,
    because he never leaves the street and the highroad to wander on the
    eternal hills, because he does not seem to be aware that such hills
    exist.
    
    Of course I have only taken Thackeray as the representative of his
    class, and I chose him, as I remarked, because, for me, he is the most
    favourable representative of it. I am thinking, really, of the "plain
    man" whom we have engaged in so many forms, and of his "plain" argument
    which comes to this--"for me a great book is a book that amuses me
    greatly and that I enjoy reading." And I say that Thackeray amuses me
    greatly and that I enjoy reading his books immensely, but that, with due
    respect to "common sense," such an argument fails to prove that "Vanity
    Fair" is fine literature. Other people would, no doubt, have chosen
    other books; many would have selected Miss Austen, and I daresay they
    would have a good deal to say for their choice. Undoubtedly there is a
    severity, a self-restraint, a fineness of observation, a delicacy of
    irony in "Pride and Prejudice" which are unmatched of their kind (the
    Thackeray of the caricatures, of those queer woodblocks, comes out now
    and then in the books, and digression occasionally goes beyond due
    bounds); but I named "Vanity Fair" because, personally, I find it more
    amusing than "Pride and Prejudice." In neither of these books is there
    art in our high sense of the word, and in preferring the one over the
    other I am simply saying that I prefer the company of a brilliant and
    witty cosmopolitan to that of a very keen and delicate, but very limited
    maiden lady, who lives in a remote country town and understands
    thoroughly the reason why the vicar bowed so low when a certain
    carriage rolled up the high street, and why that pretty, prim girl
    crossed over the way when the handsome gentleman from the Hall came out
    of the chymist's. Yes, the cosmopolitan at the club window certainly
    fails a little in his manners now and then, and the country
    gentlewoman's breeding is perfect of its kind, but the circles in which
    Pendennis moved are (to me) so infinitely the more entertaining of the
    two.
    
    You see, I think that the question of liking a book or not liking it has
    nothing whatever to do with the consideration of fine art. Art is
    _there_, if I may say so, just as the Tenth Commandment is there; and if
    we don't like them, so much the worse for us. I may find Homer very dull
    reading, I may covet your ox and your ass and everything that is yours,
    but my limited and somewhat commonplace brains, and my envy of your
    prosperity won't alter the fact that the "Odyssey" is fine literature
    and that covetousness is wicked. But when we once leave the utterances
    of the eternal, universal human ecstasy, which we have agreed to call
    art, and descend to these lower levels that we are talking of now, it
    seems to me that the question of liking or not liking counts for a good
    deal. Not for everything, of course. We must still distinguish: between
    plots stupid or ingenious, between observation that is close and keen
    and observation that is vague and inaccurate, between artifice and the
    want of it, between sentences that are neatly constructed and mere
    slipshod. All these things naturally reckon in the account, but when
    they have been estimated and allowed their value, you will usually find
    that you are influenced still more by your mere liking or disliking of
    the subject-matter, and it seems to me quite legitimately. For, if you
    look closely into the whole question, you will find that you are judging
    these secondary books as you judge of life, as you choose the scene of
    your holiday, as you read the newspaper. One man may say that he prefers
    to talk to artists, another, quite legitimately, may love the society of
    brewers; you may think Norway perfection, I am going to Constantinople;
    A. turns at once to the quotation for Turpentine at Savannah, B. folds
    down the sheet at the Police News. It is not a question of art, but of
    taste, that is of individual humour and constitution; you frequent the
    company that suits you, you go to the place you like, you read the news
    that happens to be most interesting from your special standpoint. And in
    the same way, if I find the conversation of Miss Becky Sharpe, as
    reported by Mr W. M. Thackeray, more amusing than the conversation of
    Miss Elizabeth Bennett as reported by Miss Jane Austen; it seems to me
    that there is no more to be said. Elizabeth's remarks are more skilfully
    reported? Very likely, but, granting that, I had rather listen to the
    record, imperfect, if you please, of the other lady's conversation. Here
    is a speech on Bimetallism, given at great length, and (let us presume)
    with great accuracy; here is a short summary of Professor L.'s "Lecture
    on the Eleusinian Mysteries," very badly "sub-edited." But, you see, I
    happen not to care twopence about Bimetallism, so I turn away from the
    careful report, growling; while I cut out that wretched summary of the
    Lecture with the purpose of pasting it in my scrap-book, since every
    word about the Eleusinian Mysteries has a vivid interest for me.
    
    It often amuses me to hear people quarrelling about the rival "artistic
    merit" of books which have, in most cases, no artistic merits at all. A.
    writes a book about greengrocers, and you, who find something
    singularly piquant and entertaining in the manners, speech, and habits
    of the class in question, pronounce A. to be a "great artist" who has
    written a masterpiece. I love dukes, and B's. novel of the peerage
    strikes me as a marvel of artistic accomplishment, while I pronounce the
    work that has charmed you to be as stupid and tiresome as the class it
    represents. Each of us is talking nonsense; there is no art in the
    question, which is purely a matter of individual taste. The Stock
    Exchange column interests one man, while the latest football news
    absorbs the other. That is all.
    
    Of course, as I said, artifice counts for something: there is a pleasure
    in seeing the thing neatly done, and I suppose it is this pleasure that
    has secured Miss Austen her fervent admirers. It is a little difficult
    to treat this form of pleasure quite fairly; a musician perhaps would
    find it difficult to answer the question whether he would rather hear
    Palestrina badly rendered or Zingarelli executed to perfection. In the
    latter case there would certainly be the charm of exquisite voices in
    perfect order and accord, though the music were nothing or worse than
    nothing; still, our musician might say, on the other hand, that
    Palestrina martyred was better than Zingarelli triumphant. I am afraid
    I can imagine myself saying: "Limited country-people, as seen by Jane
    Austen, are so 'slow' that they rather bore me, though the author has
    portrayed them with wonderful skill," but I can hardly fancy myself
    affirming that Becky Sharpe is such an interesting personage that she
    would still delight me, even if the author of "Ten Thousand a Year" had
    written her history. On the other hand I believe that the plot of
    "Jekyll and Hyde" would still have had some fascination, though it had
    been treated by the veriest dolt in letters. But that is not a good
    example, since "Jekyll and Hyde" is certainly in its conception, though
    not in its execution, a work of fine art. Let us take the "Moonstone"
    again as an example; I believe then, that if the events related in it
    had caught our eyes in a brief newspaper paragraph they would still have
    interested.
    
    It seems to me that, after all, this question of artifice, of "how the
    thing is done," comes under the same category as liking and disliking. I
    mean it is largely a matter of the personal equation, about which no
    very strict laws can be laid down. You might say, for example, that
    Becky would entertain you in any hands, however indifferent, provided
    that her "facts" were preserved, and I don't see that I could argue the
    point with you. It reminds me again of the way in which men choose their
    friends; one lays stress on pleasant manners, another on sterling
    goodness of character, a third on wit, a fourth on distinction of some
    kind; and argument is really voiceless. "Here is a book-case," you may
    say, "look how exquisitely it is made." Yes, but I don't want a
    book-case; whereas that table, ricketty as it is, will be really useful.
    But if you were to say: "Look at Westminster Abbey," you can hardly
    imagine my answering: "Bother Westminster Abbey; I want a pig-sty." You
    see how, here again, we come to the generic difference between fine
    literature and interesting reading matter. We read the "Odyssey" because
    we are supernatural, because we hear in it the echoes of the eternal
    song, because it symbolises for us certain amazing and beautiful things,
    because it is music; we read Miss Austen and Thackeray because we like
    to recognise the faces of our friends aptly reproduced, to see the
    external face of humanity so deftly mimicked, because we are natural.
    The question of our preference for one over the other, is, making due
    allowance for analogy, the question of our preference for a table over a
    bookcase or _vice versâ_, and the workmanship in each case is largely a
    matter of detail. And the great poem may be equated with the great
    church: each is made for beauty, the one is ecstasy in words, the other
    ecstasy in stone. But the church and the pig-sty, on the other hand, are
    not to be compared together: incidentally, no doubt, the former is
    rainproof or in ill repair, has good or bad acoustic properties, while
    the latter may be either an æsthetic pest in the back-yard, or an
    agreeable looking little shed enough. Still, the essence of the church
    is beauty, ecstasy; of the sty utility, the safe keeping of pigs. It
    would be absurd, you see, to say: "I prefer an abbey to a pig-sty," and
    it would be equally absurd to say: "I prefer the 'OEdipus' to 'Pride and
    Prejudice'" or "I prefer the Venus of the Louvre to the wax-figures in
    the exhibition." Of course these are only analogies, and you mustn't
    press them, but they may help to make my meaning clearer, to enforce the
    vast distinction between art and artifice. Please don't think that I
    wish to establish a proportion: as a pig-sty is to an abbey, so is Jane
    Austen to Sophocles. In her case you would have to substitute a neat
    Georgian house for "pig-sty" and then I think you would have a very fair
    proportion. But all that I wanted to do was to draw the line between
    things made for use, to occupy some definite place in relation to our
    common daily life; and things made by ecstasy and for ecstasy, things
    that are symbols, proclaiming the presence of the unknown world.
    
    And I chose "Pickwick" as the antithesis to "Vanity Fair" deliberately.
    Thackeray (in my private judgment) is the chief of those who have
    provided interesting reading-matter; Dickens is by no means in the first
    rank of literary artists. I think he is golden, but he is very largely
    alloyed with baser stuff, with indifferent metal, which was the product
    of his age, of his circumstances in life, of his own uncertain taste.
    Just contrast the atmosphere which surrounded the young Sophocles, with
    that in which the young Dickens flourished. Both were men of genius, but
    one grew up in the City of the Violet Crown, the other in Camden Town
    and worse places, one was accustomed to breathe that "most pellucid
    air," the other inhaled the "London particular." The wonder is, not
    that there are faults in Dickens, but that there is genius of any kind.
    I am not going to analyze "Pickwick" any more than I analyzed "Vanity
    Fair," but of course you see that, in its conception, it is essentially
    one with the "Odyssey." It is a book of wandering; you start from your
    own doorstep and you stray into the unknown; every turn of the road
    fills you with surmise, every little village is a discovery, a something
    new, a creation. You know not what may happen next; you are journeying
    through another world. I need not remind you how glorious all this is in
    the Odyssey, which of course is so much more beautiful than "Pickwick,"
    as that glowing Mediterranean Sea, whose bounds on every side were
    mystery, is more beautiful than the muddy, foggy Thames, as those
    rolling hexameters are more beautiful than Dickens's prose; and yet in
    each case the symbol is, in reality, the same; both the heroic song of
    the old Ionian world and the comic cockney romance of 1837 communicate
    that enthralling impression of the unknown, which is, at once, a whole
    philosophy of life, and the most exquisite of emotions. In varying
    degrees of intensity you will trace it all through fine literature in
    every age and in every nation; you will find it in Celtic voyages, in
    the Eastern Tale, where a door in a dull street suddenly opens into
    dreamland, in the mediæval stories of the wandering knights, in "Don
    Quixote," and at last in our "Pickwick" where Ulysses has become a
    retired city man, whimsically journeying up and down the England of
    sixty years ago. You talk of the "grotesquerie" of "Pickwick," but don't
    you see that this element is present in all the masterpieces of the
    kind? Remember the Cyclops, remember the grotesque shapes that decorate
    the "Arabian Nights," remember the bizarre element, the almost wanton
    grotesquerie of many of the "Arthur" romances. In all these cases as in
    "Pickwick" the same result is obtained; an overpowering impression of
    "strangeness," of remoteness, of withdrawal from the common ways of
    life. "Pickwick," is, in no sense, or in no valuable sense, a portrayal,
    a copy, an imitation of life in the ordinary sense of "imitation," and
    "life"; Pickwick, and Sam, and Jingle, and the rest of them are not
    clever reproductions of actual people, (is there any more foolish
    pursuit than that of disputing about the "original" of Mr Pickwick?);
    the book is rather the suggestion of another life, beneath our own or
    beside our own, and the characters, those queer grotesque people, are
    queer for the same reason that the Cyclops is queer and the dwarfs and
    dragons of mediæval romance are queer. We are withdrawn from the common
    ways of life; and in that withdrawal is the beginning of ecstasy. There
    are sentences in "Pickwick" that give me an almost extravagant delight.
    You remember the lines about the Lotus-Eaters.
    
        ~tôn d' hostis lôtoio phagoi meliêdea karpon,
         ouket' apangeilai palin êthelen oude neesthai
         all' autou boulonto met' andrasi Lôtophagoisin
         lôton ereptomenoi menemen nostou te lathesthai.~
    
    Well, do you know there is a brief dialogue in "Pickwick" that seems
    almost as enchanted, to me. The scene is the manor-farm kitchen, on
    Christmas eve.
    
    "'How it snows,' said one of the men, in a low voice.
    
    "'Snows, does it?' said Wardle.
    
    "'Rough, cold night, sir,' replied the man, 'and there's a wind got up
    that drifts it across the fields, in a thick white cloud.'
    
    "'What does Jem say?' inquired the old lady. 'There ain't anything the
    matter, is there?'
    
    "'No, no, mother,' replied Wardle; 'he says there's a snow-drift, and a
    wind that's piercing cold.'"
    
    You know this is the introduction to the Tale of Gabriel Grub, an
    admirable legend which Dickens "farsed" with an obtrusive moral. But I
    confess that the atmosphere (which to me seems all the wild weather and
    the wild legend of the north) suggested by those phrases "a thick white
    cloud," and "a wind that's piercing cold" is in my judgment wholly
    marvellous. But Dickens, of course, is full of impressions which never
    become expressions. You remember that chapter about the lawyer's clerks
    in the "Magpie and Stump"? It is always quite pathetic to me to note how
    Dickens _felt_ the strangeness, the mystery, the haunting that are like
    a mist about the old Inns of Court, and how utterly unable he was to
    express his emotion--to find a fit symbol for his meaning. He takes
    refuge, as it were, behind Jack Bamber, who tells two very insignificant
    legends as to the mystery of the Inns. Dickens feels that these legends
    are insignificant, and throws in one that is pure burlesque, and then
    changes the subject in despair; the vague impression has refused to be
    put into words; probably, indeed, it had stopped short of becoming
    thought. But I am afraid that if I once begin to talk about the defects
    and faults of Dickens I shall run on for ever, and I think you will be
    able to find out his laches quite well for yourself. What I want to
    insist on is his sense of mystery, his withdrawal from common life, and,
    finally, his ecstasy. I have not proved my case up to the hilt by a
    thorough-going analysis of "Pickwick," but I think I have suggested the
    "heads" of such an analysis. There is ecstasy in the main idea, in the
    thought of the man who wanders away from his familiar streets into
    unknown tracks and lanes and villages, there is ecstasy in the
    conception of all those queer, grotesque characters, reminders each one
    of the strangeness of life, there is ecstasy in the thought of the wild
    Christmas Eve, of the fields and woods scourged by "a wind that's
    piercing cold," hidden by the thick cloud of snow, there is ecstasy in
    that vague impression of the old, dark, Inns, of the "rotten" chambers
    that had been shut up for years and years. In a word: "Pickwick" is fine
    literature.
    
    Well, you've got what you wanted; some sort of analysis of my case:
    "'Pickwick' _v._ 'Vanity Fair'"; but it must be clearly understood that
    I'm not going to "work out" every example. However, I am not sorry that
    I have been led to go into this particular case rather fully, because it
    is a typical one, and we shall not be obliged to go over the same ground
    again. I mean, that having witnessed the dissection of Thackeray, you
    will have no need to come to me for my judgment of George Eliot, or of
    Anthony Trollope, or--to make a very long list a very short one--of
    about ninety-nine per cent of our modern novels. Yes, you have mentioned
    a great name, and I, like you, take off my cap to the man who has gone
    on his way, without caring for the "public," or the "reviewers," or
    anything else, except his own judgment of what is right. But, frankly,
    if you pass from the man and come to his work, my plain opinion is this:
    that he has written about ordinary life, regarded from an ordinary
    standpoint, in a style which is extraordinary certainly, but very far
    from beautiful. It is not a beautiful style, since a fine style, though
    it may carry suggestion beyond the bourne of thought, though it may be
    the veil and visible body of concealed mysteries, is always plain on the
    surface. It may be like an ingeniously devised cryptogram, which may
    have an occult sense conveyed to initiated eyes in every dot and line
    and flourish, but is outwardly as simple and straightforward as a
    business letter. But in the works of the writer whom we are discussing
    obscurities, dubieties of all kinds are far from uncommon; and in many
    of his books there are passages which hardly seem to be English at all.
    The words are familiar--most of them--the grammatical construction often
    offers no very considerable difficulties--it is rarely, I mean, that one
    has to search very long for the nominative of the sentence--but when one
    has read the words and parsed them, one feels inclined to think that
    after all the passage is not in English but in some other language with
    a superficial resemblance to English. Style is not everything? Certainly
    not; a book may fail in style, and yet be fine, though not the finest
    literature. You have only to open Sir Walter Scott to have highly
    conclusive evidence on that point. But the writer we are considering not
    only fails in the body of art but even more conspicuously in the soul of
    it. Just think for a moment of his story of the very earnest Jew who
    fell in love with the baroness who was not very earnest. There was a
    false female friend, you remember, and social complications perturbed
    the hearts of the curiously assorted lovers, and finally the Jew was
    shot in a duel by another, less "detrimental," courtier. Can you
    conceive anything more trivial than this? Don't you see that from such a
    book as that the _idea_, the soul of fine literature, is completely
    lacking? Great books may always be summed up in a phrase, often in a
    single word, and that phrase or that word will always signify some
    primary and palmary idea. To me the only "idea" suggested by the plot I
    have outlined is unimportance; and, as in the case of Thackeray, ecstasy
    is entirely absent both from this and from all other of the author's
    books. You say that, after all, the plot in question is a plot of the
    love of a man for a woman, and that _that_ is an idea in the highest
    sense of the word, and an idea which is the most of all fit for the
    purpose and the making of the finest literature. I agree with you in the
    latter clause of your sentence, but I must point out that the book is
    _not_ the story of the love of a man for a woman, it is the story of the
    flirtation of a baroness with a German Jew Socialist--a very different
    matter. In a word, it is a tale of the accidental, of the particular,
    of the inessential; it is completely the play of Hamlet with the part of
    Hamlet omitted, and the greatest stress laid on the minor characters.
    
    It is quite true that when an author writes a romance containing a hero
    and a heroine he must tell you who they are, he must give, briefly and
    succinctly, the necessary details--names, ages, conditions and so
    forth--but if he is a great author he will do this incidentally and make
    us feel that such details are incidental. In short, he must poise his
    feet on earth, but his way is to the stars. Think of the "Scarlet
    Letter," open it again and see how admirably Hawthorne has omitted a
    world of unessential details that a lesser man would have put in. He has
    left out a whole encyclopædia of useless and tedious information; there
    is the dim, necessary background of time and place, but in reality the
    scene is Eternity, and the drama is the Mystery of Love and Vengeance
    and Hell-fire. Of course fine literature must have its gross and carnal
    body, we must know "who's who," for I don't think an old-fashioned
    receipt that I remember was ever very successful. Oh, you must have read
    some of the tales I mean; they used to flourish in the old "Keepsakes,"
    and the hero was boldly labelled "Fernando" for all distinction and
    description. One might surmise that Fernando was domiciled on the
    continent of Europe, but that was all. It was not successful, this
    well-meaning school of fiction, and I repeat that the finest literature
    must have its accidents--it cannot exist as shining substance alone. It
    is just the same with the art of sculpture, with the art of painting.
    You cannot look at a Greek Apollo without looking at that part of the
    body which conceals the bowels, but I imagine you don't want to treasure
    this thought or to insist on it? And I suppose a geologist, looking at a
    picture, could tell you whether those wild and terrible rocks were
    volcanic or carboniferous; but really one doesn't want to know. Bowels,
    geological formation, in sculpture and painting, the social position of
    the characters and all other such details in fine literature are
    inessential; and the great artist will, as I said, make us feel that
    they are inessential. If you want an instance of what I mean read a book
    which is very comparable with the German-Jew-Baroness tale that we were
    talking about. I mean "Two on a Tower" by Mr Hardy. In that you have
    the contrast of social ranks: the "two" are the Lady of the Manor and an
    educated peasant, but how utterly all thought of "society" (in any sense
    of the word) disappears from those wonderful pages, as you advance and
    find that the theme is really Love. Why even the accidents are glorified
    and are made of the essence of the book. The old tower standing in the
    midst of lonely, red ploughlands far from the highway, is at first only
    the convenient place where the young peasant studies astronomy; but as
    you read you feel the change coming, the tower is transmuted, glorified;
    every stone of it is aglow with mystic light; it is made the abode of
    the Lover and the Beloved, it is seen to be a symbol of Love, of an
    ecstasy, remote, and passionate, and eternal, dwelling far from the ways
    of men. Compare these two books, I say again, and you will know the
    chief distinction between fine literature and reading matter. To me, I
    confess, the "Jew-book" has not even interest of the lower sort, not by
    any means the interest of Thackeray, or Jane Austen or even of poor,
    dreary, draggle-tailed George Eliot; but if you are amused by it, I have
    no objection to make. You may be amused by the plates of the "Spring
    and Summer Novelties" in the lady's paper, if you please; but for
    heaven's sake don't come here and tell me that on the whole you prefer
    Botticelli's Primavera! Nay, but the fashion-plates are sometimes very
    nicely done, and they put in backgrounds, and they are trying to give
    the faces some character. Do get it into your head--firmly and
    fixedly--that the camera and the soul of man are two entirely different
    things.
    
    You think the "photographic" comparison unfair, in this and other
    instances, because of the mechanical element in photography, because of
    that camera I have just mentioned? Well, I suppose that it _is_ a little
    misleading. The sun and the camera between them certainly do your
    picture for you, and as you urge, there is more of artifice in the
    merest Sunday-school tale than in the best of photographs. Still, you
    must remember that photography too has its artifice, its choice of the
    right and the wrong way, and its exercise of judgment; there is a great
    deal in it that is not mechanical; and in its essence it is of the same
    class as the books I have been alluding to. The means employed are
    different, and a higher and finer artifice is required for making books
    than for taking photographs, but the end of each is the same, and that
    end is to portray the surface of life, to make a picture of the outside
    of things. It is on this ground that I defend my use of the analogy, and
    you must understand me to speak only of the object which is common to
    each, when I compare the secondary writer to a photographer. The
    writers, to be sure, have invention in a greater or less degree, but you
    will remark that the artists in literature have the power of creation, a
    totally different process. Invention is the finding of a thing in its
    more or less obscure hiding-place; creation is the making of a new
    thing, the invocation of Something from Nothingness. Don Quixote is a
    creation; the clergyman in "Pride and Prejudice" is an invention,
    Colonel Newcome is, in all probability, a composite portrait, while the
    Jew-Socialist who fell in love with the Baroness is simply a portrait of
    Ferdinand Lassalle.
    
    You must remember that while the two classes--fine literature and
    reading matter--differ the one from the other generically, the
    individuals of each class differ from each other only specifically. Thus
    the difference in merit between the "Odyssey" and "Pickwick" is
    enormous, but it is a specific difference. In the same way it is hard to
    measure with the imagination the difference between "Madame Bovary" and
    that famous Sunday-school story "Jackie's Holiday": the former is
    immensely clever, the latter is immensely silly; but the two are,
    emphatically, of the same genus. In each case the effort of the author
    is to "describe life," the aim of Flaubert is absolutely identical with
    the aim of Miss Flopkins, and their results differ only as the Frenchman
    differs from the Englishwoman, the one being a serious and patient
    artificer while the other is a bungling idiot, who obtrudes her very
    empty personality and her very trashy ethics instead of studiously
    concealing them. Still: a photograph taken in the most famous studio in
    London is still a photograph equally with the spotted and misty effort
    of the amateur, and no amount of "touching-up" or "finishing," however
    patient it may be, will turn a photograph into a work of art. And, in
    like manner, no labour, no care, no polishing of the phrase, no patience
    in investigation, no artifice in plot or in construction will ever make
    "reading-matter" into fine literature.
    
    
    
    
    III
    
    
    I see that I shall be obliged to keep on reiterating the difference
    between fine literature and "literature," or in other words between art
    and observation expressed with artifice. I am afraid, that in your heart
    of hearts, you still believe that the "Odyssey" is fine literature, and
    that "Pride and Prejudice" is fine literature, though the "Odyssey" is
    "better" than "Pride and Prejudice." It is that "better" that I want to
    get out of your head, that monstrous fallacy of comparing Westminster
    Abbey with the charming old houses in Queen Square. You would see the
    absurdity of imagining that there can be any degree of comparison
    between two things entirely different, if I substituted for "Pride and
    Prejudice" some ordinary circulating-library novel of our own times. At
    least I hope you would see, though, as I told you a few weeks ago, I
    doubt very much whether many people realise the distinction between the
    "Odyssey" and a political pamphlet. The general opinion, I expect, is
    that both belong to the same class, though the Greek poem is much more
    "important" than the pamphlet. I think we succeeded in demonstrating the
    falsity of this idea, in showing clearly and decisively that fine
    literature means the expression of the eternal human ecstasy in the
    medium of words, and that it means nothing else whatsoever. Words, it is
    true, are used for other ends than this: they are used in sending
    telegrams to stockbrokers, for example, but why should this double
    office create any confusion? A tub and a tabernacle may each be made of
    wood, but you don't mix the two things up on that account? The other day
    you gave me a most amusing account of your landlady's quarrels with her
    servant girls. I remember that I laughed consumedly, and at the moment,
    that solemn preconisation of the servant Mabel to the effect that her
    mistress, Mrs Stickings, was not a "lydy," was more to my taste than the
    recitation of the "Ode on a Grecian Urn." But you surely didn't think
    that you were making literature all the while? Or that the history of
    Mrs Stickings and Mabel would have mysteriously become literature if you
    had written it down and got somebody to print it? Or that it would have
    been literature if some of the details had been a little exaggerated (I
    thought you had embroidered here and there); or if you had made the
    whole story up out of your own head? Exactly, you were, as you say,
    amusing me by the relation of facts a little altered, compressed, and
    embellished, and I am glad that you see that no process of writing or
    printing, no variation in the proportion of truth and invention, even to
    the total lack of all truth, could have changed an amusing presentation
    of the Stickings _ménage_ into fine literature. But, surely, it is so
    very obvious. Did any cook ever think that he could change a turkey into
    a bird of paradise by careful attention to the _farse_ and the sauce?
    The farmer might as well expect to breed early phoenixes for Leadenhall
    Market by the simple process of lighting a bonfire in the farmyard. The
    young ducks would jump into the blaze, and the transformation would be
    the work of a second! There is no more madness in _that_ notion than in
    the other one--that one has only to print an amusing, interesting,
    life-like, or pathetic tale to make it into fine literature.
    
    Yes; but what I am afraid is still lurking somewhere in your skull is
    this: that if only the stuffing is extremely well made, if only the
    sauce is an exquisite concoction, the turkey _is_, somehow or other,
    changed into a bird of paradise. That is, to translate the analogy, if
    only the plot is very ingenious, if only the construction is well
    carried out, if the characters are extremely life-like, if the English
    is admirably neat and sufficient, then reading-matter becomes fine
    literature. Make the bonfire high enough and your young ducks will be
    burned into phoenixes fast enough; let the artifice be sufficiently
    artificial and it will be art. Indeed you might as well maintain that a
    wooden statue, if it be really well carved, is thereby made into a gold
    statue.
    
    Well, I remember saying one night that you were here that ecstasy is at
    once the most exquisite of emotions and a whole philosophy of life. And
    it is to the philosophy of life that we are brought, in the last resort.
    You know that there are, speaking very generally, two solutions of
    existence; one is the materialistic or rationalistic, the other, the
    spiritual or mystic. If the former were true, then Keats would be a
    queer kind of madman, and the "Morte d'Arthur" would be an elaborate
    symptom of insanity; if the latter is true, then "Pride and Prejudice"
    is not fine literature, and the works of George Eliot are the works of
    a superior insect--and nothing more. You must make your choice: is the
    story of the Graal lunacy, or not? You think it is not: then do not talk
    any more of turning glass into diamonds by careful polishing and
    cutting. Do not say: Mr A. spends five years over a book, and therefore
    what he writes is fine literature; Miss B. polishes off five novels in a
    year, and therefore she does not write fine literature. Do not say, Mr
    Shorthouse has got the name of a man who kept a private school in the
    time of Charles I. quite right; therefore "John Inglesant" is fine
    literature, while the archæological details in "Ivanhoe" are all wrong,
    therefore it is not fine literature. Good Lord! You might as well say:
    but my landlady's name is Mrs Stickings, and the girl (who left last
    month) was really called Mabel; _therefore_ that story of mine was fine
    literature. What's that about sustained effort? Can you turn a deal
    ladder into a golden staircase by making it of a thousand rungs? What I
    say three times is right, eh? and if I tell the tale of Mrs Stickings so
    that it extends to "our minimum length for three volume novels," it
    becomes fine literature.
    
    Well, I really hope that we have at last settled the matter; that fine
    literature is simply the expression of the eternal things that are in
    man, that it is beauty clothed in words, that it is always ecstasy, that
    it always draws itself away, and goes apart into lonely places, far from
    the common course of life. Realise this, and you will never be misled
    into pronouncing mere reading-matter, however interesting, to be fine
    literature; and now that we clearly understand the difference between
    the two, I propose that we drop the "fine" and speak simply of
    literature.
    
    But I assure you that, even after having established the grand
    distinction, it is by no means plain sailing. Everything terrestrial is
    so composite (except, perhaps, pure music) that one is confronted by an
    almost endless task of distinguishing matter from form, and body from
    spirit. Literature, we say, is ecstasy, but a book must be written about
    something and about somebody; it must be expressed in words, it must
    have arrangement and artifice, it must have accident as well as essence.
    Consider "Don Quixote" as an example; it is, I suppose, the finest prose
    romance in existence. Essentially, it expresses the eternal quest of the
    unknown, that longing, peculiar to man, which makes him reach out
    towards infinity; and he lifts up his eyes, and he strains his eyes,
    looking across the ocean, for certain fabled, happy islands, for Avalon
    that is beyond the setting of the sun. And he comes into life from the
    unknown world, from glorious places, and all his days he journeys
    through the world, spying about him, going on and ever on, expecting
    beyond every hill to find the holy city, seeing signs, and omens, and
    tokens by the way, reminded every hour of his everlasting citizenship.
    "From the great deep to the great deep he goes": it is true of King
    Arthur and of each one of us; and this, I take it, is the essence of
    "Don Quixote," and of all his forerunners and successors. Then, in the
    second place, you get the eternal moral of the book, and you will
    understand that I am not using "moral" in the vulgar sense. The eternal
    moral, then, of "Don Quixote" is the strife between temporal and
    eternal, between the soul and the body, between things spiritual and
    things corporal, between ecstasy and the common life. You read the book
    and you see that there is a perpetual jar, you are continually
    confronted by the great antinomy of life. It seems a mere comic
    incident when the knight dreaming of enchantment is knocked about, and
    made ridiculous; but I tell you it is the perpetual tragedy of life
    itself, symbolised. I say that it is, under a figure, the picture of
    humanity in the world, that you will find the truth it represents
    repeated again and again throughout all history. You know that if one
    goes back resolutely to the first principles of things, one finds
    oneself, as it were, in a place where all lines that seemed parallel and
    eternally divided meet, and so it is with this tragedy symbolised by the
    Don Quixote. It is, you may say, the tragedy of the Unknown and the
    Known, of the Soul and Body, of the Idea and the Fact, of Ecstasy and
    Common Life; at last, I suppose, of Good and Evil. The source of it lies
    far beyond our understanding, but its symbol is shown again and again in
    Cervantes's page.
    
    Then, there is a third element in the book. The author intended to write
    a burlesque on the current romances of chivalry; and he wrote, I
    suppose, the best burlesque that has ever been written, or ever will be
    written. If you unhappily so choose, you can shut your eyes to
    everything serious and everything beautiful, and read merely of Amadis
    and Arthur "taken off," of the highest ideals turned into nonsense, of
    the best motives shown to be, in effect, mischievous. You will read how
    the knight, in the approved manner of knights, helped the oppressed and
    the wretched, and how he usually worsened their condition tenfold. You
    may lend your ear to Sancho, grumbling and quoting "common-sense"
    proverbs all the road, as he rides on his ass, and if it were not for
    the wit and the comedy, you might fancy yourself in a suburban train
    bound for the city. Why, if you so please, "Don Quixote" is the
    Institute of cynicism, the reduction of every generous impulse to
    absurdity.
    
    Finally, the knight is the mouthpiece of Cervantes himself, especially
    towards the end of the second part, where the armour and the fantasy
    drop off, piece by piece, and shred by shred, on that mournful, homeward
    journey. At last, I say, Don Quixote is almost simply Cervantes,
    commenting on men and affairs in Spain, and I think that in those final
    chapters the art has vanished together with the armour and the ecstasy.
    Yes, I always dread the ending of "Don Quixote." A star drops a line of
    streaming fire, down the vault of the sky, and perhaps you may have
    seen the ugly, shapeless thing that sinks into the earth.
    
    But this very brief and imperfect analysis of a great masterpiece of
    literary art may give you some idea of the extraordinary complexity of
    all literature. As it is I have omitted one most important item in the
    account; I have said nothing of the style, because, I am sorry to say
    that I have no Spanish, and Cervantes speaks to me through an
    interpreter named Charles Jarvis. But, omitting style, you see that we
    have, in this particular case, five books in one; we have the utterance
    of pure ecstasy, the strife between ecstasy and the common life, the
    burlesque of chivalry, the institutes of cynicism, and the comments on
    affairs. Each of these different themes is managed with consummate
    ability, and (always excepting the last chapters of the book), each
    keeps its due place, so that it really rests with the reader, in a
    manner, to choose which book he is to read.
    
    And then, there are other elements which must be accounted for if one is
    to judge a book as a whole, fairly and thoroughly. I may be so charmed
    with the writer's rapture, with the wonder and beauty of his idea, that
    I may forget the fact that the artist must also be the artificer; that
    while the soul conceives, the understanding must formulate the
    conception, that while ecstasy must suggest the conduct of the story,
    common-sense must help to range each circumstance in order, that while
    an inward, mysterious delight must dictate the burning phrases and sound
    in the music and melody of the words, cool judgment must go through
    every line, reminding the author that, if literature be the language of
    the Shadowy Companion it must yet be translated out of the unknown
    speech into the vulgar tongue. Here then we have the elements of a book.
    Firstly the Idea or Conception, the thing of exquisite beauty which
    dwells in the author's soul, not yet clothed in words, nor even in
    thought, but a pure emotion. Secondly, when this emotion has taken
    definite form, is made incarnate as it were, in the shape of a story,
    which can be roughly jotted down on paper, we may speak of the Plot.
    Thirdly, the plot has to be systematised, to be drawn to scale, to be
    carried out to its legitimate conclusions, to be displayed by means of
    Incident; and here we have Construction. Fourthly, the story is to be
    written down, and Style is the invention of beautiful words which shall
    affect the reader by their meaning, by their sound, by their mysterious
    suggestion.
    
    This, then, is the fourfold work of literature, and if you want to be
    perfect you must be perfect in each part. Art must inspire and shape
    each and all, but only the first, the Idea, is pure art; with Plot, and
    Construction, and Style there is an alloy of artifice. If then any given
    book can be shown to proceed from an Idea, it is to be placed in the
    class of literature, in the shelf of the "Odyssey" as I think I once
    expressed it. It may be placed very high in the class; the more it have
    of rapture in its every part, the higher it will be: or, it may be
    placed very low, because, for example, having once admired the
    Conception, the dream that came to the author from the other world, we
    are forced to admit that the Story or Plot was feebly imagined, that the
    Construction was clumsily carried out, that the Style is, æsthetically,
    non-existent. You will notice that I am never afraid of blaming my
    favourites, of finding fault with the books which I most adore. I can do
    so freely and without fear of consequences, since having once applied my
    test, and having found that "Pickwick," for example, is literature, I
    am not in the least afraid that I shall be compelled to eat my words if
    flaws in plot and style and construction are afterwards made apparent.
    The statue is gold; we have settled that much, and we need not fear that
    it will turn into lead, if we find that the graving and carving is poor
    enough. Once be sure that your temple _is_ a temple, and I will warrant
    you against it being suddenly transmuted into a tub, through the
    discovery of scamped workmanship.
    
    Well, suppose we begin to apply our analysis. Let us take the strange
    case of Mr R. L. Stevenson, and especially his "Jekyll and Hyde," which,
    in some ways, is his most characteristic and most effective book. Now I
    suppose that instructed opinion (granting its existence) was about
    equally divided as to the class in which this most skilful and striking
    story was to be placed. Many, I have no doubt, gave it a very high place
    in the ranks of imaginative literature, or (as we should now say) in the
    ranks of literature; while many other judges set it down as an extremely
    clever piece of sensationalism, and nothing more. Well, I think both
    these opinions are wrong; and I should be inclined to say that "Jekyll
    and Hyde" just scrapes by the skin of its teeth, as it were, into the
    shelves of literature, and no more. On the surface it would seem to be
    merely sensationalism; I expect that when you read it, you did so with
    breathless absorption, hurrying over the pages in your eagerness to find
    out the secret, and this secret once discovered, I imagine that "Jekyll
    and Hyde" retired to your shelf--and stays there, rather dusty. You have
    never opened it again? Exactly. I _have_ read it for a second time, and
    I was astonished to find how it had, if I may say so, evaporated. At the
    first reading one was enthralled by mere curiosity, but when once this
    curiosity had been satisfied what remained? If I may speak from my own
    experience, simply a rather languid admiration of the ingenuity of the
    plot with its construction, combined with a slight feeling of
    impatience, such as one might experience if one were asked to solve a
    puzzle for the second time. You see that the secret once disclosed, all
    the steps which lead to the disclosure become, _ipso facto_,
    insignificant, or rather they become nothing at all, since their only
    significance and their only existence lay in the secret, and when the
    secret has ceased to be a secret, the signs and cyphers of it fall also
    into the world of nonentity. You may be amazed, and perplexed, and
    entranced by a cryptogram, while you are solving it, but the solution
    once attained, your cryptogram is either nothing or perilously near to
    nothingness.
    
    Well, all this points, doesn't it, towards mere sensationalism, very
    cleverly done? But, as I said, I think "Jekyll and Hyde" just scrapes
    over the border-line and takes its place, very low down, among books
    that are literature. And I base my verdict solely on the Idea, on the
    Conception that lies, buried rather deeply, beneath the Plot. The
    plot, in itself, strikes me as mechanical--this actual physical
    transformation, produced by a drug, linked certainly with a theory of
    ethical change, but not linked at all with the really mysterious, the
    really psychical--all this affects me, I say, as ingenious mechanism and
    nothing more; while I have shown how the construction is ingenious
    artifice, and the style is affected by the same plague of laboured
    ingenuity. Throughout it is a thoroughly conscious style, and in
    literature all the highest things are unconsciously, or at least,
    subconsciously produced. It has music, but it has no under-music, and
    there are no phrases in it that seem veils of dreams, echoes of the
    "inexpressive song." It is on the conception, then, alone, that I
    justify my inclusion of "Jekyll" amongst works of art; for it seems to
    me that, lurking behind the plot, we divine the presence of an Idea, of
    an inspiration. "Man is not truly one, but truly two," or, perhaps, a
    polity with many inhabitants, Dr Jekyll writes in his confession, and I
    think that I see here a trace that Mr Stevenson had received a vision of
    the mystery of human nature, compounded of the dust and of the stars, of
    a dim vast city, splendid and ruinous as drowned Atlantis deep beneath
    the waves, of a haunted quire where a flickering light burns before the
    Veil. This, I believe, was the vision that came to the artist, but the
    admirable artificer seized hold of it at once and made it all his own,
    omitting what he did not understand, translating roughly from the
    unknown tongue, materialising, coarsening, hardening. Don't you see how
    thoroughly _physical_ the actual plot is, and if one escapes for a
    moment from the atmosphere of the laboratory it is only to be confronted
    by the most obvious vein of moral allegory; and from this latter light,
    "Jekyll and Hyde" seems almost the vivid metaphor of a clever preacher.
    You mustn't imagine, you know, that I condemn the powder business as bad
    in itself, for (let us revert for a moment to philosophy) man is a
    sacrament, soul manifested under the form of body, and art has to deal
    with each and both and to show their interaction and interdependence.
    The most perfect form of literature is, no doubt, lyrical poetry which
    is, one might say, almost pure Idea, art with scarcely an alloy of
    artifice, expressed in magic words, in the voice of music. In a word, a
    perfect lyric, such as Keats's "Belle Dame Sans Mercy" is _almost_ pure
    soul, a spirit with the luminous body of melody. But (in our age, at all
    events) a prose romance must put on a grosser and more material envelope
    than this, it must have incident, corporeity, relation to material
    things, and all these will occupy a considerable part of the whole. To a
    certain extent, then, the Idea must be materialised, but still it must
    always shine through the fleshly vestment; the body must never be mere
    body but always the body of the spirit, existing to conceal and yet to
    manifest the spirit; and here it seems to me that Mr Stevenson's story
    breaks down. The transformation of Jekyll into Hyde is solely material,
    as you read it, without artistic significance; it is simply an
    astounding incident, and not an outward sign of an inward mystery. As
    for the possible allegory I have too much respect for Mr Stevenson as an
    artificer to think that he would regard this element as anything but a
    very grave defect. Allegory, as Poe so well observed, is always a
    literary vice, and we are only able to enjoy the "Pilgrim's Progress" by
    forgetting that the allegory exists. Yes, that seems to me the _vitium_
    of "Jekyll and Hyde": the conception has been badly realised, and by
    badly I do not mean clumsily, because from the logical, literal
    standpoint, the plot and the construction are marvels of cleverness; but
    I mean inartistically: ecstasy, which as we have settled is the synonym
    of art, gave birth to the idea, but immediately abandoned it to
    artifice, and to artifice only, instead of presiding over and inspiring
    every further step in plot, in construction, and in style. All this may
    seem to you very fine-drawn and over-subtle, but I am convinced that it
    is the true account of the matter, and perhaps you may realise my theory
    better if I draw out that analogy of "translation" which I suggested, I
    think, a few minutes ago. I was passing along New Oxford Street the
    other day, and I happened to look into a shop which displays Bibles in
    all languages, and I glanced at the French version, open at the seventh
    chapter of the Book of Proverbs. I saw the words "un jeune homme
    dépourvu de bon sens," and then, lower down, "comme un boeuf à la
    boucherie," and it was some considerable time before I realised that
    these phrases "translated," "a young man void of understanding," and "as
    an ox goeth to the slaughter." Now you notice that these are in every
    way commonplace examples; there is nothing extraordinarily poetical in
    either phrase as it stands in the Authorised Version. I might have made
    the contrast much more violent by choosing a passage from the Song of
    Songs or Ecclesiastes; and I wonder how "Therefore with Angels and
    Archangels" would go into French. But isn't the gulf astounding between
    "void of understanding" and "dépourvu de bon sens"? Yet the meaning of
    the French is really the same as the meaning of the English; logically,
    I should think, the two phrases are exactly equivalent. And yet ...
    well, we know perfectly well that "dépourvu de bon sens" in no way
    renders that noble and austere simplicity that we reverence in the
    English text.
    
    Now, I think, you ought to see what I have been trying to express about
    the gulf that may open always between the conception and the plot, or
    story, that does divide the conception from the plot of "Jekyll and
    Hyde." Of course the analogy is not perfect, because the _magnum chaos_
    that yawns between the unformulated Idea and the formulated plot,
    between pure ecstasy and ecstasy _plus_ artifice, is much vaster than
    the distinction between English and French, indeed between the two
    former there is almost or altogether the difference of the infinite and
    the finite, of soul and body; still, you see how a book is a rendering,
    a translation of an Idea, and how a very fine idea may be embodied in a
    very mechanical plot.
    
    You remember the "Socialist and Baroness" novel that we were talking
    about the other night. We placed it outside of literature firstly and
    chiefly because it was not based on ecstasy, on an idea of any kind, and
    secondly, and by way of consequence, because in its execution and detail
    it was so thoroughly insignificant, because it played Hamlet with the
    part of the Prince omitted. Now I think that it is strong evidence of
    the soundness of my literary theory that we are enabled by it to take
    two books so utterly dissimilar in manner and method, in story and
    treatment, and to judge them both by the same scale. For this is what it
    really comes to: we say that the "Tragic Comedians" is not literature
    because it simply tells of facts without their significance, because it
    deals with the outward show and not with the inward spirit, because it
    is accidental and not essential. And in just the same way we say that
    "Jekyll and Hyde" (its conception apart) is not literature inasmuch as
    it too has the body of a story without the soul of a story, the
    incident, the fact, without the inward thing of which the fact is a
    symbol. For if you will consider the matter you will see that a fact
    _qua_ fact has no existence in art at all. It is not the painter's
    business to make us a likeness of a tree or a rock; it is his business
    to communicate to us an emotion--an ecstasy, if you please--and that he
    may do so he uses a tree or a rock as a symbol, a word in his language
    of colour and form. It is not the business of the sculptor to chisel
    likenesses of men in marble; the human form is to him also a symbol
    which stands for an idea. In the same manner it is not the business of
    the literary artist to describe facts--real or imaginary--in words: he
    is possessed with an idea which he symbolises by incident, by a story of
    men and women and things. He is possessed, let us say, by the idea of
    Love: then he must write a story of lovers, but he must never forget
    that A. and B., his actual lovers in the tale, with their social
    positions, their whims and fancies, their sayings and doings are only of
    consequence in the degree that they symbolise the universal human
    passion, which in its turn is a copy of certain eternal and ineffable
    things. If A. and B. do _not_ do this then they are nothing, and worse
    than nothing, so far as art is concerned. "But my tree is like a tree,"
    says the dull painter, and "my anatomy is faultless," says the bad
    sculptor, and "my characters are life-like," says the novelist.
    
    And one can apply exactly the same reasoning to Mr Stevenson's ingenious
    story. I do not know whether there is, or has been, or will be a salt in
    existence which can turn a man into another person; that is of not the
    slightest consequence to the argument. The result of the powder, as it
    is described in the book, is an incident, and it makes no difference to
    the critical judgment whether the incident is true or false, probable or
    improbable. The only point, absolutely the only point is this: is the
    incident significant or insignificant, is it related for its own sake,
    or is it posited because it is a sign, a symbol, a word which veils and
    reveals the artist's ecstasy and inspiration? The socialist fell in love
    with the baroness: it is true, you say, it really happened so in Germany
    some twenty-five years ago. But in the book it is insignificant. The
    doctor took the powder and became another man; it is probably untrue.
    But it is also insignificant; and to the critic of art in literature the
    one incident stands precisely on the same footing as the other.
    
    And, do you know, I am glad I have made this comparison between "Jekyll
    and Hyde" and the "Tragic Comedians," because it has struck me that what
    I have been saying about the essential element of all literature might
    be open to very grave misunderstanding. I have been insisting, with
    reiteration that must have tired you, that there is only one test by
    which literature may be distinguished from mere reading matter, and that
    that test is summed up in the word, ecstasy. And then we admitted a
    whole string of synonyms--desire of the unknown, sense of the unknown,
    rapture, adoration, mystery, wonder, withdrawal from the common
    life--and I daresay I have used many other phrases in the same sense
    without giving you any special warning that it was our old friend again
    in a new guise. But it has just occurred to me that with all this wealth
    of synonyms, I may not have made my meaning perfectly clear. For
    example, while I was laying down the law about Dr Jekyll's powder and
    its effects, you might have interrupted me with the remark: "But I
    thought you said the sense of wonder was characteristic of literature;
    and surely the change from Jekyll into Hyde is extremely wonderful." Or
    again, when I was belauding the "Odyssey," dwelling on the voyage of
    Ulysses amongst strange peoples, you might have put in some modern tale
    of strange adventure, and requested me to distinguish between the two,
    to justify my praise of the old, and rejection of the new. And we have
    mentioned Sunday-school books, always, I think, with a certain _nuance_
    of contempt; but Sunday-school books usually deal with religion, and
    religion and adoration are almost synonymous. And so one could go on
    with the list, making out, on our premises, with our own test, a
    plausible case for books which we know very well are neither literature
    nor anything remotely approaching it. And that would look rather like
    the collapse of our literary case, wouldn't it?
    
    Well, the solution of the difficulty seems to me to be sought for in the
    remarks I was making just now about "facts" in art. I said, you
    remember, that in art, facts as facts have no existence at all. Facts,
    incidents, plots, simply form the artistic speech--its mode of
    expression, or medium--and if there is no idea behind the facts, then
    you have no longer language but gibberish. Just as language is made up
    of the letters of the alphabet, arranged in significant words and
    sentences; so is the artistic language made up of plots, incidents,
    sentences which are informed with significance. If I heap up letters of
    the alphabet, and arrange them in an arbitrary collocation, without
    meaning, I am forming gibberish, and not a language; and so if I pepper
    my pages with extraordinary incidents, without attaching to them any
    significance, I am writing, it may be, an exciting, absorbing,
    interesting book, but I am not making literature. Indeed, some of the
    books that might be mentioned in this connection remind me of a man
    swearing: he uses the holiest names but he does so in such a manner that
    he excites not reverence and awe but disgust and repulsion. Tell the
    bare "plot" of the Odyssey to one of these writers, and hint that it
    might be made into a "successful Christmas book for boys," and he will
    produce you a book which will contain the Lotus-Eaters, and Calypso and
    the Cyclops, but which will have just the same relation to literature as
    blasphemy bears to the Liturgy. That seems to me the explanation; one
    must say again that mere incident is nothing, that it only becomes
    something when it is a symbol of an interior meaning. And, turning this
    maxim inside out, as it were, we shall sometimes find that a book which
    seems on the surface to be "reading matter" is really literature, and
    incidents, apparently insignificant, may turn out, on a closer
    examination, to be significant and symbolic in a very high degree. So I
    don't think our literary criterion is in any way invalidated by the
    occurrence of surprising incidents in very worthless books. Look at "Mr
    Isaacs" for example. In a sense it is a "wonderful" book, inasmuch as
    it contains incidents which are far removed from common experience; but
    you have only to read it to discover that the author had not been
    visited by any inspiration of the unseen. One may trace some
    acquaintance with theosophical "literature," but not even the dimmest
    vision of "the other things." The "other things"? Ah, that is another
    synonym, but who can furnish a precise definition of the indefinable?
    They are sometimes in the song of a bird, sometimes in the scent of a
    flower, sometimes in the whirl of a London street, sometimes hidden
    under a great lonely hill. Some of us seek them with most hope and the
    fullest assurance in the sacring of the Mass, others receive tidings
    through the sound of music, in the colour of a picture, in the shining
    form of a statue, in the meditation of eternal truth. Do you know that I
    can never hear a jangling piano-organ, contending with the roar of
    traffic without the tears--not of feeling but of emotion--coming to my
    eyes?
    
    And that instance--it is grotesque enough--reminds me that I think I
    have an explanation of another puzzle that has often perplexed me, and I
    daresay has perplexed you. Do you remember the books that you read when
    you were a boy? I can think of stories that I read long ago (I have
    forgotten the very names of them) that filled me with emotions that I
    recognised, afterwards, as purely artistic. The sorriest pirate, the
    most wretchedly concealed treasure, poor Captain Mayne Reid at his
    boldest gave me then the sensations that I now search for in the
    "Odyssey" or in the thought of it; and I looked into some of these
    shabby old tales years afterwards, and wondered how on earth I had
    managed to penetrate into "faëry lands forlorn" through such miserable
    stucco portals. And you, you say, extracted somehow or other, from
    Harrison Ainsworth's "Lancashire Witches," that essence of the unknown
    that you now find in Poe, and I expect that everybody who loves
    literature could gather similar recollections.
    
    Well, it would be easy enough to solve the problem by saying that the
    emotions of children are of no consequence and don't count, but then I
    don't think that proposition is true. I think, on the contrary, that
    children, especially young children before they have been defiled by the
    horrors of "education," possess the artistic emotion in remarkable
    purity, that they reproduce, in a measure, the primitive man before he
    was defiled, artistically, by the horrors of civilisation. The ecstasy
    of the artist is but a recollection, a remnant from the childish vision,
    and the child undoubtedly looks at the world through "magic casements."
    But you see all this is unconscious, or subconscious (to a less degree
    it is so in later life, and artists are rare simply because it is their
    almost impossible task to translate the emotion of the sub-consciousness
    into the speech of consciousness), and as you may sometimes see children
    uttering their conceptions in words that are nonsense, or next door to
    it, so nonsense or at any rate very poor stuff suffices with them to
    summon up the vision from the depths of the soul. Suppose we could catch
    a genius at the age of nine or ten and request him to utter what he
    felt; the boy would speak or write rubbish, and in the same way you
    would find that he read rubbish, and that it excited in him an ineffable
    joy and ecstasy. Coleridge was a Bluecoat boy when he read the "poems"
    of William Lisle Bowles, and admired them to enthusiasm, and I am quite
    sure that at some early period Poe had been enraptured by Mrs Radcliffe,
    and we know how Burns founded himself on Fergusson. When men are young,
    the inward ecstasy, the "red powder of projection" is of such efficacy
    and virtue that the grossest and vilest matter is transmuted for them
    into pure gold, glistering and glorious as the sun. The child (and with
    him you may link all primitive and childlike people) approaches books
    and pictures just as he approaches nature itself and life; and a
    wonderful vision appears where many of us can only see the common and
    insignificant.
    
    But all this has been a digression; it has come by the way in a talk
    about worthless and insignificant books. But I think that we should by
    this time have brought our testing apparatus into working order; we
    should be able to criticise any given book on some ground or principle,
    not on the rule of thumb of "it sent me to sleep," or "it kept me
    awake." And I think that what I have already remarked about the
    subconscious element in literature should have answered that question
    about "books with a purpose." As a matter of fact I believe that they
    are mostly trash, but it is not a case for _à priori_ reasoning; you
    must test each book by itself. Mr Stevenson was, I believe, an artist at
    heart, but we have seen how the artificer overcame the artist in "Jekyll
    and Hyde," and in like manner there have been cases of people who were
    artificers, and even preachers, at heart, who were forced to succumb to
    the concealed, subconscious artist, when pen touched paper. For example;
    first logically analyze "Lycidas"; you will be disgusted just as Dr
    Johnson, who had no analysis but the logical, was disgusted. Forget your
    logic, your common-sense, and read it again as poetry; you will
    acknowledge the presence of an amazing masterpiece. An unimportant
    lament over an unimportant personage, constructed on an affected
    pseudo-pastoral plan, full of acrid, Puritanical declamation and abuse,
    wantonly absurd with its mixture of the nymphs and St Peter; it is not
    only wretched in plan but clumsy in construction, the artifice is
    atrocious. And it is also perfect beauty! It is the very soul set to
    music; its austere and exquisite rapture thrills one so that I could
    almost say: he who understands the mystery and the beauty of "Lycidas"
    understands also the final and eternal secret of art and life and man.
    
    
    
    
    IV
    
    
    Do you know that when we last talked _belles lettres_ the whole evening
    went by (or at least I think so) without my saying anything about
    "Pickwick"? I hope you noted the omission in your diary, if you keep
    one, because I find it difficult to talk much about literature, without
    drawing some illustration from that very notable, and curious, and
    unappreciated book. Yes, I maintain the justice of the last epithet in
    spite of circulation, in spite of popularity, and in spite of "Pickwick
    'literature.'" You may like a book very much and read it three times a
    year without appreciating it, and if a great book is really popular it
    is sure to owe its popularity to entirely wrong reasons. There are
    people, you know, who study Homer every day, because he throws so much
    light on the manners and customs of the ancients, and if a book of our
    own time is both great and popular, you may be sure that it is loved for
    its most peccant parts, just as nine people out of ten will recall the
    "Raven" and the "Bells" if the poetry of Edgar Allan Poe is mentioned.
    
    After all, I needn't have excused myself for my constant references to
    Dickens's masterpiece, since I have already informed you that, like
    Coleridge, I love a "cyclical" mode of discoursing; and I honestly think
    that if you want to understand something about the Mysteries or the Fine
    Arts (which are the expression of the mysteries) it is the only way. A
    proposition in Euclid is demonstrated and done with, since nothing can
    be added to a mathematical proof; but literature is different. It is
    many-sided and many-coloured, and variable always; you can consider it
    in half-a-dozen ways, from half-a-dozen standpoints, and from
    half-a-dozen judgments, each of which will be true and perfect in
    itself, and yet each will supplement the other. Two or three weeks ago I
    think I tried to show you what a complex organism any given book
    reveals, if one examines it with a little attention, and if one specimen
    be so curiously and intricately fashioned, you may imagine the
    complexity of the whole subject.
    
    But I have a more particular reason for turning once more to the
    "Posthumous Papers." We have noted that that which at first sight seems
    significant, may turn out to be insignificant, and I think that in
    passing I hinted that the reverse was sometimes the case. Very good; and
    the especial instance that is in my mind is the enormous capacity for
    strong drink exhibited by Mr Pickwick and all his friends and
    associates. Of course you've noticed it; perhaps you have thought it a
    nuisance and a blemish from the artistic standpoint, just as many "good
    people" have found it a nuisance and a blemish from the temperance or
    teetotal standpoint. You may have felt quite certain that a set of men
    who were always drinking brandy and water, and strong ale, and
    milk-punch, and madeira, who constantly drank a great deal too much of
    each and all of these things, would be extremely unpleasant companions
    in private life; I daresay you have been thankful that you never knew Mr
    Pickwick or any of his followers. You know, I expect, by personal
    experience, that a man whose daily life is a pilgrimage from one whiskey
    bar to another is, in most cases, an extremely tedious and unprofitable
    companion; and it is undeniable that the "Pickwickians" rather made
    opportunities for brandy and water than avoided them. And in an
    indirect manner, you feel that all this makes you like the book less.
    
    But (I can no more miss an opportunity of digression than Mr Pickwick
    could keep on the coach if there were a chance of drinking his favourite
    beverage) do you know that there are really people who make their liking
    or disliking of the characters the criterion of literature--of romances,
    I mean? We touched on this some time ago, and I remember saying that in
    the case of such secondary books as Jane Austen's and Thackeray's, it
    was permissible enough to go where one was best amused, that one had a
    right to say, "Yes, the artifice may be the better here, but the
    characters are much more amusing there, and I had rather talk to the
    cosmopolitan whose manners are now and then a little to seek, than to
    the maiden lady in the village, whose decorum is so unexceptionable."
    But I confess that at the time it had not dawned upon me that there are
    people who try to judge fine art--the true literature--on the same
    grounds. I believe, however, that such is the case; I believe, indeed,
    that the egregious M. Voltaire was dimly moved by some such feeling when
    he wrote his famous "criticism" of the prophet Habakkuk. What (he must
    have said to himself) would they think in the _salons_ of a man who
    talked like this:--
    
        And the everlasting mountains were scattered,
        The perpetual hills did bow:
        His ways are everlasting?
    
    Evidently Habakkuk could never hope for a second invitation; and
    _therefore_ he wrote rubbish. And I believe, as I said, that there are
    many people who more or less unconsciously judge literature by this
    measure, by asking, "Would these people be pleasant to meet? would one
    like to hear this kind of thing in one's drawing-room?" And this is well
    enough with secondary books, since they contain nothing but
    "characters," and "incidents," and "scenes," and "facts"; but it is by
    no means well in literature, in which, as we found out, all these things
    are symbols, words of a language, used, not for themselves, but because
    they are significant. Remember our old definition--ecstasy, the
    withdrawal, the standing apart from common life--and you will see that
    we may almost reverse this popular method of judgment, and turn it into
    another test, or rather another way of putting the test, of art. For, if
    literature be a kind of withdrawal from the common atmosphere of life,
    we shall naturally expect to find its utterance, both in matter and
    manner, wholly unsuitable for the drawing-room or the street, and its
    "characters" persons whom we cannot imagine ourselves associating with
    on pleasant or comfortable terms. Neither you nor I would be very happy
    on Ulysses's boat, we should soon become irritated with Don Quixote, we
    should hardly feel at home with Sir Galahad. It is true that all the
    good there is in men is this--that at rare intervals, in certain lonely
    moments of exaltation they do feel for the time a faint stirring of the
    beautiful within them, and _then_ they would adventure on the Quest of
    the Graal; but as you know few of us are saints, fewer, perhaps, are men
    of genius; we are sunk for the most part of our days in the common life,
    and our care is for the body and for the things of the body, for the
    street and the drawing-room, and not for the perpetual, solitary hills.
    So you see that if you read a book and can say of the characters in it:
    "I wish I knew them," there is very strong reason to suspect that the
    book in question is not literature, though it may well be a pleasant
    picture of pleasant people.
    
    Yes, I was expecting that question. I should have been sorry if your
    sense of humour had _not_ prompted you to ask whether the drinking of
    too much milk-punch constituted a withdrawal from the common life, a
    profound and lonely ecstasy. But don't you remember that when we were
    discussing "Pickwick" before, and comparing it with the "Odyssey," I
    suddenly deserted Homer, and brought in Sophocles? I think I contrasted,
    very briefly, the education of the dramatist with the education of the
    romance writer, the London of the 'twenties and 'thirties with the city
    of the Violet Crown, the fate of him,
    
        ~aei dia lamprotatou
         bainontos habrôs aitheros~
    
    with that of the other who tried to find the way through the evil and
    hideous London fog.
    
    Well, you might have been inclined to ask, why Sophocles? But do you
    remember for whose festivals, in whose honour the Greek wrote his dramas
    and his choral songs? It was the god of wine who was worshipped and
    invoked at the Dionysiaca, in the praise of Dionysus the chorus sang and
    danced about the altar, and all the drama arose from the celebration of
    the Bacchic mysteries. So you get, I think, a pretty fair proportion: as
    the Athens of Sophocles is to the Cockneydom of Dickens, so is the cult
    of Dionysus to the cult of cold punch and brandy and water. The interior
    meaning is in each case the same; the artistic expression has lamentably
    deteriorated, in the degree that the artistic atmosphere on the banks of
    Fleet Ditch, the "mother of dead dogs," was inferior to the artistic
    atmosphere on the banks of the Ilissus.
    
    I expect you have gathered from all this talk the point I want to make:
    that the brandy and water and punch business in "Pickwick," which at
    first sight seems trivial and insignificant and even disgusting, is, in
    fact, full of the highest significance. Don't you notice the insistence
    with which the writer dwells on drinking, the unction and enthusiasm
    with which he describes it? We have admitted the poverty of the
    "materials" with which Dickens works, and of course it would be as idle
    to expect him to write a choral song in honour of Dionysus as it would
    be to expect him to write in Greek. He expressed himself as best he
    could, in the "language" (that is with the incidents and in the
    atmosphere) that he knew, but there can be no possible doubt as to his
    meaning. In a word, I absolutely identify the "brandy and water scenes"
    with the Bacchic cultus and all that it implies.
    
    This is "a little too much for you" is it? Well, let us take another
    well-known book, the "Gargantua" and "Pantagruel." You know it well, and
    I have only to remind you of the name to remind you that as "Pickwick"
    has been said to "reek with brandy and water," so does Rabelais
    assuredly reek of wine. The history begins:--
    
         "Grandgousier estoit bon raillard en son temps, aimant à boire
         net,"
    
    it ends with the Oracle of the Holy Bottle, with the word
    
         "_Trinch_ ... un mot panomphée, celebré et entendu de toutes
         nations, et nous signifie, _beuvez_;"
    
    and I refer you to the allocution of Bacbuc, the priestess of the
    Bottle, at large. "By wine," she says, "is man made divine," and I may
    say that if you have not got the key to these Rabelaisian riddles much
    of the value--the highest value--of the book is lost to you. You know
    how they drink, those strange figures, the giants and their followers,
    you know the aroma of the vintage, the odour of the wine vat that fills
    all those marvellous and enigmatic pages, and I tell you that here again
    I recognise the same signs as in "Pickwick," the same music as that of
    the dithyrambic choruses in honour of Dionysus, which were eventually
    amplified into that magnificent literary product, the Greek drama. And
    if we wish to penetrate the secret we must not forget the Hebrew
    psalmist, with his _calix meus inebrians quam præclarus est_. And
    remember, too, if you feel inclined to shudder at the milk-punch, that
    the words which I have just quoted might be rendered, "how splendid is
    this cup of wine that makes me drunk!" and we may say that, in a manner,
    poor Dickens did so render them, since, as I have reminded you he
    belonged, after the flesh, to the Camden Town of the 'twenties, and was
    forced to use its unbeautiful dialect because he knew no other.
    
    And after all, then, what does this Bacchic cultus mean? We have seen
    that under various disguises the one spirit appeared in Greece, in the
    France of the Renaissance, and in Victorian England, and that in each
    instance there is an apparent glorification of drunkenness. The Greeks,
    indeed, a sober people by necessity, as all Southerners are,
    impersonated the genius of intoxication, and made excessive drinking, as
    it would seem, an elaborate religion, with rites and festivals and
    mysteries. The Tourainian, whose personal habit was that not of a
    drunkard, but of a learned physician and restorer of ancient letters,
    who probably drank very much in the manner of the good curé I once knew
    ("My God!" he said to me, after the third small glass of small white
    wine, "'tis a veritable debauch!"), has, on the face of it, dedicated
    all his enormous book to the same cause, so that to read Pantagruel is
    like walking through a French village in the vintage season, when the
    whole world, as Zola unpleasantly and nastily expresses it "pue le
    raisin." Thirdly, Dickens, who loved to talk of concocting gin-punch,
    and left it, when concocted, to be drunk by his guests, shows us Mr
    Pickwick "dead drunk" in the wheel-barrow. And, for a final touch of
    apparent absurdity, you remember that the Dionysus myth represents wine
    as a civilising influence! You may well think of the public-house at
    the corner, and ask yourself how strong drink can contribute to
    civilisation.
    
    Well, that is, in very brief outline, the problem and the puzzle; and I
    may say at once that to the literalist, the rationalist, the materialist
    critic, the problem is quite insoluble. But to you and me, who do not
    end in any kind of _ist_, the enigma will not be quite so hopeless. Let
    us get back to our maxim that, in literature, facts and incidents are
    not present for their own sake but as symbols, as words of the language
    of art; it will follow, then, that the incidents of the Dionysus myth,
    the incidents of "Pantagruel" and "Pickwick" are not to be taken
    literally, but symbolically. We are not to conclude that the Greeks were
    a race of drunkards, or that Rabelais and Dickens preached habitual
    excess in drink as the highest virtue; we are to conclude that both the
    ancient people and the modern writers recognised Ecstasy as the supreme
    gift and state of man, and that they chose the Vine and the juice of the
    Vine as the most beautiful and significant symbol of that Power which
    withdraws a man from the common life and the common consciousness, and
    taking him from the dust of the earth, sets him in high places, in the
    eternal world of ideas. And, after all, I cannot do better than quote at
    length the sermon of Bacbuc, priestess of the Dive Bouteille.
    
         "Et icy maintenons que non rire, ains boire, est le propre de
         l'homme: je ne dis boire simplement et absolument, car aussi bien
         boivent les bestes: je dis boire vin bon et frais. Notez, amis, que
         de vin, divin on devient: et n'y a argument tant seur, ni art de
         divination moins fallace. Vos academiques l'afferment, rendans
         l'etymologie de vin lequel ils disent en Grec ~OINOS~, estre comme
         _vis_, force, puissance. Car pouvoir il a d'emplir l'ame de toute
         verité, tout savoir et philosophie. Si avez noté ce qui est en
         lettres Ioniques escrit dessus la porte du temple, vous avez peu
         entendre qu'en vin est verité cachée."
    
    You see how that passage lights up the whole book, and you see what
    Rabelais meant in the Prologue to the first book by that reference to
    "certain little boxes such as we see nowadays in apothecaries' shops,
    the which boxes are painted on the outside with joyous and fantastic
    figures ... but within they hold rare drugs, as balm, ambergris, amomum,
    musk, civet, certain stones of high virtue, and all manner of precious
    things." I do not know whether you have read any of our English
    commentators on Rabelais, if not, I would not advise you to do so,
    unless you take pleasure in futility. For instance they take the passage
    from the prologue, and seeing the hint that something is concealed, try
    by some complicated chain of argument to show that Rabelais veiled his
    attacks on the Church under a mask of "wild buffoonery." Of course the
    attacks on the Church (the "secondary" and comparatively unimportant
    element in the book, fairly answering to the attacks on books of
    Chivalry in the Don Quixote) are as open as any attack can well be, and
    anyone who finds a veil drawn between Rabelais' dislike for the clergy
    and his expression of it must have a very singular notion of what
    constitutes concealment, and a still more singular misapprehension of
    the motive-forces which make and shape great books. Art, you may feel
    quite assured, proceeds always from love and rapture, never from hatred
    and disdain, and satire of every kind _qua_ satire is eternally
    condemned to that Gehenna where the pamphlets, the "literature of the
    subject," and the "life-like" books lie all together. In "Don Quixote"
    one perceives that Cervantes loved the romances he condemns, and the
    satire is therefore good-humoured, and, one may say, does his book
    little harm or none at all; but Rabelais had been harshly treated by the
    friars, and his consequent ill-humour, his very violent abuse _are_ in
    disaccord with the eternal melodies which may be discerned in
    "Pantagruel," noted there under strange symbols. Yes, the satire in
    Rabelais is an "accident," which one has to accept and to make the best
    of; some of it is amusing enough, "joyous and fantastic," like the "apes
    and owls and antiques" that adorn the little boxes of the apothecaries,
    some of it is a little acrid, as I said; but let us never forget that
    the essence of the book is its splendid celebration of ecstasy, under
    the figure of the vine.
    
    You know I have not opened the door; I have only put the key into your
    hands, in this as in other instances. There are things, which, strange
    to say, are better left unsaid, and this, no doubt, Rabelais perceived
    when he devised his symbolism and set many traps in the paths of the
    shallow commentator. It was not from dread of the consequences of
    attacking the clergy that he devised curious veils and concealments,
    since, as I have noted, his hatred of the church is quite open and
    unconcealed. He chose the method of symbolism, firstly because he was
    an artist, and symbolism is the speech of art; and secondly because the
    high truth that he prophesied was not, and is not, fit for vulgar ears.
    The secret places of the human nature are not heedlessly to be exposed
    to the uninitiated, who would merely profane this occult knowledge if
    they had it. By consequence the "Complete Works of Rabelais" are
    obtainable in Holywell Street, and many, seeking the libidinous, have
    found merely the tiresome, and have cursed their bargain.
    
    No, I will positively say no more. The key is in your hands, and with it
    you may open what chambers you can. There is only this to be mentioned:
    that, if I were you, I would not be "afraid with any amazement" should
    Mr Pickwick's overdose of milk punch prove, ultimately, a clue to the
    labyrinth of mystic theology.
    
    There are, however, one or two minor points in Rabelais that may be
    worth notice. I might, you know, analyze it as I attempted to analyze
    "Don Quixote." There is in "Gargantua" and "Pantagruel" that same
    complexity of thought and construction: you may note, first of all, the
    great essence which is common to these masterpieces as to all
    literature--ecstasy, expressed in the one case under the similitude of
    knight-errantry, in the other by the symbol of the vine. Then, in
    Rabelais you have another symbolism of ecstasy--the shape of
    _gauloiserie_, of gross, exuberant gaiety, expressing itself by
    outrageous tales, outrageous words, by a very cataract of obscenity, if
    you please, if only you will notice how the obscenity of Rabelais
    transcends the obscenity of common life; how grossness is poured out in
    a sort of mad torrent, in a frenzy, a very passion of the unspeakable.
    Then, thirdly, there is the impression one collects from the book: a
    transfigured picture of that wonderful age: there is the note of the
    vast, interminable argument of the schools, and for a respond, the
    clear, enchanted voice of Plato; there is the vision, there is the
    mystery of the vast, far-lifted Gothic quire; and those fair, ornate,
    and smiling _châteaux_ rise smiling from the rich banks of the Loire and
    the Vienne. The old tales told in farmhouse kitchens in the Chinonnais,
    the exultation of the new learning, of lost beauty recovered, the joy of
    the vintage, the old legends, the ancient turns of speech, the new style
    and manner of speaking: so to the old world answers the new. Then one
    has the satire of clergy and lawyers--the criticism of life--analogous,
    as I said with much that is in Cervantes, and so from divers elements
    you see how a literary masterpiece is made into a whole.
    
    But now, do you know, I am going to make a confession. You have heard me
    say more than once that in art, in literature properly so called, liking
    and disliking count for nothing. We have understood, I think, that when
    once amusing reading matter has been put out of court, the question of
    how often, with what absorption one reads a work of art, matters
    nothing. Well, I want to contradict, or rather to modify that axiom; we
    have been speaking of three great books, each of which I believe firmly
    to be true literature--"Pickwick," "Don Quixote," and "Pantagruel." Here
    is my confession. I read "Pickwick," say, once a year, "Don Quixote,"
    once every three years, while I read Rabelais in fragments perhaps once
    in six years. You might suppose that I have indicated the order of
    merit? Well, I have, but you must reverse the order, since I firmly
    believe that "Pantagruel" is the finest of the three. We will leave
    Dickens out of account, since we are agreed that though the message was
    that of angels, the accent and the speech were of Camden town; he, that
    is to say, approaches most nearly to the common life, to the common
    passages in which we live, and hence he, naturally, pleases us the most
    in our ordinary and common humours. But, of the other two, I confess
    that Cervantes pleases me much the more; the vulgarity of Dickens is
    absent or rather it is concentrated in Sancho, in a much milder form
    than that of "Pickwick," for a Spanish peasant of the sixteenth century,
    with all his "common-sense," and practical reason, is less remote from
    beauty than the retired "business man" of the early nineteenth century;
    just as poor Mr Pickwick, an honest, kindly creature, is vastly superior
    to the blatant, pretentious, diamond-bedecked swindlers who represent
    the city in our day. But Cervantes, who lacks, as I say, the
    "commonness" of Dickens, has something of the urbanity, the
    cosmopolitanism of Thackeray, he is, to a certain degree, a Colonel
    Newcome of his time, but he has seen the world more sagaciously than
    Colonel Newcome ever could. So while Rabelais appals me with his
    extravagance, his torrents of obscene words, I am charmed with the good
    humoured and observant companionship of Cervantes.
    
    And hence I conclude that "Pantagruel" is the finer book. It may sound
    paradoxical to say so, but don't you see that the very _grotesquerie_ of
    Rabelais shows a further remove from the daily round, a purer metal,
    less tinged with the personal, material, interest than "Don Quixote."
    Mind you, I find greater deftness, a finer artifice in Cervantes, who I
    think expressed his conception the more perfectly, but I think that the
    conception of Rabelais the higher, precisely because it is the more
    remote. Look at the "Pantagruel"; consider those "lists," that more than
    frankness, that ebullition of grossness, plainly intentional, designed:
    it is either the merest lunacy, or else it is sublime. Don't you
    remember the trite saying "extremes meet," don't you perceive that when
    a certain depth has been passed you begin to ascend into the heights?
    The Persian poet expresses the most transcendental secrets of the Divine
    Love by the grossest phrases of the carnal love; so Rabelais soars above
    the common life, above the streets and the gutter by going far lower
    than the streets and the gutter: he brings before you the highest by
    positing that which is lower than the lowest, and if you have the
    prepared, initiated mind, a Rabelaisian "list" is the best preface to
    the angelic song. All this may strike you as extreme paradox, but it has
    the disadvantage of being true, and perhaps you may assure yourself of
    its truth by recollecting the converse proposition--that it is when one
    is absorbed in the highest emotions that the most degrading images will
    intrude themselves. No; you are right: this is not the psychology of the
    "scientific" persons who write hand-books on the subject, it is not the
    psychology of the "serious" novelists, of those who write the annals of
    the "engaged"; but it happens to be the psychology of man.
    
    I don't know that very much can be made of the signification of the
    characters in "Pantagruel," as I hardly think that Rabelais was anxious
    to be systematic or consistent in delineating them. I believe that there
    are two reasons for the gigantic stature of Pantagruel, or perhaps
    three. The form of the whole story came from popular legends about a
    giant named Gargantua, and that is the first and least important reason.
    Secondly the "giant" conception does something to remove the book from
    common experience; it is a sign-post, warning you _not_ to expect a
    faithful picture of life, but rather a withdrawal from life and from
    common experience, and you are in a position to appreciate the value of
    that motive, since I have never ceased from telling you that it is the
    principal motive of all literature. And, thirdly, I hesitate and doubt,
    but nothing more, whether the giant Pantagruel, he who is "all thirst"
    and ever athirst, may not be a hint of the stature of the perfect man,
    of the ideal man, freed from the bonds of the common life, and common
    appetites, having only the eternal thirst for the eternal vine.
    Candidly, I am inclined to favour this view, but only as a private
    interpretation; it may be all nonsense, and I shall not be offended or
    surprised if you can prove to me that it is nonsense. But have you
    noticed how Pantagruel is at once the most important and the least
    important figure in the book? He is the most important personage; he is
    the hero, the leader, the son of the king, the giant, wiser than any or
    all of his followers: formally, he is to Rabelais that which Don Quixote
    is to Cervantes. And yet, actually, he is little more than a vague,
    tremendous shadow; the living, speaking, impressive personages are
    Frère Jean and Panurge, who occupy the stage and capture our attention.
    Doesn't this rather suggest to you the part played by the "real" man in
    life itself; a subordinate, unobtrusive part usually, hidden very often
    by an exterior, which bears little resemblance to the true man within.
    You know Coleridge says that:--
    
    "Pantagruel is the Reason; Panurge the Understanding--the pollarded man,
    the man with every faculty except the reason. I scarcely know an example
    more illustrative of the distinction between the two. Rabelais had no
    mode of speaking the truth in those days but in such form as this; as it
    was, he was indebted to the king's protection for his life."
    
    I must cavil at the last sentence, in which Coleridge seems to hint that
    Rabelais was in danger because he had hinted the distinction between the
    Reason and the Understanding. With all respect to Coleridge, Rabelais
    might have gone to the limits of psychology and metaphysics without
    incurring any danger; he was threatened on account of his very open
    satire of the church and the clergy, which, as I have pointed out, is as
    plain spoken as satire well can be. Still, I think that Coleridge,
    using the technical language of German philosophy, had a glimpse of the
    truth, and Mr Besant's remark that Panurge is a careful portrait of a
    man without a soul is virtually the same definition in another
    terminology. As I have already said, I don't think that Rabelais kept
    his characters within the strict limits of consistence--they are only
    significant, perhaps, now and then--and I want to say, again, that I
    speak under correction in this matter, not feeling at all sure of my
    ground. But I am inclined to think that Pantagruel, Panurge, and the
    Monk are not so much three different characters, as the representative
    of man in his three persons. Frère Jean is, perhaps, the natural man,
    the "healthy animal," Panurge is the rational man, and Pantagruel, as I
    said, is the spiritual, or perfect man, who looms, gigantic, in the
    background, almost invisible, and yet all important, and the three are,
    in reality, One. If I may apply the case to our own subject, I may say
    that while Pantagruel conceives the idea, Panurge writes the book, and
    Brother John has the courage to take it to the publishers. The first is
    the artist, the second the artificer, and the third the social being,
    ready to battle for his place in the material world. The giant is
    always calm, since his head is high above earth--_vidit nubes et
    sidera_--but the other two have to face the compromises of life, and
    suffer its defeats. All this may be purely fantastical; and at any rate
    I am sure that anyone who knows his Rabelais could pick many holes in my
    interpretation. For example, I said that the monk was the "healthy
    animal," and Panurge the rational man; but there are occasions when
    Panurge assumes the character of the unhealthy beast, the hairy-legged,
    hybrid, creature of the Greek myth, who uses the superior human artifice
    for ends that are wholly bestial or worse than bestial. Still; is this a
    valid objection? Are there not such men in life itself? Is it not,
    perhaps, the peculiar and terrible privilege of humanity that it may, if
    it pleases, prostitute its most holy and most blessed gifts to the worst
    and most horrible uses? And does not each one of us feel that,
    potentially, at all events, there is such a being within him, not
    yielded to, perhaps, for a moment, yet always present, always ready to
    assume the command. The greatest saints, we are told, have suffered the
    most fiery temptations; in other words--Pantagruel is always attended by
    _Panurge diabolicus_. I have talked once or twice of the Shadowy
    Companion, but one must not forget that there is the Muddy Companion
    also; a being often of exquisite wit and deep understanding, but given
    to evil ways if one do not hold him in check.
    
    But, in any case, I think I have shown that the Pantagruel is one of the
    most extraordinary efforts of the human mind, full of "Pantagruelism";
    and that word stands for many concealed and wonderful mysteries.
    
    It is not in the least a "pleasant," or a "life-like," or even an
    "interesting" book; I think that when one knows of the key--or rather of
    the keys--one opens the pages almost with a sensation of dread. So it is
    a book that one consults at long intervals, because it is only at rare
    moments that a man can bear the spectacle of his own naked soul, and a
    vision that is splendid, certainly, but awful also, in its constant
    apposition of the eternal heights and the eternal depths.
    
    
    
    
    V
    
    
    I have been waiting for that question for a very long time, and I only
    wonder that you have been able to restrain yourself so well--through
    such a series of what I know you believe to be paradoxes, though I have
    assured you that I deal merely in the plainest truth. But, after all,
    your question is quite a legitimate one, and I remember when I first
    began to think of these things I went astray--simply because I did not
    recognise the existence of the difficulty that has been bothering you,
    ever since that talk of ours about the _haulte sagesse Pantagrueline--et
    Pickwickienne_, and perhaps before it.
    
    Yes, I will put the question in its plainest, crudest form, and I will
    make you ask, if you please, whether Charles Dickens had any
    consciousness of the interior significance of the milk-punch, strong
    ale, and brandy and water which he caused Mr Pickwick and his friends to
    consume in such outrageous quantities. It sounds plain enough and simple
    enough, doesn't it, and yet I must tell you that to answer that
    question fairly you must first analyze human nature, and I needn't
    remind you that _that_ is a task very far from simple. "Man" sounds a
    very simple predicate, as you utter it; you imagine that you understand
    its significance perfectly well, but when you begin to refine a little,
    and to bring in distinctions, and to carry propositions to their
    legitimate bounds, you find that you have undertaken the definition of
    that which is essentially indefinite and probably indefinable. And,
    after all, we need not pitch on this term or on that, there is no need
    to select "man" as offering any especial difficulty, for, I take it,
    that the truth is that all human knowledge is subject to the same
    disadvantage, the same doubts and reservations. _Omnia exeunt in
    mysterium_ was an old scholastic maxim; and the only people who have
    always a plain answer for a plain question are the pseudo-scientists,
    the people who think that one can solve the enigma of the universe with
    a box of chemicals.
    
    But all this is a caution--necessary I suppose--that you need not expect
    me to give you a plain, cut and dried answer to your question whether
    literature is a conscious production--or, in more particular form--was
    Dickens aware that by milk-punch he meant ecstasy? I shall "ask you
    another" in the approved Scotch manner. You were telling me that as you
    came along this evening you had to stop for five minutes at the corner
    of the Caledonian Road to watch the exquisite grace of two slum-girls of
    fourteen or fifteen, dancing to the rattling tune of a piano-organ. You
    spoke of the charm of their movements--_motus Ionici_, some of them, I
    fear--of the purely æsthetic delight there was in the sight of young
    girls, disguised as horrible little slatterns, leaping and dancing as
    young girls have always leapt and danced, I suppose, from the time of
    the cave-dwellers onwards. Well, but do you suppose that this charm you
    have remarked was conscious? Do you think that Harriet and Emily
    realised that they were of the kin of the ecstatic dancers of all time,
    that they were beautiful because they were naturally expressing by a
    symbol that is universal, the universal and eternal ecstasy of life?
    Look back in your memory for illustrations; I, as you know, am rather
    the enemy of facts, and it is rarely that I am able to support a theory
    by a systematic _catena_ of instances and authorities. But, if one had
    the industry and energy, one might make a most curious history of the
    dance. Remember the Hebrew dances of religious joy, of ecstasy in its
    highest form, remember that strange survival of the choristers' dance
    before the high altar in Spain on certain solemn feasts, a survival
    which has persisted in spite of the strong Roman influences which make
    for rigid uniformity. Think of the Greek Menads and Bacchantes, of the
    Dionysiac chorus in the theatre, of our old English peasants "treading
    the mazes," and dancing round the maypole, of dances at Breton
    _Pardons_, of the fairies, supposed to dance in the forest glade beneath
    the moon. Why, dancing is as much an expression of the human secret as
    literature itself, and I expect it is even more ancient; and Harriet and
    Emily, leaping on the pavement, to that jingling, clattering tune, were
    merely showing that though they were the children of the slum, and the
    step-children of the School Board, they were yet human, and partakers of
    the universal sacrament.
    
    But if you ask, were they conscious of all this, it will be very
    difficult to give a direct answer. I need hardly say that they could not
    have put their very real emotion into the terms I have used--nor perhaps
    into any terms at all--and yet they know the delight of what they do,
    as much as if they had been initiated in all the mysteries. If someone
    with the genius of Socrates for propounding searching questions could
    "corner" Harriet and Emily, and face and overcome that preliminary,
    inevitable "garn," it is possible that he might find that they were
    fully conscious of the reasons why they danced and delighted in dancing;
    just as Socrates demonstrated to the slave that he was perfectly
    acquainted with geometry; but failing a Socrates, and using words in
    their usual senses, I suppose we must say that they are not conscious.
    They dance and leap without calculation, as they eat and drink, and as
    birds sing in springtime; and very much the same answer must be given to
    the similar question as to literature.
    
    I said that to answer the riddle fully and completely, one would have to
    make an analysis of human nature; and, in truth, the problem is simply a
    problem of the consciousness and subconsciousness, and of the action and
    interaction between the two. I will not be too dogmatic. We are in
    misty, uncertain and unexplored regions, and it is impossible to chart
    all the cities and mountains and streams, and fix with the nicety of
    the ordnance survey their several places on the map--but I am strangely
    inclined to think that all the quintessence of art is distilled from the
    subconscious and not from the conscious self; or, in other words, that
    the artificer seldom or never understands the ends and designs and
    spirit of the artist. Our literary architects have all, I think, builded
    better than they knew, and very often, I expect, the draughtsman who
    sees the triumph and enjoys it in his manner, takes all the credit to
    himself, and ludicrously imagines that it is his careful drawing and
    amplification of the sketch, and following the scale, that have created
    the high and holy house of God. There is a queer instance of what I mean
    in Dickens's preface to the later editions of "Pickwick"--I put the book
    up on a high shelf the other day, and I can't be bothered getting it
    down and verifying the quotation--but I believe the author, after
    telling us that the original design was to give opportunities to the
    etcher Seymour, goes on to recapitulate, as it were, the achievements of
    the book, and his list of triumphs is much more amusing than any list in
    Rabelais. The law of imprisonment for debt has been altered! Fleet
    Prison has been pulled down! The School-Board is coming! Lawyers'
    clerks have nicer manners! Parliamentary elections are a little better,
    but they might be better still! and one wonders that he does not
    announce that, in consequence of the publication of "Pickwick," medical
    students have given up brandy for barley-water. It is evident, you see,
    that Dickens thought (or thought that he thought, for it is very
    difficult to be exact) that his masterpiece of the _picaresque_, his
    epitome of Pantagruelism, was written to correct abuses, and looking
    back, many years after its publication, he congratulates himself that
    most of these abuses have been corrected, and (one can almost hear him
    say) _ergo_, it is a very fine book. He was impelled to write this
    nonsense of the preface because he was, by comparison, "educated";
    Harriet, the dancer, would probably tell you, if you succeeded in
    penetrating beyond "garn," that she danced because she liked it; but,
    granting that the poisoning process had been carried out more
    successfully in the case of Emily, she might, conceivably, reply that
    she danced "becos it's 'elthy, and Teacher says as 'ow it cirkilates the
    blood." Emily, you see, obtained the prize for Physiology, as well as
    for French and the Piano-Forte; she is thus enabled to give "reasons,"
    and they are quite as valuable as the "reasons" of Dickens, explaining
    the merits of "Pickwick." You know that pompous old fool Forster, who
    took in Dickens at times, sniffed a little at "Pickwick," and thought
    the later books, with their ingenious plots, and floods of maudlin
    tears, and portentous "character-drawing," immense advances, and I
    suppose the master felt obliged to justify himself for that first
    enterprise--to show that he had not really been inspired, but had
    written a useful tract! You remember he "explains" Stiggins; he warns
    you not to be under any misconceptions, not to suppose that Stiggins
    satirises a, b, or c, since he is only aimed at x, y, and z. Can you
    conceive that a mediæval artist in gurgoyles, having perfected for our
    eternal joy, a splendid grinning creature, lurking on the parapet, and
    having endowed him, greatly to our oblectation, with the tail of a
    dragon, the body of a dog, the feet of an eagle, the head of a bull in
    hysterics, with a Franciscan cowl, by way of finish, should afterwards
    explain that no offence was intended to Father Ambrose, the prior over
    the way?
    
    So it seems fairly plain, doesn't it, that in the case of Dickens, at
    all events, there was no very clear consciousness of what had been
    achieved, and I believe that you would find the rule hold good with
    other artists in a greater or less degree. With Dickens it holds in a
    very high degree, just because there was that tremendous gulf I have so
    often spoken about between his inward and his outward self; because,
    with the soul of rare genius, his intelligence lived in those dreary,
    dusty London streets, because the artificer, even while he carried out
    the artist's commands, understood very little what he was doing. But one
    can trace the same working in other cases. Take the case of Mr Hardy,
    for instance. You remember what I said about his "Two on a Tower"; I
    praised it for its ecstatic passion, for that revelation of a great
    rapture, for its symbolism, showing how one must withdraw from the
    common ways, from the dusty highroad and the swarming street, and go
    apart into high, lonely places, if one would perceive the high, eternal
    mysteries. I did not say so in so many words, but you no doubt saw that
    I was indicating that which is, in my opinion, valuable in Mr Hardy's
    work, that which makes his books literature. And I am sure he would most
    decidedly and entirely disagree with me, and if you want to know why I
    am sure, I refer you to his later books, to his "Tess" and "Jude." You
    know how the "Tess" was talked about, how it remade the author from the
    commercial standpoint, simply because it contained, with many beautiful
    things, many absurd "preachments," much pseudo-philosophy of a kind
    suited to the intelligence of persons who think that "Robert Elsmere" is
    literature. If Mr Hardy had been a conscious artist, if he had
    understood, I mean, what makes the charm and the wonder of "Two on a
    Tower," he could never have adulterated the tale of "Tess" with a
    free-thinking tract, he would never have turned "Jude" into a long
    pamphlet on secondary education for farm labourers, with agnostic notes.
    It is pathetic in the latter book amidst much weary and futile writing
    to come across a passage here and there that shows the artist striving
    for utterance, longing to sing us his incantations, in spite of the
    preacher, who howls him down. Think of that distant vision of Oxford
    from the lonely field, of all those clustering roofs and spires, wet
    with rain, suddenly kindling into glancing, and scintillant fire, at the
    sunset; and then remember, with what sorrow, that this is but an oasis
    in a barren land of blundering argument. It is almost as if literature
    had become "literature"--the "literature of the subject"--and one must
    only rejoice that the artist still lives even if the enemy has shut him
    up in prison. You can trace the struggle all through the book: "Sue" was
    an artistic conception, a very curious but a very beautiful revelation
    of some strange elements in the nature and in the love of women; but how
    difficult it is to detect this--the real Sue--underneath the surface,
    which makes Sue seem the prophetess of the "Woman Question," or whatever
    the contemporary twaddle on the subject was called. Conceive the
    "Odyssey" so handled that it seems like a volume in a "technical series"
    dealing with "Seamanship and Navigation," think what might have happened
    if the Rabelais who had been put in the dark cell of Fontenay-le-Comte
    had completely gained the upper hand, and had silenced that other
    Rabelais--that solitary and rapturous soul who had seen as in a glass
    the marvellous face of man. Well, the five books of the "Pantagruel"
    would have conveyed to us, no doubt with some eloquence and vigour, the
    highly unimportant fact that François Rabelais, runaway Franciscan
    friar, did not like Franciscan friars; and now that the centuries have
    gone by we see how (comparatively) worthless such a book as that would
    have been. Fortunately Pantagruel was too strong for the forces of
    Panurge and Frère Jean combined, and so they have been able to do little
    harm to the book.
    
    And how one wishes that it might be so with Mr Hardy! It is not as if he
    had no "body" for his conceptions; his studies of peasant folk do very
    well as backgrounds for his dramas, though, of course, his work in this
    way, good as it is, is not his element of real value. But it is
    inoffensive always, sometimes amusing, and it might well suffice him in
    his more material moments, when he feels the necessity of descending
    from the solitary heights into the pleasant, populous valleys and
    villages of common life. But his true work is--as it is the work of all
    artists--the shaping for us of ecstasy by means of symbols; and for him
    the symbol which he understands is, no doubt, the passion of love, and
    with it the symbol of red, lonely ploughlands, of deep overshadowed
    lanes that climb the hills and wander into lands that we know not, of
    dark woods that hide a secret, of strange, immemorial barrows where one
    may have communion with the souls of the dead. The passion of love, the
    passion of the hills--no artist could desire more exquisite or
    significant symbols than these, nor need he seek for more beautiful
    forms for the expression of the perfect beauty. And Mr Hardy has chosen
    to be a pamphleteer, to voice for us our poor, ignorant contemporary
    chatter: it is as if an angel's pen were to be occupied in inditing
    "Society Small Talk!"
    
    But it proves the unconsciousness of Mr Hardy's art; and here, by the
    way, I am moved to revert to the case of Rabelais. How far, you may ask,
    was he conscious of what he was saying, and I see you remember that
    passage I quoted from the last book--the splendid declaration of the
    Priestess Bacbuc that "by wine is man made divine." That passage, and
    indeed many other passages in the final chapters, would seem to show
    that the author had worked consciously, and I certainly think the point
    worth our consideration. You will remember that I stated my rule without
    bigotry; I rather proposed it as a pious opinion--to the effect that in
    literature the finest things are not designed. And I confess, that at
    first sight, this matter of Bacbuc and her allocution looks rather like
    an exception to the rule, a proof that Rabelais, at all events,
    understood clearly what he was doing.
    
    Well; it may have been so; for Rabelais was, as I think I have shown, a
    very exceptional man, whom it would be difficult to place in any class.
    But I hardly think this _is_ an instance of the proverbial (and
    fallacious) exception that proves the rule. In the first place I believe
    that some French editors have grave doubts whether Rabelais wrote the
    fifth book at all; but I am not inclined to press this point. _My_ point
    is that the allocution of Bacbuc and all those chapters which describe
    the Oracle of the Holy Bottle are the last in the book--the last words
    of the author; and I am in no way concerned to defend the position that
    an author must always remain unconscious of the work that he has done.
    As a matter of fact I think that always, or almost always, he is
    unconscious while he is writing; but I see no reason why the revelation
    may not come to him afterwards, especially in such a case as the
    "Pantagruel," which was the affair of many years--of a lifetime, indeed.
    In the beginning of production, in the youth, the springtime of artistic
    work, the creative influence prevails, and this, it seems to me, always
    or almost always operates secretly; but in later years the critical
    spirit is apt to assert itself, and this will lead, very naturally,
    to the artist's understanding more plainly the nature of his
    accomplishment. Rabelais had a long, wonderful career; his life was
    full of incident, of violent breaks, and his books were produced at
    intervals, and it seems to me very possible that, towards the end, he
    may have reflected on what he had done, and have understood in part, at
    all events, the sense of the amazing message that he had delivered.
    This, I think, is the explanation of the "Holy Bottle" chapters, and you
    will note that, admirable as criticism, they are inferior as art to
    those astounding early pages where there is no hint of conscious
    workmanship, but rather evidence of a man for whom the world has been
    transformed, who has been visited by an astounding vision. He takes an
    old, popular story about a giant, he takes the vine that flourishes in
    his native Chinonnais, he takes the New Learning that seems to him like
    the New Wine, he takes the gross tale of the farmhouse and the tavern,
    the rank speech of the people, and with these elements, with these
    "facts," he symbolises the revelation that he has received. He writes,
    he writes on, he writes madly, and every line is written in a fury of
    delight; but, I think I may say, there is at the moment of writing, no
    conscious apperception of all that that torrent of words conveys and
    implies. _That_ may well come later; one may well begin with legend:
    "Grandgousier was a good drinker," and end with the interpretation: "All
    truth and every philosophy is contained in wine"; but I believe that if
    Rabelais had perceived this at the beginning he would have been not an
    artist but a philosopher.
    
    Well; if you are content with this comment on Bacbuc, I should like to
    give you a very curious instance of our own day, in which the
    unconscious artist has been subdued by the conscious preacher. You
    remember those very notable books: "Keynotes" and "Discords"? I have not
    seen them for some time, so I am afraid my criticism will be very loose
    and general, but I think that the two volumes mark very well the fatal
    descent from the higher to the lower ground. In the first, it seems to
    me, there is a somewhat slight, but very genuine, note of ecstasy;
    I mean that you can collect a certain distinct image of real
    womanhood--not the laboured, foolish, inane psychology of Mr Meredith
    and those who work with him--not the analysis of the surface, of the
    "society" woman, belonging to a particular grade, and a particular
    period, but of the very woman who remains really the same in all social
    grades and in all ages. I remember thinking when I read "Keynotes" that
    it was a "lonely" book; it hinted, I think, a soul apart, and afar from
    the secondary, tertiary problems of an organised civilisation, and
    though there was an undertone of "preaching" and arguing, the total
    impression was curiously and beautifully artistic. I found, if I
    remember rightly, that subordination of the accidental to the essential
    that I praised in "Two in a Tower," and I am the more convinced that
    this is so by my own recollections. I have forgotten all about social
    conditions, if any such things are indicated; I only think of women and
    of men, of the true, inalterable human nature; and here, it seems to me,
    you have a very high achievement. But the next volume "Discords" took
    distinctly lower ground. The artifice was better, the stories, as
    stories, were told with more skill and more deftness than anything in
    "Keynotes"; but there was no more literature; there was only the
    "literature of the subject." The incidents were no longer symbols of an
    emotion; they had become the basis of an agitation, concerning which my
    curiosity never led me to inquire further: and there you see another
    proof of the unconsciousness of art. If the author of "Keynotes" had
    understood her achievement "Discords" would never have been written. One
    might continue the _catena_ almost _ad infinitum_: would not Wordsworth,
    supposing him to have been a conscious artist, have rather cut off his
    right hand than have suffered such a _magisterium_ as the "Ode on
    Intimations of Immortality" to have the companionship of the enormous
    mass of futility and stupidity which constitutes the greater part of the
    "Complete Works"?
    
    Well, there is the evidence that must guide us in answering the question
    you propounded, and it shows, conclusively enough, I think, that art is
    not, in the ordinary acceptation of the term, a conscious product.
    Perhaps it would be a perilous dogmatism, on the other hand, to
    definitely pronounce it to be unconscious; and I expect we had better
    take refuge in the subconscious, that convenient name for the
    transcendental element in human nature. For myself, I like best my old
    figure of the Shadowy Companion, the invisible attendant who walks all
    the way beside us, though his feet are in the Other World; and I think
    that it is he who whispers to us his ineffable secrets, which we
    clumsily endeavour to set down in mortal language. I think that while
    the artist works he is conscious of joy and of nothing more; he works
    beautifully but he could give no _rationale_ of the process, and when he
    endeavours to explain himself, we are often perplexed by this strange
    spectacle of a man wholly ignorant of his own creation. Consider again
    the grotesqueness of that preface to "Pickwick"; it is really as if a
    great sculptor, congratulated on his achievement, should answer that his
    Venus was indeed beautiful--because it tended to improve the marble
    industry and the general knowledge of anatomy.
    
    And after all the conclusion does return to us from other than literary
    sources. You cannot conceive a builder of the fourteenth century
    hesitating as to the respective merits of Romanesque, Norman, First and
    Second Pointed; to him there was only one possible method, and he built,
    as he spoke, without calculation and without conscious effort, only
    knowing the joy of his work. So indeed we all speak and live when we are
    not bound by convention and acquired usages and manners, and you see
    that art, properly so called, takes its place in the great scheme of
    things; it is no studied contortion, no strange trick acquired by the
    late ingenuity of man, but as "natural" (and as supernatural) as the
    blossoming of a flower, and the singing of the nightingale. Art, indeed,
    is wholly natural, artifice is more or less acquired, the creature of
    reason, of experiment, of systematised intelligence. It is doubtful, I
    suppose, whether the natural, untaught man has of himself, by endowment,
    any artifice at all; doubtful, perhaps, whether, in the beginning, his
    artifice was not the product of his art; whether he did not learn to
    speak with artifice because he had received from nature the art of
    singing; certainly the child, entering the world, has not the inborn
    artifice of the swallow and the bee. This artifice, it seems, man has
    been forced to acquire by slow and painful degrees, and perhaps it only
    differs from the artifice of animals in that it has been aided and
    reinforced by imagination, that is by art, that is by the power the
    human soul possesses of projecting itself into the unknown, and
    adventuring in the realm of nothingness. Man, I mean, could never have
    invented the telephone, had he not first created it, had he not
    conceived the possibility of its existence, when as yet, it was
    non-existent, and so his artifice will always be progressive, and
    distinguished from the artifice of animals.
    
    But art is born with man, and is of the essence, the very differentia of
    man. It is of his very inmost being, and therefore, I suppose, is
    removed from his consciousness simply because it is within and not from
    without. You may say that I have been vague, that I have not solved the
    problem I propounded, that I have not clearly explained whether the
    Greeks knew what they did when they worshipped Dionysus, whether
    Rabelais was conscious of an inner meaning in his praise of wine,
    whether Dickens understood the value of his punch and brandy. But if I
    have been vague it is because man, in the last analysis, is a tremendous
    mystery, because he is a complex being, because he is at once
    Pantagruel, and Panurge, and Frère Jean, because he is both Don Quixote
    and Sancho Panza. In some cases Pantagruel and Panurge seem to speak a
    common language, to be able to communicate the one with the other: if
    Rabelais wrote the "Dive Bouteille" chapters, he certainly understood
    much of that which he had expressed in symbols. Sometimes the two seem
    like foreigners in one home, Pantagruel dictates, and Panurge the scribe
    writes down his words, hardly or not at all comprehending the magic
    symbols that he expresses. So Dickens ludicrously misinterprets his own
    "Pickwick." And, doubtless, this understanding of the artificer of the
    artist varies in an almost infinite chain of _nuances_: there have been
    artists, perhaps, who have worked like men under the influence of
    haschish, who have opened their mouths and prophesied, and then
    recovering from the possession, have sat up and stared, and asked where
    they were, and what they had been doing. Indeed, it may be that this was
    the condition of the working of art in the very dawn of human life, for
    this, no doubt, is the explanation of that old equation in which bards,
    magicians, seers, prophets, and madmen ranked all together as men who
    spoke and worked miracles, things unintelligible to the "common sense,"
    to the understanding which regulates and arranges the affairs of the
    common life. All these were alike men of the mountains, men who withdrew
    from the camp, and went apart into high solitary places, into the lonely
    wilderness, into the forest, and in such retirements and cells they
    uttered the voices that came to them, speaking words that were
    unintelligible to themselves.
    
    On the other hand there may have been artists in whom the two persons
    have been happily reconciled, who have not only the "gift of tongues"
    but also the gift of the interpretation of tongues. Even these, I think,
    are always "possessed," ecstatic, rapt from their common nature at the
    moment of inspiration, but afterwards, when the magic song is done, they
    awake and return and remember, and understand, in a measure at least,
    the meaning of their prophecies. They never wholly understand, they are
    never able to express in rational terms the _whole_ force of the
    message, for the good reason that the language of the soul infinitely
    transcends the language of the understanding; because art is, indeed,
    the sole channel by which the highest and purest truth can reach us. You
    may, perhaps, succeed in giving a Boer "some notion" of a Greek chorus
    through the medium of the "Taal," but it would be vain to dream of
    translating almost perfect beauty into that poor medium, framed for the
    temporary and corporal necessities of rough and illiterate farmers. And
    so, however well an artist or those who appreciate his work may
    "understand" his meaning, they do but "understand" a little; since the
    tongue of art has many words which have no rendering in the speech of
    the understanding.
    
    Here, then, is another form of our text which enables us to separate art
    from artifice, literature from reading matter. Artifice is explicable;
    you remember that someone has said Thackeray was simply the ordinary
    clubman _plus_ genius and a style. We must correct his phrases: but if
    you substitute an "immense talent of observation" for genius, and a
    "great gift of expression" for style, I think the definition admirable.
    Thackeray, in short, is the clubman of heightened faculties; he differs
    not in quiddity but in quality and quantity from his neighbour at the
    window; he looks more closely than Tom Eaves, and he can give you the
    result of his inspection in better phrases and with a better system, but
    he looks at the same things from the same standpoint, and you and I can
    admire his work and be amused and delighted by it, but we have no sense
    of miracle, of transcendent vision and achievement. We simply see a man
    who does the things that we do, but does them with a far greater
    dexterity: you may watch an acrobat with an immense admiration, but you
    recognise that you, too, are potentially an acrobat, that with a little
    training you, too, could hang by the heels, though not with such grace,
    nor for so long a time.
    
    But art is always miraculous. In its origin, in its working, in its
    results it is beyond and above explanation, and the artist's
    unconsciousness is only one phase of its infinite mysteries.
    
    
    
    
    VI
    
    
    I am afraid that at our last conversation I rather spoke to you "as if
    you were a public meeting." Not precisely in that manner, perhaps, since
    no public meeting that I can imagine would have stood me for a moment,
    but I fear that I was what is called "high-flown." And yet how can one
    avoid that reproach? Look here: let us suppose an examination paper, and
    the following questions set.
    
    1. Explain, in rational terms, the "Quest of the Holy Graal." State
    whether in your opinion such a vessel ever existed, and if you think it
    did not, justify your pleasure in reading the account of the search for
    it.
    
    2. Explain, logically, your delight in colour. State, in terms that
    Voltaire would have understood, the meaning of the phrase, "the beauty
    of line."
    
    3. What do you mean by the word "music"? Give the rational explanation
    of Bach's Fugues, showing them to be as (1) true as Biology and (2)
    useful as Applied Mechanics.
    
    4. Estimate the value of Westminster Abbey in the Avoirdupois measure.
    
    5. "The light that never was on land or sea." What light?
    
    6. "Faery lands forlorn." Draw a map of the district in question,
    putting in principal towns, and naming exports.
    
    7. Show that, "heaven lies about us in our infancy" must mean "wholesome
    maternal influences surround us in our childhood."
    
    You say that is all nonsense? that one cannot express art of any kind in
    the terms of rationalism? Well, I agree with you that it _is_ nonsense;
    that the tables of weights and measures give no æsthetic guide to the
    value of Westminster Abbey; but if we agree on this I am afraid that we
    must be content to be called high-flown. Having once for all settled
    that "common sense" has nothing to do with literary art, we must be, I
    suppose, uncommon, and (apparently) nonsensical if we want to talk about
    it to any profit. That is what it comes to, after all. If literature be
    a kind of dignified reporting, in which the reporter is at liberty to
    invent some incidents and leave out others, and to arrange all in the
    order that pleases him best; then, let us have as much "common sense"
    and "rationalism" as you please, and the more the better; but if
    literature is a mysterious ecstasy, the withdrawal from all common and
    ordinary conditions--well, I suppose, we had better be mystics when we
    discuss the subject, and frankly confess that with its first principles
    logic has nothing to do. I suppose that there are only two parties in
    the world: the Rationalists and the Mystics, and one's vote on
    literature goes with one's party. One might leave the matter there, and
    amiably agree to differ with the other side, but I, personally, have the
    ferocity to insist, that my side, the mystical, is wholly right, and the
    other, the rationalist, wholly wrong, and moreover I shall be so
    indecent as to prove the truth of my position. But, I have done so, and
    with that "Examination Paper" I just read out to you. For if rationalism
    be the truth, then all literature, all that both sides agree in thinking
    the finest literature is simple lunacy, and all the world of the arts
    must go into the region of mania. Take the lowest, the simplest
    instance. Here is a knife with a wooden handle, and the handle has
    certain curious carved designs on it, which do _not_ enable it to be
    held better. Why is this knife better, more to be valued, than that
    other knife, which is not decorated at all? It does not cut better; it
    does not justify its existence and purpose as a knife more than the
    other; where is its superiority? Because I find pleasure in seeing those
    designs? But _why_ do I find any pleasure in ornament? What is the
    rationalistic justification for that pleasure? By logical definition a
    knife is an instrument for cutting, and nothing else; the plain cuts as
    well as the ornate; _why_ then are you sorry if you lose the one, while
    you don't care twopence for the loss of the other? You have at last to
    answer that you have a joy which you cannot in any way define in the
    purely decorative pattern; and with that answer the whole system of
    rationalism topples over. Rationalism may say to you: Either give a
    definite reason for going to Mass, or leave off going. You have only to
    answer: Your command is based on the premiss that one should do nothing
    without being able to give a definite reason for it. But I can give no
    definite reason for liking--the Odyssey or a curiously carved knife--and
    yet you confess that I am right in liking these things. Then I have
    proved the contradictory of your premiss, as you have admitted that
    there are things that one may do without being able to give a definite
    reason for doing them: _ergo_, I shall not neglect the "parson's bell."
    
    Of course, all this is altogether outside of my business; but I confess
    I am fond of carrying things to their limits. You remember how poor S.
    T. C. used to talk, humbly and yet proudly, of "my system," though I am
    afraid "my system," never emerged from the state of fragments and
    _disjecta membra_. And I too, though I have only broken morsels and
    ruinous stones to show for the splendid outlines and indicated arches of
    Coleridge, still like to follow up an argument whithersoever it will
    lead me, regardless of consequences; and this, I am sure, should count
    for righteousness with our friends the rationalists. I love to start a
    _sorites_, something as follows: I admire that odd but beautiful little
    decorative scheme on the seventeenth century chest, and therefore, I
    think poetry, as poetry, finer than prose, as prose. Hence I approve of
    "Ritualism" in the service of the church, and from the same premiss I
    draw the conclusion that Keats was a poet and that Pope was not. Pope
    not being a poet, it follows that to "intone" is in every way better
    than to "read" the Liturgy and the Offices, and "reading" the service
    being wrong, you will easily infer that I dislike Mr Frith's pictures.
    And after learning that I do not care for the "Derby Day," you will
    scarcely require my opinion as to the (theoretical) righteousness of the
    first Reform Bill, and from my attitude towards Lord John Russell's
    measure, you can, of course, guess my opinion on the respective merits
    of the French and English languages as literary instruments. And French
    being vastly inferior to English, it necessarily follows that the
    English Reformation was a great (though perhaps unavoidable) misfortune.
    Hence, you see, admiring certain lines cut in an old oaken box, I am led
    by the strictest logic to dislike the religious policy of Edward VI.,
    with all the other consequences in order; and on the other hand if I saw
    no sense in that rude ornament I should be an Atheist, or at the
    mildest, an attendant at Pleasant Sunday Afternoons, with George Eliot
    for my favourite reading.
    
    Yes, I like my theories to "work through," and I confess that my belief
    in the truth of "my system" is very much strengthened by the fact that
    it does "work through," that it seems to me justified by the facts of
    life. I mean that the premiss which enables me to declare Keats to be a
    poet and Pope not to be a poet does really enable me to pronounce
    democracy to be a bad system in theory; and the premiss baldly stated is
    simply this: that logic does not cover life, or in other words, that
    life cannot be judged by the rules of logic, of common sense.
    
    But yet I am using logic all the time, you say? Certainly, but I am
    using it in its right place, to do the work for which it is competent.
    If I say that a scythe is not exactly the instrument for performing a
    surgical operation, I am not therefore bound to have my meadow mown with
    a bistoury? A microscope is good and a telescope is good, but it is the
    microscope that one uses in bacteriology. You know, don't you, that ever
    since that unhappy Reformation of ours people have been talking nonsense
    about the Aristotelian logic, and fumbling, in the most grotesque
    manner, for some "new" logic. Our great false prophet Bacon (a wretch
    infinitely more guilty than Hobbes) began it in England with his "Novum
    Organum"; and if you wish to really estimate "educated" folly, to touch
    the bottom of the incredible depths to which a man of information may
    sink, read Macaulay's comparison of the "old" philosophy and the "new"
    philosophy. The essayist says that the "old" philosophy was no good,
    because it never led up to the steam-engine and the telegraph post.
    Isn't it almost humiliating to think that we have to acknowledge
    ourselves of the same genus as that "brilliant" Macaulay? But if I told
    you that the Greek Alphabet was no good because it has never grilled a
    single steak you would probably get uneasy and make for the door, and if
    you were charitable you would tell the landlady that I ought to be
    "taken care of." But such a remark as that is no whit more lunatic than
    Macaulay's "comparison" between philosophy, properly so called, and
    physical science applied to utilitarian purposes. Well, all the
    portentous stuff that has been written about logic is nonsense of
    exactly the same kind. The scholastic logic, people said, won't discover
    the truth. That is perfectly true, but then the scholastic logic was not
    intended to discover truth. It will draw conclusions from truths already
    discovered, from premisses granted, but it wont make premisses any more
    than a scythe will make grass. And, it is, curiously enough, the very
    class of people who despise the formal logic, who insist on your giving
    logical reasons for actions and emotions which are altogether outside
    the jurisdiction of logic. With one breath they say: Aristotle is
    useless, because the "Organon" could never have led men to discover the
    stomach-pump; and with the next breath they ask you what you mean by
    admiring the "Ode on a Grecian Urn" if you can't give any logical reason
    for your admiration. Your religion doesn't rest on a logical foundation,
    they say. But does anything of any consequence rest on a logical
    foundation? Can you reduce the "Morte d'Arthur" into valid syllogisms in
    _Barbara_, can you "disprove" Salisbury Cathedral by the aid of
    _Celarent_. What is the "rational" explanation of our wonder and joy at
    the vision of the hills? Are a great symphony, the swell and triumph of
    the organ, the voices of the choristers, to be tested by the process of
    the understanding? But perhaps I am misjudging the people who ask these
    questions. When they say that logic does not discover truth, they
    doubtless mean by logic that formal analysis of the ratiocinative
    process that is rightly so called; but I am inclined to think that when
    they condemn religious or artistic emotions because they are
    "illogical," they mean by "illogical" that which does not conduce to the
    ease and comfort of the digestive apparatus or the money-making faculty.
    They are terrible fellows, you know, some of these persons. For example,
    I asked, with a tone of undue triumph, I am afraid, for the "reason why"
    we experience awe and delight in the presence of the hills. But in
    certain quarters my problem would be very quickly solved. I should be
    told, more in sorrow than in anger, that my emotion at the sight of
    certain shapes of earth was due to the fact that hill air was highly
    ozonised, and that the human race had acquired an instinctive pleasure
    in breathing it, greatly to its digestive profit. And if I tried to turn
    the tables by declaring that I experienced an equal, though a different
    delight in the spectacle of a desolate, smoking marsh, where a red sun
    sinks from a world of shivering reeds, I suppose I should hear that some
    remote ancestor of mine had found in some such place "pterodactyls
    plentiful and strong on the wing." And if I like the woods, it was
    because a monkey sat at the root of my family tree, and if I love an
    ancient garden it is because I am "second cousin to the worm."
    
    There: I confess it is difficult to keep one's temper with these people,
    but one must try to do so. Do you remember how Trunnion's marriage was
    delayed? The bridegroom set out bravely with his retinue for the
    parish-church, where the bride waited a whole half hour--in vain. A
    messenger was sent who saw:
    
    "The whole troop disposed in a long field, crossing the road obliquely,
    and headed by the bridegroom and his friend Hatchway, who finding
    himself hindered by a hedge from proceeding farther in the same
    direction, fired a pistol and stood over to the other side, making an
    obtuse angle with the line of his former course; and the rest of the
    squadron followed his example, keeping always in the rear of each other
    like a flight of wild geese.
    
    "Surprised at this strange method of journeying, the messenger came up
    ... and desired he would proceed with more expedition. To this message
    Mr Trunnion replied, 'Hark ye, brother, don't you see we make all
    possible speed? Go back, and tell those who sent you, that the wind has
    shifted since we weighed anchor, and that we are obliged to make short
    trips in tacking, by reason of the narrowness of the channel; and that,
    as we lie within six points of the wind, they must make some allowance
    for variation and leeway.' 'Lord, sir!' said the valet, 'what occasion
    have you to go zig-zag in that manner? Do but clap spurs to your horses,
    and ride straight forward, and I'll engage you shall be at the church
    porch in less than a quarter of an hour.' 'What! right in the wind's
    eye?' answered the commander. 'Ahey! brother, where did you learn your
    navigation?'"
    
    You see Commodore Trunnion's "logic" was perfect, only it was the logic
    of seamanship and not of riding to church on horseback. There are a good
    many people at the present day who are quite unable to get to church in
    time, for "reasons" as valid as Trunnion's; and when I hear of "the
    scientific basis of literature" I am always a little reminded of those
    scarecrows straggling in short tacks from one side of the lane to the
    other on their way to the wedding. The moral is, you know, that they
    didn't get there.
    
    I tackled a materialist once on very similar lines. He began by saying
    that time and thought devoted to religion (they never see that art and
    religion stand or fall together, religion being the foundation of the fine
    arts) were an utter waste of time as they only diverted us from
    consideration of the present world, which we ought to study to the utmost;
    and he went on to praise some saying of Confucius on the folly of
    troubling about the future things. Then I went for him. He had to admit
    that agriculture is good, and I pointed out to him that England was
    changed from a savage wilderness into a pleasant garden by the monastic
    houses. He agreed that to found and endow hospitals and alms-houses was
    not precisely a waste of time, and I showed him that such institutions
    were begun by the religion of the past and carried on by the religion of
    the present. Then he allowed, in response to my Socratic question, that
    painting was something, and I demonstrated that all painting arose from
    the religious impulse, that the greatest paintings in the world were meant
    to adorn churches. Then he admitted the value of architecture, and he got
    the Parthenon, all the mediæval cathedrals, and the wonderful mound
    temples of Ceylon right at his head. He granted me that travel civilised,
    and I rubbed in the pilgrimage; he confessed that he liked to read the
    Latin and Greek classics--sometimes--and he received from me information
    as to the monastic scriptorium, and its part in the preservation of the
    old literature. As for the blessedness of forming one's character on the
    teaching of Confucius; there happened to be an article in the morning's
    paper on the Mandarin class! Well, my rationalist hadn't anything to say
    to it at all, with the exception of some vague remark that the Romans made
    roads, which, considering the state of England in the sixth century, was
    about as helpful as the somewhat similar remark of Mr F's. Aunt--that
    there are milestones on the Dover Road. I told him that the only Roman
    civilisation which contributed to the making of our country was that
    brought over by St Austin; and he had to allow that his statement that
    religion was a waste of time, an elaborate form of idleness, was, to put
    it mildly, not proven. Then he said kindly but firmly that religion wasn't
    rational, and I used up most of the arguments that I have used to-night; I
    mean, I showed him that it is good to paint pictures, to write poems, to
    devise romances, and to compose symphonies, and that it is also good to
    meditate and enjoy all these things. Hence, he was forced to admit, that
    his suppressed premiss had been disproved, and that he must no longer
    say: "that which is not rational is absurd."
    
    And then, I think, the fun really began. I carried the war into the very
    camp of the enemy; that is, into actual, observable life, into the every
    day world of fact and experience. You talk about "reason," I said, and I
    presume you won't mind if I substitute, occasionally, "common sense" for
    reason, as I think that in your phraseology the two terms are very
    fairly equated. Very well, then, don't you think that there is a good
    deal of common sense in many of the actions of animals? Take the case of
    the small birds who mob an owl all day, in order that their enemy may be
    kept awake, and so unable to hoot at night. Take the case of the ants,
    who milk the aphides, and go slave-hunting. Take the bees, who rise to
    an emergency, and remedy, with singular contrivance, the threatened lack
    of a queen. Take the dog, who brought a wounded fellow to the hospital
    where he had been cured. All these are instances of common sense, aren't
    they, as rational as the telegram "Sell Cobras at once"? Very good;
    animals, then, have a plentiful supply of reason, and not of a mere
    mechanical reason, but of reason that can rise to the height of
    unforeseen cases, and remedy unexpected evils. When the experimenter
    tilted the bees' house to one side, so that the equilibrium was in
    danger, a sufficient number of bees climbed up, and placed themselves on
    the other side so that they constituted a balance; here there was no
    mechanism, but a calculated and rational contrivance. Animals, then,
    have reason and its effect artifice; the adaptation of means to secure
    ends. But, then, how about instinct? By what motion does the swallow
    make her nest in spring? Can the bee demonstrate the advantages of the
    hexagon cell? Does the fly, laying its eggs, here and there, in this or
    in that according to its kind, in meat or in dung, or in the crevices of
    a wall, rationally foresee that it is providing for the future grub its
    only possible food? No; but then animals, even, perform "irrational"
    actions; though they have common sense they do things which must be
    troublesome to them, at some instance, which is not common sense. But if
    a bluebottle lays her eggs in my beef, and knows not why, perhaps I, a
    man, may sing the _Sanctus_, and pray that I may be joined _cum angelis
    et archangelis, cum thronis et dominationbus, Cumque omni militiâ
    cælestis exercitus_.
    
    And consider our own human life; the great _coups_ of war, commerce,
    diplomacy, of all the conduct of life, are often, or usually, the result
    of "intuitions," that is of irrational and inexplicable mental
    processes, which elude all analysis. If the knowledge, the successful
    and triumphant knowledge of men and affairs and strategy were a
    "rational" product; then, indeed, Carlyle's dictum were true, and each
    one of us were, at choice, a man of genius in diplomacy, or business, or
    battle. We know that it is not so, and that no man by taking thought can
    make himself, say, a Stonewall Jackson. And we have all heard of the
    "woman's reason"--"I don't know why I am sure that x = a, but I am
    sure"--and this extremely irrational process often corresponds with the
    truth. So, I finished up, your "reason" far from being the despot of the
    world, turns out to be a humble, though useful, deputy-assistant
    councillor-general, and is by no means a prerogative force, even in
    affairs of common, everyday existence. Why, "reason," alone and
    unassisted, won't enable you to make a decent living by selling ribbons
    and laces, and you have been trying to make me accept its dictation in
    the highest affairs of the soul. You have been appealing from the
    King's Majesty in Council to the Magistrates of Little Pedlington in
    Petty Sessions assembled!
    
    Then my rationalist made a point. You know, he said, that some men seem
    to have an almost miraculous skill in solving mathematical problems:
    would you, therefore, give up teaching the ordinary arithmetic? I was
    not alarmed; I pointed out that the analogy was not quite perfect. The
    case, I said, was this. A certain number of "problems" were,
    confessedly, beyond the jurisdiction of the "ordinary arithmetic"
    altogether, but offered no difficulties to the "lightning calculator,"
    who obtained results that were demonstratively correct, and I therefore
    thought it well to trust to him in all problems of a similar character,
    even though the "ordinary arithmetic," confessedly incompetent, assured
    me that his answers were wholly unreliable--a case of a schoolboy, well
    on in Colenso, scouting the Binomial Theorem because one couldn't prove
    it by Practice or the Rule of Three. I left then, unanswered, and I
    suppose my friend passed the rest of the evening in showing that
    Salisbury Cathedral was "opposed" to the facts of Biology, and that
    Sisters of Charity are to be classed with criminal lunatics.
    
    But, you know, I was the real lunatic. You would not have "argued" with
    me if I _had_ disparaged the Greek alphabet, because it never grilled a
    single steak; I hinted the course you would probably have pursued if I
    had chanced to make such an alarming remark. And why should I argue with
    the sect of Macaulay, with the tribe which utters such stuff as this:
    
    "Assuredly if the tree which Socrates planted and Plato watered is to be
    judged of by its flowers and leaves, it is the noblest of trees. But if
    we take the homely test of Bacon--if we judge the tree by its
    _fruits_--our opinion of it may be less favourable. When we sum up the
    useful truths which we owe to that philosophy, to what do they
    amount.... But when we look for something more--for something which adds
    to the comfort or alleviates the calamities of the human race--we are
    forced to own ourselves disappointed."
    
    No; there is, really, nothing to be said. If the Learned Pig found voice
    and articulate speech and expressed his scorn of the poet's art, since
    it added nothing to the pleasures of the wash-tub, we might wonder but
    we should not argue; and it were idle to contend with a Laughing
    Jackass, contemptuously amused by the chanting of the cathedral choir.
    
    And, perhaps, you are wondering what all this talk of mine has to do
    with our main subject--literature? But don't you see that all the while
    I have merely been reiterating our old conclusions in a new phraseology?
    I may have appeared to you to be the last of the Cavaliers, gallantly
    contending for the rights of Holy Church, but, in reality, I have been
    showing, at every step, that Jane Austen's works are not literature.
    Yes, but it is so. If the science of life, if philosophy, consisted of a
    series of mathematical propositions, capable of rational demonstration,
    then, "Pride and Prejudice" would be the highest pinnacle of the
    literary art; but if not, but oh! if we, being wondrous, journey through
    a wonderful world, if all our joys are from above, from the other world
    where the Shadowy Companion walks, then no mere making of the likeness
    of the external shape will be our art, no veracious document will be our
    truth; but to us, initiated, the Symbol will be offered, and we shall
    take the Sign and adore, beneath the outward and perhaps unlovely
    accidents, the very Presence and eternal indwelling of God.
    
    We have tracked Ecstasy by many strange paths, in divers strange
    disguises, but I think that now, and only now, we have discovered its
    full and perfect definition. For Artifice is of Time, but Art is of
    Eternity.
    
    
    
    
    APPENDIX
    
    
    Poe was not altogether right in saying that the object of poetry was
    Beauty as distinguished from Truth. I don't for a moment suppose that
    his meaning was amiss, but I hardly like his expression of it. I should
    contend, on the other hand, that poetry ~kat' exochên~, and literature,
    generally, are the sole media by which the very highest truth can be
    conveyed. Poe, no doubt, meant to state a proposition which is true and
    self-evident--that poetry has nothing to do with scientific truth, or
    facts, or information of any kind, and I say that that proposition is
    self-evident, because we have already seen that in literature, facts as
    facts, have no existence at all. They are only "words" in the language
    of literary art, and are used as symbols of something else. That A. is
    in love with B. is a "scientific truth," a fact; but if it be not also a
    symbol, it has no literary existence whatever; and this of course is
    what Poe wished to say--literature is not a matter of information.
    
    But I doubt, after all, whether Poe had quite grasped the theory of
    literature, of all the arts. You remember that he says that he yields to
    no man in his love of the truth; and unless he meant the highest truth
    the statement is almost nonsensical. No one, I should imagine, surely
    not Poe, would express his enthusiasm for facts as facts, would adore
    correct information in the abstract. You remember what Rossetti
    said--that he neither knew nor cared whether the sun went round the
    earth or the earth round the sun--and so far as art is concerned this
    is, no doubt, the expression of the true faith, which, from what we know
    of Poe, would be his faith also. We should therefore conclude that by
    truth he meant philosophical truth, the highest truth, the essential
    truth as distinguished from the accidental, the universal as
    distinguished from the particular. Yet in the next breath he contrasts
    this Truth with Beauty, being clearly under the impression that they
    were two different things. Of course he was completely mistaken. In the
    last analysis it is entirely true that "Beauty is Truth and Truth
    Beauty": they are one and the same entity seen from different points of
    view. You will see how this fits in with all we have been saying about
    literature lately: how we can if we please put our test of literature
    into yet another phraseology. For instance: "Vanity Fair" is
    information, while "Pickwick" is Truth; the one tells you a number of
    facts about Becky Sharpe and other people, while the other symbolises
    certain eternal and essential elements in human nature by means of
    incidents. And, as I said, it is doubtful whether truth in this, its
    highest and its real significance, can be adequately expressed in any
    other way. All the profound verities which have been revealed to man
    have come to him under the guise of myths and symbols--such as the myth
    of Dionysus--and truth in the form of a mathematical demonstration or a
    "rational" statement is a contradiction in terms. Yet note the profound
    vice of language; we are obliged to use the same word to imply things
    which are separated by an immeasurable gulf. It is "true" that Mrs
    Stickings sent away Ethelberta to-night (you imparted that interesting
    fact, and I rely on your testimony), and the "Don Quixote" is "true":
    that is, it conveys to us by means of symbols the verities of our own
    nature.
    
    But Poe had not grasped the essential distinction between literature
    and "literature." He thought that poetry alone should be beautiful, or
    as we should say, ecstatic; he did not see that the qualities which make
    poetry to be what it is must also be present in prose if it is to be
    something more than "reading-matter." Poetry of course is literature in
    its purest state; it is, as I think I once said, _almost_ the soul
    without the body; at its highest it is _almost_ pure art unmixed with
    the alloy of artifice. And to carry on the analysis, the finest form of
    poetry is necessarily the lyrical. Where you get the element of
    narrative, you are apt also to get the element of prose; there have to
    be passages linking the raptures together, and these will, probably or
    indeed necessarily, run on lower levels.
    
    Of course primitive man had moods in which rapture seemed to embrace
    everything, to invest every detail of existence with its own singular
    and inexplicable glory. A meal by the seashore, the dry wood flaming and
    crackling on the sand, the roasting goat's flesh, the honey-sweet wine,
    dark and almost as glorious as the sea itself--a mere dinner of
    half-savages, one might think it, but it too seems to have its solemnity
    and its inner meaning. I believe this element in the early poetry has
    often been noticed; people have wondered at the _naïve_ delight with
    which the writers describe the work of man's hands, and they are, I
    think, inclined to account for it on the ground that then everything was
    new. This might pass, perhaps, since as you, no doubt, perceive,
    "everything new" means "everything unknown" (that which is known is no
    longer new), but I hardly think that the explanation can stand in its
    present form. I am not at all up in the theories which assign this or
    that age to the appearance of man on the earth, but I presume that on
    the gentlest and most antiquated computation man must have long known
    the world before Homer wrote; so one scarcely sees that human skill and
    art, the knack of making things and the gift of adorning them, could
    have been novelties, or in any sense, "things unknown." I repeat I know
    nothing or next to nothing about these dates in anthropology, but one
    has heard something about the neolithic age, and the palæolithic age,
    about the very early man who scratched the rude likeness of a reindeer
    on the brute's own bone, and so there hardly seems room for this theory
    of novelty. And besides, as we have seen, the rapture is universal or
    all but universal; it colours the whole of life, including the meal by
    the seashore; and there, we see, there was no possibility of invention
    or sense of newness. No; the theory is tempting, and it would fall in
    perfectly, as I daresay you see, with all that we have concluded about
    literature, but I really think that it must be definitely abandoned. No;
    it seems to me that primitive man, Homeric man, mediæval man, man,
    indeed, almost to our own day when the School Board (and other things)
    have got hold of him, had such an unconscious but all-pervading,
    all-influencing conviction that he was a wonderful being, descended of a
    wonderful ancestry, and surrounded by mysteries of all kinds, that even
    the smallest details of his life partook of the ruling ecstasy; he was
    so sure that he was miraculous that it seemed that no part of his life
    could escape from the miracle, so that to him every meal became a
    sacrament.
    
    It is the attitude of the primitive man, of the real man, of the child,
    always and everywhere; it may be briefly summed up in the phrase: things
    are because they are wonderful. This, of course, is the atmosphere in
    which poets ought to live, and in which poetry should be produced.
    Formerly it was natural to all men or almost all; now, perhaps, it has
    to be regained by a conscious effort; and the difficulty of the effort,
    the impossibility of sustaining it for long, explain the supremacy of
    lyrical poetry. If you lived in a world that could regard a common meal
    as a sacrament, you could be supreme in narrative poetry; but, that
    atmosphere wanting, we have to be content for the most part with the
    lyric, with the simple incantation, without any description of the
    circumstance or occasion.
    
    Yet prose, though it yields in much to the world, must still keep the
    same ideal before it as poetry. I say, distinctly, that the only
    essential, defining difference between the two is to be sought in the
    "numbering" of poetry, in the fact that art, in its intensest raptures,
    in its most truly "natural" moment, desires and obtains the strictest
    and most formal laws. It is, I suppose, immaterial what these laws are,
    rhyme, assonance, accents, feet, alliteration, all testify to the
    important and essential rule that freedom is chiefly free when it is
    most bound and bounded by restrictions which _we_ should call
    artificial, which are, in truth, in the highest sense, natural. And
    this, I am sure, is the only possible distinction that can be
    established between such a book as the "Odyssey" and such a book as the
    "Morte d'Arthur." Neither is "prosaic" in the common sense of the word;
    each is "poetical"; but the Greek book is poetry because it is numbered,
    and the English is prose because it lacks number. Of course there are
    difficult cases; hybrids, as there always are, whatever laws one may lay
    down.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    That word "natural" is another of the many traps that language sets us.
    I think that its real meaning has become almost reversed. Take the
    average man to church, and ask him his opinion of the "intoning," and in
    nine cases out of ten he will say that it may be pretty, but that it is
    very unnatural. He means, of course, that speaking is natural, and that
    singing--"numerosity" of tone--is not natural, is, in a word,
    artificial. He is utterly wrong. It is artificial to speak in the
    ordinary manner, while the priests' chant, and every chant are purely
    natural. For the proof of this you have only to read a little--a very
    little--about primitive, or "natural" peoples, or, more simply, to
    listen to children at play. You will always find that where convention
    has not cast out nature, some kind of "sing-song," some sort of chant is
    the entirely natural utterance of man in his most fervent, that is, his
    most natural moments. Listen to half-a-dozen children (children, you
    must remember, are all "primitives" and therefore natural) playing some
    game, learning their lesson at school. Their voices are pretty sure to
    fall into a very rude, but a distinctly measured, chant. The Greek drama
    was intoned, the Koran is intoned, the Welsh preacher of to-day at the
    impassioned height of eloquence begins to chant, the Persian
    passion-plays are recited in a sing-song. Nay, but listen only to our
    great tragic actor. Quite unconsciously, I am sure, he has elaborated
    for himself a distinctly musical and measured utterance, so that a
    skilful musician, provided with scored paper, could note Irving's
    delivery of many passages, as if it were music. The Chinese language, I
    am told, depends largely on the tonal variations which distinguish the
    meaning of one word from that of another; you will find the same thing
    in the Norwegian; and the Jewish "cantillation," which is "sing-song" in
    a very simple form, bears witness to the truth--that "speaking" is
    acquired, conventional, and artificial, while "singing" is natural. All
    this would be perfectly clear in itself, would require no demonstration
    of any kind, if it were not for the fact that we have, somehow or other,
    got into the way of making the very impudent assumption that man is only
    natural when he is doing business on the Stock-Exchange or reading
    leading-articles. It seems almost too nonsensical an assumption to put
    into words, but I really do believe that "at the back of our heads"
    there is a sort of vague, floating idea that there never were any real
    men at all till the period of the first Reform Bill, and I suppose that
    before very long Lord John Russell will be pushed back into the region
    of myth, and the foundation of the School Board will be the era of true
    humanity. I say, this sounds too ridiculous, but examine yourself and
    see whether you don't dimly believe that before the advent of trousers
    the whole world was really "play-acting," that existence in the days of
    laced coats was, in a way, a kind of phantasmagoria, and that a man who
    wore chain-mail was hardly a man. I believe it really is so, and you
    will find the same nonsense influencing religious opinion. Take your
    average Protestant, and I am much mistaken if you do not discover that
    he believes some grotesque preacher, in his greasy black suit, mouthing
    platitudes at his conventicle to be somehow more "natural" than the
    priest, clad in the mystical robes of his office, chanting Mass at the
    altar. But in literature--why this perversion of the word influences the
    whole of criticism. Jane Austen, we say, is natural, and Edgar Allan Poe
    is unnatural, or as it is sometimes expressed, inhuman. Of course, if
    you wish for the truth, the proposition must be reversed, unless you are
    willing to believe that a Company Prospectus is, somehow, more natural
    and more human than, say, Tennyson's "Fatima." If you think that the
    real man is the stomach, there is, of course, an end of the discussion;
    but then we should have to admit that all the greatest artists of the
    world were maniacs. But you see clearly, don't you, that all these
    questions as to what we shall get for dinner, and whom shall we meet at
    dinner, and in what order shall we go into dinner, and how shall we
    behave at dinner, are in no sense natural, since they are all so purely
    temporary, since they will be answered by one age in a manner that will
    seem wholly "unnatural" to the next. That, I think, is truly natural
    which is unchanging, which belongs to men always, at all times, and in
    all ages. In this sense, ecstasy is natural to man, and it finds
    expression in the arts, in poetry, in romance, in singing, in melody, in
    dancing, in painting, in architecture. Many animals have sufficient
    artifice to shelter themselves from the weather, no animal has
    architecture, or the art of beauty in building; many animals, or all
    animals, have the faculty of communicating with one another by means of
    signs, but man alone has the art of language.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    Has it ever struck you while I have been talking of ecstasy in books,
    that it is nearly always a question of degree, of more or less? I think
    I indicated as much while I was talking about "Pickwick"; I showed how
    the ecstatic conception had been alloyed with much baser matter, in
    other words that there was much in "Pickwick" that was by no means
    literature. And, I daresay, though I am not sure, that if you were to go
    through your Meredith you might succeed in finding some passages and
    sentences which are literature, and for all I know there may be hints
    of rapture between the lines of "Pride and Prejudice." Still, we do not
    call a man poet on the strength of a single line.
    
    But sometimes one is confronted with books which are really very
    difficult to judge, and this sometimes happens because the ecstasy, the
    true literary feeling, supposing it to be present, is present not here
    or there, not in a phrase or in a particular passage, but throughout, in
    a very weak solution, if one may borrow the phraseology of physical
    science. We read such books, and are puzzled, feeling that, somehow,
    they are literature, only we can't say why, since on the face of it they
    seem only to be entertaining reading. Do you know that I can conceive
    many people who would find something of this difficulty in Mark Twain's
    "Huckleberry Finn"? Here you have a tale of the rude America of forty or
    fifty years ago, of a Mississippi village, full of the most ordinary
    people, of a boy and a negro who "run away." I don't think anyone with
    the slightest perception of literature could read it without
    experiencing extraordinary delight, but I can imagine many people would
    be a good deal puzzled to justify the pleasure they had received. The
    "stuff" of the book is so very common and commonplace, isn't it, it
    seems so frankly a rough bit of recollection drawn up from the author's
    boyish days with jottings added from the time when he was a pilot on one
    of the river-boats--it is all so apparently devoid of "literary" feeling
    that I am sure many a reader must have felt greatly ashamed of his huge
    enjoyment. To me "Huckleberry Finn" is not a very difficult case. That
    flight by night down the great unknown, rolling river, between the dim
    marshy lands and the high "bluffs" of the other shore comes in my mind
    well under the great "Odyssey" class; it has, indeed, the old,
    unquenchable joy of wandering into the unknown in a more acute degree
    than "Pickwick," which, as we have seen, is to be reckoned under the
    same heading. In a word it is pure romance, and you will note that the
    story is told by a boy, and that by this method a larger element of
    wonder is secured, for even in this absurd age children are allowed to
    be amazed at the spectacle of the world. In the mouth of a man the tale
    would necessarily have lost somewhat of its "strangeness," since partly
    from affectation, partly from vicious training, partly from the
    absorption of the "getting-on" process, grown-up people have largely
    succeeded in quenching the sense of mystery which should be their
    principal delight. You have only to read the average book of travels to
    see how this affectation (or perversion of the soul) has deprived the
    seeing being of his sight. Dip into a book--say a book on China--and you
    will probably find that Pekin streets are dusty in summer and muddy in
    winter, and that the author caught cold through imprudent bathing. So it
    is well for us that Mark Twain put his story in the mouth of an
    "infant," who is frankly at liberty to express his sense of the marvels
    of the world. Later, there is an introduction of the "literary" feeling;
    those chapters about Jim's "Evasion" are very Cervantic in their
    artifice and method, but, to my thinking, they have lost the spirit,
    though they preserve the body. They are most amusing reading, but they
    are burlesque and nothing more than burlesque; and from them one can
    almost imagine what "Don Quixote" would have been if it had been written
    by a very clever man, by an artificer who was not an artist. But the
    earlier chapters are wonderfully fine, and I think that it would be
    difficult to find a more successful rendering of the old "wandering"
    theme with modern language.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    But there is another writer who is much more difficult to account for--I
    mean Miss Wilkins. I confess I find her tales delightful, and I often
    read them, but as you know I am not content to rest on my own pleasure
    in literary criticism. We are no longer talking of the great
    masterpieces, of the gigantic achievements of such men as Homer,
    Sophocles, Rabelais, Cervantes; we agreed that when we spoke of these
    great, enduring miracles of art, it was best to lay aside all question
    of liking or not liking, of reading often or reading seldom. But when
    one comes to modern days, to books which have yet to prove their merit
    by the test of their endurance, it is pardonable if one is sometimes a
    little confused, if one fails to discriminate at once between the merely
    interesting and the really artistic. I may be so delighted with a book
    for reasons that have nothing to do with art, that, by an unconscious
    trick of the mind, I persuade myself that I am reading literature while
    there is only reading-matter. And at one time I was inclined to think
    that I had "confused" Miss Wilkins in this manner. For, on the surface,
    you have in her books merely village tales of New Englanders, tales
    often sentimental, often trivial enough, and sometimes, it would seem,
    of hardly more than local interest. Hardly can one conceive the
    possibility of any ecstasy in these pleasant stories; for they deal,
    ostentatiously, with the surface of things, with a breed of Englishmen
    whose chief pride it was to hide away and smother all those passions and
    emotions which are the peculiar mark of man as man.
    
    Yet, I believe that I can justify my love of Miss Wilkins's work on a
    higher ground than that of mere liking. In the first place I agree with
    Mr T. P. O'Connor, who pointed out very well that the passion does come
    through the reserve, and occasionally in the most volcanic manner. He
    selects a scene from "Pembroke," in which the young people play at some
    dancing game called "Copenhagen," and Mr O'Connor shows that though the
    boys and girls of Pembroke knew nothing of it, they were really animated
    by the spirit of the Bacchanals, that the fire and glow of passion, of
    the youthful ecstasy, burst through all the hard crusts of Calvinism
    and New England reserve. And we have agreed that if a writer can make
    passion for us, if he can create the image of the eternal human ecstasy,
    we have agreed that in such a case the writer is an artist.
    
    But I think that there are other things, more subtle, more delicately
    hinted things in Miss Wilkins's tales; or rather I should say that they
    are all pervaded and filled with an emotion, which I can hardly think
    that the writer has realised. Well, I find it difficult to express
    exactly what I mean, but I think that the whole impression which one
    receives from these tales is one of loneliness, of isolation. Compare
    Miss Wilkins with Jane Austen, the New England stories with "Pride and
    Prejudice." You might imagine, at first, that in one case as in the
    other there is a sense of retirement, of separation from the world, that
    Miss Austen's heroines are as remote from the great streams and
    whirlpools of life as any "Jane Field" or Charlotte of Massachusetts.
    But in reality this is not so. The people in the English novels are in
    no sense remote; they are merely dull; they cannot be remote, indeed,
    since they are not human beings at all but merely the representatives of
    certain superficial manners and tricks of manner which were common in
    the rural England of ninety years ago. "Remoteness" is an affection of
    the soul, and wicker-figures, dressed up in the clothes of a period,
    cannot have any such affections predicated of them; and consequently
    though Emma or Elizabeth may appear very quaint to us from the contrast
    between the manners of the 'tens and the 'nineties, they cannot be
    remote. But that does seem to me the quality of those books of Miss
    Wilkins's; the people appear to be very far off from the world, to live
    in an isolated sphere, and each one lives his own life, and dwells apart
    with his own soul, and in spite of all the trivial chatter and
    circumstance of the village one feels that each is a human being moved
    by eminently human affections.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    It seems to me that one of the most important functions of literature is
    to seize the really fine flavours of life and to preserve them, as it
    were, in permanent form. When we were talking about "Huckleberry Finn,"
    for example, I remember that I spoke of it as the story of a boy who "runs
    away." But what a curious magic there is in these words "runs away."
    Doesn't it, when you come to examine the phrase, exhale the very essence
    and spirit of romance? Some time ago I reminded you that the essential
    thing is concealed under all manner of grotesque and unseemly forms, that
    one can detect a veritable human passion under the cry of the news-boy,
    shouting, "All the winners!" So I think that phrase, "run away," carries
    to us its meaning and significance. For, after all, what did all the
    heroes of romance do but "run away"? They left the region of the known,
    the familiar fields or the familiar shores, and adventured out in the
    great waste of the unexplored, into the forest or upon the sea. Here,
    perhaps, you have the true interpretation of the phrase "divine
    discontent," for surely only that is divine which revolts from the
    commonness of the common life, which is conscious of things beyond, of
    better things, of a world which transcends all daily experience. I said
    once, I think, that the English passion for trading goes very well with
    the supremacy of English poetry, since poetry and shop-keeping are but
    different expressions of the one idea; and here again you find
    confirmation of the theory in that very marked English characteristic--the
    desire of wandering, of "going on and on" in the manner of a knight
    errant or a fairy tale hero. Of course, in practice, this really divine
    impulse is corrupted by all kinds of earthly, secondary motions; and just
    as the love of a venture which is at the root of trade often or always
    ends in a very vulgar wish to make money and more money and to set up a
    brougham and confound the Smiths, so the great joy of exploration, of
    running away from the mapped and charted land has for its issues the
    "development of markets," the "progress of civilisation," the profitable
    sale of poison, and all manner of base and blackguardly manoeuvres. But,
    of course, one expects all this; it is the inevitable mixture of the lower
    with the higher which characterises all our human ways. Still the higher
    motive dwells within us--I suspect, indeed, that if it were not for the
    higher the lower could hardly flourish--and so when you hear that a boy
    has run away to sea or elsewhere I wish you to think kindly of him as a
    survival of the most primitive and important human passions. Yes, I think
    I am right in saying that the lower things of humanity only flourish in
    consequence of the existence of the higher. Take the French nation, for
    example. It is infinitely more bent on gain for the mere sake of gain
    than the English; it is ready to work harder, to give more time, to live
    more unpleasantly, to eat less and to drink less than the English; and all
    in the pursuit of money. Rationally, in short, the French should be
    infinitely better men of business than the English; and yet we know that
    this is not so, that the English is, _par excellence_, the business
    nation. Seriously, I believe, that this is so because the French are
    money-grubbers and nothing more, because they hate a "risk" of any kind,
    because they abhor any kind of mercantile venturing into the unknown. In
    other words, they engage in money-making simply for the sake of making
    money: they have no joy of the hazard, they will never deserve the title
    of "merchant adventurers," and, _therefore_, they remain in truth a nation
    of shopkeepers and of second-rate shopkeepers. Sir, a man of acute
    intelligence would, in the seventeenth century, have deduced the future
    state of French and English commerce, of French and English colonization
    from a comparison between Shakespeare and Racine. I have no doubt that the
    Phoenicians were shopkeepers of the French kind, and hence their
    extinction, their shadowy survival merely in the history of their
    conquerors.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    You think the Roman Empire a formidable objection to my theory, because
    Roman literature and Roman art show, in general, so little of the
    imaginative, adventurous faculty? I think the objection _is_ formidable,
    but I believe that it can be redargued, as Dominie Sampson used to say.
    The Roman Empire was such a purely military settlement, wasn't it? it
    was, if one may say so, a garrisoning of the world, not in any way a
    real colonizing in the Greek and the English sense. And in the second
    place, do you know that I have grave doubts whether we know very much of
    the Roman spirit from the Roman literature. How far into the English
    character would the works of the excellent Dr. Johnson carry us? One
    hardly finds Chaucer, the Elizabethans, the Cavalier poets, Keats or
    Wordsworth in "Rasselas" and "The Rambler," and I have always suspected
    that Latin literature was in a great measure "Johnsonized," periwigged,
    hidden and perverted by the irresistible flood of Greek culture. It may
    be a paradox, but I have a very strong conviction that the Missal and
    the Breviary tell us more about the true Latin character than Cicero and
    Horace. But we must be thankful that in the sixteenth and early
    seventeenth centuries England stood aloof from the continent of Europe,
    and that when it did borrow it transformed and transmuted so that the
    original entirely lost its foreign character. I always think that change
    of Madame de Querouaille into Madam Carewell such a wonderful instance
    of our nationalism--our transforming force! If it had been otherwise, if
    we had grovelled before the literature of France or Spain or Italy, as
    Rome grovelled before the literature of Greece--well, perhaps, English
    literature would have meant "Chevy Chace" and a few old ballads, and the
    eighteenth century! I hate the Reformation, but perhaps it saved our
    literature, simply by isolating the nation.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    I claimed, I think, literary merit for Miss Wilkins because her books
    give out an impression of loneliness. I think that is so, but I should
    like to point out that "loneliness" is merely another synonym for that
    one property which makes the difference between real literature and
    reading-matter. If you look into the French literature of the last two
    hundred years and complain of its elegant nothingness, of its wholly
    secondary character, I would point out that it is second-rate because it
    is the expression, not of the lonely human soul, like a star, dwelling
    apart, but of society, of the _ruelles_, of the _salon_, of polite
    company, of the _café_ and the _boulevard_. I am not making an
    accusation, I am adopting the terms of the eminent M. de Brunetière, who
    tells us, I think, that French literature is beautiful because it is
    firstly sociable, and secondly because it is a kind of a long "talk to
    ladies." I hardly think that I need go into the merits of the question;
    you and I, I take it, are convinced of the vast immeasurable inferiority
    of Racine to Shakespeare (with these two names one sums up the whole
    debate), but I am quite sure that M. de Brunetière has given the true
    reason of the French literature being on the distinctly low level. It is
    always Thackeray, it is always Pope, it is always Jane Austen; it is, in
    our sense of the word, not literature at all, though, to be sure, its
    artifice is often of the most exquisite description. Of course I do not
    speak of the ultimate reason--that is to be sought, I presume, in the
    mental constitution of the nation--but when one reads M. de Brunetière's
    account of the formation of modern French letters, and notes his
    insistance on the social element as the chief factor, one may be pretty
    sure that this social factor is responsible for the pleasant nullities
    which we all know. You may feel pretty certain, I think, that real
    literature has always been produced by men who have preserved a certain
    loneliness of soul, if not of body; the masterpieces are not generated
    by that pleasant and witty traffic of the drawing-rooms, but by the
    silence of the eternal hills. Remember; we have settled that literature
    is the expression of the "standing out," of the withdrawal of the soul,
    it is the endeavour of every age to return to the first age, to an age,
    if you like, of savages, when a man crept away to the rocks or to the
    forests that he might utter, all alone, the secrets of his own soul.
    
    So this is my plea for Miss Wilkins. I think that she has indicated this
    condition of "ecstasis"; she has painted a society, indeed, but a
    society in which each man stands apart, responsible only for himself and
    to himself, conscious only of himself and his God. You will note this,
    if you read her carefully, you will see how this doctrine of awful,
    individual loneliness prevails so far that it is carried into the
    necessary and ordinary transactions of social life, often with results
    that are very absurd. Many of the people in her stories are so
    absolutely convinced of their "loneliness," so certain that there are
    only two persons in the whole universe--each man and his God--that they
    do not shrink from transgressing and flouting all the social orders and
    regulations, in spite of their very strong and social instinct drawing
    them in the opposite direction. You remember the man who vowed that
    under certain circumstances he would sit on the meeting-house steps
    every Sunday? He kept his vow--for ten years I think--and he kept it in
    spite of his profound horror of ridicule, of doing what other people
    didn't do, in spite of his own happiness; but he kept it because he
    realised his "loneliness," because he saw quite clearly that he must
    stand or fall by his own word and his own promise, and that the opinions
    of others could be of no possible importance to him. The instance is
    ludicrous, even to the verge of farce, and yet I call it a witness to
    the everlasting truth that, at last, each man must stand or fall alone,
    and that if he would stand, he must, to a certain extent, live alone
    with his own soul. It is from this mood of lonely reverie and ecstasy
    that literature proceeds, and I think that the sense of all this is
    diffused throughout Miss Wilkins's New England stories.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    You ask me for a new test--or rather for a new expression of the one
    test--that separates literature from the mass of stuff which is not
    literature. I will give you a test that will startle you; literature is
    the expression, through the æsthetic medium of words, of the dogmas of
    the Catholic Church, and that which in any way is out of harmony with
    these dogmas is not literature. Yes, it is really so; but not exactly in
    the sense which you suppose. No literal compliance with Christianity is
    needed, no, nor even an acquaintance with the doctrines of Christianity.
    The Greeks, celebrating the festivals of Dionysus, Cervantes recounting
    the fooleries of Don Quixote, Dickens measuring Mr Pickwick's glasses of
    cold punch, Rabelais with his thirsty Pantagruel were all sufficiently
    Catholic from our point of view, and the cultus of Aphrodite is merely
    a symbol misunderstood and possibly corrupted, and if you can describe
    an initiatory dance of savages in the proper manner, I shall call you a
    good Catholic. You say that "Robert Elsmere" is not literature, and you
    are perfectly right, but I hope you don't condemn it because it contains
    arguments directed against the Catholic Faith? These, from our own
    standpoint, are simply nothing at all, not reckoning either way. We pass
    them over, just as we should pass over a passage on quadratic equations
    pleasantly interpolated by an author into the body of his romance.
    The conscious opinions of a writer are simply not worth twopence in
    the court of literature; who cares to enquire into the theology of
    Keats? But when we find not only the consciousness but also the
    subconsciousness permeated by the impression that man is a logical,
    "rationalistic" creature and nothing more, when the total impression of
    the human being gathered from the book is of a simply demonstrating and
    demonstrable animal; then, we may be perfectly assured that we have not
    to deal with literature. It is the subconsciousness, remember, alone
    that matters; and (to put it again theologically) you will find that
    books which are not literature proceed from ignorance of the
    Sacramental System. Thackeray was an unconscious heretic, while George
    Eliot was a conscious one, but each was ignorant of the meaning of
    Sacramentalism, and so, making allowance for the fact that the one was a
    clever man, while the other was a dull, industrious woman, you have from
    each a view of life that is substantially the same, and entirely false.
    Each was profoundly convinced that there _are_ milestones on the Dover
    Road, and each, in his several way, was so intent on the truth of this
    proposition (and it _is_ a perfectly true one) that the secret of the
    scenery and the secret of Canterbury Cathedral are altogether to seek in
    their books. Certainly the gentleman is a delightful companion, and the
    milestones seem few indeed while we are on the way, while with the other
    guide we feel like a girls' school, compelled to listen to the "now,
    young ladies" and the "lessons" which every object on the road suggests.
    Still, the total view is much the same, the same in genus if not in
    species, and you may add Flaubert to your companions on the road and you
    will be in the same case. But read a chapter of "Don Quixote"; you will
    not be aware of the existence of the milestones, since your gaze is
    fixed on the mystery of the woods, and you are a pilgrim to the blissful
    shrine beyond. Don't imagine that you can improve your literary chances
    by subscribing the Catechism or the Decrees of the Council of Trent. No;
    I can give you no such short and easy plan for excelling; but I tell you
    that unless you have assimilated the final dogmas--the eternal
    truths--upon which those things rest, consciously if you please, but
    subconsciously of necessity, you can never write literature, however
    clever and amusing you may be. Think of it, and you will see that from
    the literary standpoint, Catholic dogma is merely the witness, under a
    special symbolism, of the enduring facts of human nature and the
    universe; it is merely the voice which tells us distinctly that man is
    _not_ the creature of the drawing-room and the Stock Exchange, but a
    lonely awful soul confronted by the Source of all Souls, and you will
    realise that to make literature it is necessary to be, at all events,
    subconsciously Catholic.
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    Have you noticed how many of the greatest writers, so far from desiring
    that compliment of "fidelity to life" do their best to get away from
    life, to make their books, in ordinary phraseology, "unreal?" I do not
    know whether anybody has compared the facts before or made the only
    possible inference from them; but you remember how Rabelais professes to
    derive his book from a little mouldy manuscript, found in a tomb, how
    Cervantes, beginning in _propria persona authoris_, breaks off and
    discovers the true history of "Don Quixote" in the Arabic Manuscript of
    Cid Hamet Benengeli, how Hawthorne prologises with the custom-house at
    Salem, and lights, in an old lumber-room, on the documents telling him
    the history of the "Scarlet Letter." "Pickwick" was a transcript of the
    "Transactions" or "Papers" of the Pickwick Club, and Tennyson's "Morte
    D'Arthur" shelters itself, in the same way, behind the personality of an
    imaginary writer. There is a very profound significance in all this, and
    you find a trace of the same instinct in the Greek Tragedies where the
    final scene, the peripeteia, is not shown on the stage, but described by
    a "messenger." The fact is that the true artist, so far from being the
    imitator of life, endures some of his severest struggles in endeavouring
    to get away from life, and until he can do this he knows that his labour
    is all in vain. It would be amusing to trace all the various devices
    which have been used to secure this effect of separation, of withdrawal
    from the common track of common things. I have just pointed out one, the
    hiding of the author, as it were, behind a mask, and in the Greek Play
    the analogous talking of what has happened in place of visibly showing
    it, but there must be many more. From this instinct I imagine arises the
    historical novel in all its forms, you make your story remote by placing
    it far back in time, by the exhibition of strange dresses and unfamiliar
    manners. Or again you may get virtually the same effect by using the
    remoteness of space, by playing on the theme "far, far away" which
    really calls up a very similar emotion to that produced by the other
    theme of "long, long ago," or "once on a time," as the fairy tale has
    it. Briefly we may say that all "strangeness" of incident, or plot, or
    style makes for this one end; and of course you see that all this is
    only the repetition of our old text in another form. It is, perhaps,
    hardly necessary to give the caution that, on the principle of
    _corruptio optimi_, there is nothing more melancholy than the book which
    has the body of fine literature without the soul, which uses literary
    methods without understanding. You needn't ask for proofs of that
    proposition; our memories are aghast with recollections of futile
    "historical novels," of the terrific school of the "two horsemen," and
    every Christmas brings its huge budget of those dreadful "boys' books,"
    which carry commonplace to the very ends of the earth, and occasionally
    penetrate to the stars. And in style, too, what can be more depressing
    than the style which is meant to be "strange" and is only flatulent? In
    many cases of course such books as I have alluded to are mere survivals
    of tradition, conventions of bookmaking which bear witness to the fact
    that pirates and treasure-hoards were once symbols of wonder, and the
    extravagancies of style are probably to be accounted for in the same
    way. At some remote period it may, possibly, have been effective to call
    the sun, "the glorious orb," and even now some minds may be made to
    realise the strangeness of great flights of birds by the phrase "the
    feathered Zingari of the air"; but if one is a little sophisticated one
    feels the pathos and the futility of such efforts. The writer has felt
    and experienced the wonder of things--the beauty of the sun and the
    hieroglyphic mystery of the figures that the birds make in the air--and
    he feels, quite rightly, that to describe wonders one must suggest
    wonder by words. Unfortunately, he breaks down at this point, and falls
    back on unhappy phrases that give the very opposite impression to that
    which he wishes to excite. Here you have the whole history of "poetic
    diction." The instinct is in itself an entirely right one, and I need
    hardly say that the masters--those who have the secret--can use archaic
    forms, obsolete constructions, conventional phrases even, with
    miraculous effect. But the beginner would do well to be wary of these
    things, and to turn his face resolutely away from "flowery meads" and
    all the family of inversions. How is one to know when such phrases may
    be used? If I could give you the answer to that question I should be
    also giving you the secret of making literature, and from all our talks
    I expect you have gathered this much at all events--that the art of
    literature, with all the arts, is quite incommunicable. Many kinds of
    artifice, even, are unteachable--I could not write or be taught to write
    one of those George Eliot novels that I have been abusing with such
    hearty good will--but art is by its very definition quite without the
    jurisdiction of the schools, and the realm of the reasoning process,
    since art is a miracle, superior to the laws.
    
    
      PRINTED BY
      TURNBULL AND SPEARS,
      EDINBURGH
    
    
           *       *       *       *       *
    
    
    TRANSCRIBER'S NOTES
    
    The variant spellings "bookcase" and "book-case", "bookmaking" and
    "book-making", "milk punch" and "milk-punch", "subconsciousness" and
    "sub-consciousness", "Morte D'Arthur" and "Morte d'Arthur" are all used in
    this text.
    
    The four Greek quotations are indicated by tildes ~like this~. Words in
    italics are indicated by underscores _like this_.
    
    There is no consistency in the use of italics, single quotes or double
    quotes. For example _Vanity Fair_, "Vanity Fair" and 'Vanity Fair' all
    appear.
    
    OE and oe ligatures have been replaced by OE and oe respectively.
    
    The spellings "gurgoyles" (p. 132), "insistance" (p. 196), "ecstasis"
    (p. 196) and "extravagancies" (p. 204) have been left unchanged.
    
    The following amendments have been made:
    
    1) Full stop (period) added after "Sophocles" on p. 53, after "runs away"
    on p. 189 and after "Dr" in "Dr Johnson" on p. 193.
    
    2) Full stop replaced by question mark after "unreal" on p. 214.
    
    A Table of Contents has been added.
    
    </text>